<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="abi">
<title>Application Model (Application Binary Interface)</title>

<preface>
<p>This chapter gathers information about the ABI <ndash/> software binary interface.
This includes questions about what the runtime and program model are,
what are the sections and segments of the program, how the program finds its private data,
what are the available addressing methods, what are the accepted agreements on the relationships between the procedures
and register preservation, relocation types and object file formats are described.
</p>

<p>Depending on the execution environment (hardware capabilities of the target architecture, type of operating system)
program models are (in order of the history of the emergence and growth of universality):
</p>

<ul>
<li>Absolute <ndash/> MS DOS for Intel X86</li>
<li>Relative <ndash/>?</li>
<li>Segmented (with protection based on access windows to a single address space) <ndash/>?</li>
<li>Implicitly segmented based on a single global address space <ndash/> IBM AIX for POWER, HP-UX for HP PA-RISC</li>
<li>Virtual memory and multiple isolated address spaces (MAS) <ndash/> Windows, Unix, Linux</li>
<li>Virtual memory and uniform global address space (SAS) <ndash/> IBM AS/400, Palm OS, Mungi, Opal</li>
</ul>

<p>For the <archname/> system, a combined SAS/MAS environment with implicit segmentation was selected,
when each segment can be configured as SAS or MAS.</p>

</preface>

<section id="abi_program_sections">
<title>Sections and segments</title>

<p>The compiler divides the different parts of the generated object code and data into different sections.
During linking, when combining object files, sections with the same name come together
and consolidate, getting an output file with one instance of each type of section.
These sections of the output file are further grouped into several segments,
which are processed by the loader as indivisible units.
</p>

<p>The purpose of sections is to allow the compiler to generate separate pieces of code and data,
which can be combined with other similar parts from other object files at the build stage.
This makes it possible to achieve link locality, and confidence in the correct addressability of the contents of these sections.
The most important section attributes are the type of access to the section pages;
all data in one section shares the same minimum set of permissions.
</p>

<p>The purpose of the segments is to allow the linker to group sections into fewer program units.
Each segment has unique addressing methods for it, and sections of one segment are addressed in the same way.
The compiler may make assumptions that any two objects in the same segment have a fixed offset
relative to each other when the program is executed, but cannot assume the same for two objects in different segments.</p>

<p>The runtime architecture also defines some additional segments,
which do not get their contents directly from the compiled object file.
These segments are the <ndash/> heap, stack, and shared memory segments <ndash/>
are created at program startup time or dynamically at runtime.</p>

<table>
<caption>Standard scheme of a software module (using ELF format as an example)</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>segment</th>
<th>section</th>
<th>type of program</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td rowspan="22">TEXT</td><td>header</td><td>all</td><td>file header</td></tr>
<tr><td>sectab</td><td>all</td><td>section heading table</td></tr>
<tr><td>shstrtab</td><td>all</td><td>section names</td></tr>
<tr><td>.dynamic</td><td>shared</td><td>Dynamic linking information Header</td></tr>
<tr><td>.liblist</td><td>shared</td><td>A list of the names of the required spherical libraries</td></tr>
<tr><td>.rel.dyn</td><td>shared</td><td>Relocation for DATA process data</td></tr>
<tr><td>.rel.tdata</td><td>shared</td><td>Relocation for TDATA thread data</td></tr>
<tr><td>.conflict</td><td>shared</td><td>Additional dynamic linking information</td></tr>
<tr><td>.msym</td><td>shared</td><td>Additional dynamic linking symbol table</td></tr>
<tr><td>.dynstr</td><td>shared</td><td>Name of linking external functions</td></tr>
<tr><td>.dynsym</td><td>shared</td><td>Link table of external functions</td></tr>
<tr><td>.hash</td><td>shared</td><td>Hash table for quick search in the export table</td></tr>
<tr><td>.rconst</td><td>all</td><td>Read-only constants (no configuration)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.rodata</td><td>all</td><td>Immutable global data (setting at first boot into the system)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.lita</td><td>nonshared</td><td>Literal address pool section</td></tr>
<tr><td>.lit</td><td>all</td><td>Literals (Literal pool section)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.tlsinit</td><td>all</td><td>Initial copy of TDATA data</td></tr>
<tr><td>.pdata</td><td>all</td><td>Exception procedure table</td></tr>
<tr><td>.text</td><td>all</td><td>Main program code (not corrected during loading, it is possible to configure it at the first load in the system)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.init</td><td>all</td><td>Section of the program initialization code</td></tr>
<tr><td>.fini</td><td>all</td><td>Program Termination Code Section</td></tr>
<tr><td>.comment</td><td>all</td><td>Comment Section</td></tr>

<tr><td rowspan="5">TEXT but not downloadable</td><td>rsrc</td><td>all</td><td>Compiled resources</td></tr>
<tr><td>line</td><td>all</td><td>Debug information</td></tr>
<tr><td>debug</td><td>all</td><td>Debug information</td></tr>
<tr><td>unwind</td><td>all</td><td>Table for stack rollback after exceptional situations</td></tr>
<tr><td>unwind_info</td><td>all</td><td>Blocks of information to roll back the stack after exceptional situations</td></tr>

<tr><td rowspan = "6">DATA</td><td>.data</td><td>all</td><td>Initialized private process data (setting at boot)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.xdata</td><td>all</td><td>Exception scope table</td></tr>
<tr><td>.sdata</td><td>all</td><td>Near-address small data initialized private process data (setting at boot)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.got</td><td>shared</td><td>GOT table (Global offset table) for references to DATA variables of other modules</td></tr>
<tr><td>.sbss</td><td>all</td><td>Small-address (small bss) uninitialized private process data</td></tr>
<tr><td>.bss</td><td>all</td><td>Uninitialized private process data</td></tr>

<tr><td rowspan = "5">TDATA</td><td>.tdata</td><td>all</td><td>Initialized thread local data (setting at boot)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.tsdata</td><td>all</td><td>Near-address small data initialized thread local data (setting at boot)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.tgot</td><td>shared</td><td>Module GOT table for the thread (links to TDATA variables of other modules)</td></tr>
<tr><td>.tsbss</td><td>all</td><td>addressable small (bss) uninitialized thread local data</td></tr>
<tr><td>.tbss</td><td>all</td><td>Uninitialized thread local data</td></tr>

</tbody></table>

<p>A program in the <archname/> architecture consists of a main program module,
dynamically loaded libraries (the same program modules), stacks of the main and other threads, several heaps.
Each program module consists of four types of sections.
</p>

<p>The TEXT segment is shared by all processes in the system and is read-only and executable.
The addressing within the segment is relative to the instruction pointer.
Its CODE section contains program code.
Its RODATA section contains immutable data, placed after the CODE section.
</p>

<p>The DATA segment contains private process data. The segment is read-write.
The addressing within the segment is relative to the instruction pointer.
The DATA segment of the main software module, in addition to its private data,
contains a table of base addresses for all DATA segments of dynamically loaded libraries.
</p>

<p>The TDATA segment contains private process data. The segment is read-write.
The segment after creation is <strong>unknown</strong> distance from everyone else
segments and is addressed relative to the selected base register <reg>tp</reg>.
The TDATA segment of the main software module, in addition to its private data,
contains a table of base addresses for all segments of TDATA dynamically loaded libraries.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "abi_data_model">
<title>Data model</title>

<p>There are several data models for binding fundamental integer scalar data types from programming languages to architectural data types.</p>

<table>
<caption>Dimensions of fundamental types</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th rowspan="2" width="20%">Data model</th>
<th colspan="4">Architectural types</th>
</tr><tr>
<th width="20%">1-byte</th>
<th width="20%">2-byte</th>
<th width="20%">4-byte</th>
<th width="20%">8-byte</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>ILP16</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type>, <type>int</type>, <type>long int</type>, near pointer</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>LP32</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type>, <type>int</type>, near pointer</td>
<td><type>long int</type>, far pointer</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>ILP32</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type></td>
<td><type>int</type>, <type>long int</type>, pointer</td>
<td><type>long long int</type></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>LLP64</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type></td>
<td><type>int</type>, <type>long int</type></td>
<td><type>long long int</type>, pointer</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>LP64</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type></td>
<td><type>int</type></td>
<td><type>long int</type>, <type>long long int</type>, pointer</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>ILP64</td>
<td><type>char</type></td>
<td><type>short int</type></td>
<td><type>wchar_t</type></td>
<td><type>int</type>, <type>long int</type>, <type>long long int</type>, pointer</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The ILP16 variant was used by very ancient 16-bit systems, LP32 uses MS DOS,
ILP32 use all 32-bit systems, LLP64 chose Microsoft for Windows-64,
LP64 is selected for Linux-64 and most other 64-bit Unix systems, ILP64 is used in some versions of Unix systems.
</p>

<p>The choice between LLP64, LP64, and ILP64 is determined by different criteria.
If you need support (without recompiling) an existing array of 32-bit software when migrating to 64-bit systems, then LLP64 is the best choice.
The disadvantage of <ndash/> alteration for 64 bits requires a deep modernization of the program.
If you want the existing code array to take advantage of 64-bit addressing with minimal code rework, then ILP64 is a good fit.
The disadvantage of a <ndash/> superficial code upgrade leads to memory overrun where 64 bits are not needed.
If you follow a balanced approach between the complexity of converting to 64-bit systems and the need to support existing 32-bit programs, then choose LP64.
ILP64 was chosen for <archname/>, with the addition of the new fundamental type <type>long char</type> to describe four-byte numbers (<type>wchar_t</type>).
</p>

<table>
<caption>Binding to fundamental types</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Size and alignment</th>
<th>Machine Type</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>signed char</td><td>1 (1)</td><td>signed byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned char</td><td>1 (1)</td><td>unsigned byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>char</td><td>1 (1)</td><td>byte, the sign depends on the compiler</td></tr>
<tr><td>bool</td><td>1 (1)</td><td>unsigned byte, 0 or 1</td></tr>
<tr><td>[signed] short int</td><td>2 (2)</td><td>signed 2-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned short int</td><td>2 (2)</td><td>unsigned 2-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>[signed] long char</td><td>4 (4)</td><td>signed 4-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long char</td><td>4 (4)</td><td>unsigned 4-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>enum</td><td>1,2,4,8</td><td>depends on the range of values   </td></tr>
<tr><td>[signed] int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>signed 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>unsigned 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>[signed] long int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>signed 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>unsigned 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>[signed] long long int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>signed 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long long int</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>unsigned 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>data pointer: type *</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>unsigned 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>function pointer: type (*) ()</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>unsigned 8-byte</td></tr>
<tr><td>float</td><td>4 (4)</td><td>IEEE single</td></tr>
<tr><td>double</td><td>8 (8)</td><td>IEEE double</td></tr>
<tr><td>long double</td><td>16 (16)</td><td>IEEE quadruple</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Aggregate data types (structures <ndash/> <type>struct</type>, <type>class</type> <ndash/> and arrays)
and unions (<type>union</type>) are aligned with their most strictly aligned component.
The size of any object, including aggregates and associations, is always a multiple of the alignment of the object.
An array uses the same alignment as its elements.
Structure and join objects may require inserts to meet size and alignment restrictions.
The content of any padding is undefined.
</p>

<ul>
<li>The structure or union as a whole must be aligned on the same byte boundary as its most strictly aligned field.</li>
<li>Each field is assigned the smallest available offset with a suitable alignment.
This may require internal inserts between the fields, depending on the previous field.</li>
<li>If necessary, the size of the structure must be increased to be a multiple of the alignment.
This may require end insertion, depending on the last member.</li>
</ul>

<p>C structures and associations can contain bit fields that define integer objects with a specified number of bits.
The table shows the permissible values   of bit fields for each base type, and the corresponding limits.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Binding of bit fields to fundamental types</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Field Width W</th>
<th>Limits</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>char, signed char</td><td>1-8</td><td rowspan="6"> <minus/> 2 <sup>W<minus/>1</sup> <hellip/> 2 <sup>W<minus/>1</sup> <minus/> 1</td></tr>
<tr><td>long char, signed long char</td><td>1-16</td></tr>
<tr><td>short, signed short, enum</td><td>1-32</td></tr>
<tr><td>int, signed int</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
<tr><td>long, signed long</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
<tr><td>long long, signed long long</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned char</td><td>1-8</td> <td rowspan="6"> 0 <hellip/> 2<sup>W</sup> <minus/> 1</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long char</td><td>1-16</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned short</td><td>1-32</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned int</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
<tr><td>unsigned long long</td><td>1-64</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Bit fields whose base type (with the exception of enumerated types) is represented without an explicit <type> signed</type> or <type> unsigned</type> definition,
considered as unsigned (fixme).
Bit fields of enumerated types are considered to be signed, unless an unsigned type is needed to represent all constants from the enumeration type.
Bit fields obey the same size and alignment rules as other fields in a structure or union, with the following additions:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Bit fields are placed from right to left (from the least significant bit to the most significant) for little-endian,
and from left to right (from the most significant bit to the least significant) for big-endian.</li>
<li>The bit field must completely fit in the machine type corresponding to its declared type.
For example, a <type>short</type> bitfield should never cross the <type>mem4</type> border.</li>
<li>Bit fields can share a machine-type cell with other fields of <type>struct</type> / <type>union</type>,
including other bit fields and even non-bit fields (<type>enum</type> types?).
Of course, each field of the structure occupies its own part of the machine type.</li>
<li>Unnamed bitfield types do not affect structure alignment or union.
Unnamed zero-length bit fields force alignment of subsequent fields to a border corresponding to the size of the bit field.</li>
</ul>

<p>Bit fields like <type>int</type> and <type>long</type> (<type>signed</type> and <type>unsigned</type>) are usually packed denser,
the smaller the base types (less restrictions on crossing the boundaries of the base type).
You can use bit fields and types <type>char</type> and <type>short</type>,
to force placement within those types, but <type>int</type> is generally more efficient.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "abi_reserved_registers">
<title>Reserved registers</title>

<p>Although all 128 general-purpose registers are physically equal
(except for the difference between global and rotate registers, and some other differences)
the software binary interface reserves several general purpose registers for its (special) purposes.
Unlike real special purpose registers, these registers are <em>special</em> only in the sense that
that the program is obliged to use them only in an authorized way.
The choice of numbers for these registers is (almost) arbitrary and not part of the architecture.
</p>

<p>The initial contents of the registers <reg>sp</reg>, <reg>tp</reg>
set by the loader at the start of the process / thread and should be changed by the program only according to ABI rules.
The contents of the reg <reg>sp</reg> should always correctly display the state of the stack
and be aligned with the strictest boundary for the base types <ndash/> 16 bytes.
Register <reg>r0</reg> must contain the return info when the procedure is called.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Dedicated General Purpose Registers</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Register</th>
<th>Content</th>
</tr>
</thead><tbody>
<tr>
<td><reg>r0</reg></td><td><regname>link pointer</regname> <ndash/> return address from the procedure.
The called procedure receives the return address in the first register of the new frame of the local registers, register <reg>r0</reg>.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><reg>sp</reg></td><td><regname>stack pointer</regname> <ndash/> pointer to the top of the stack.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><reg>tp</reg></td><td> <regname>thread pointer</regname> <ndash/>
pointer to the beginning of thread local data for the main (static) module.
Used by load/store instructions and <mim>lda_n</mim> only inside the main module.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

</section>

<section id="pic">
<title>Position independent code and GOT</title>

<p>The code segment must not contain relocations (PIC).
To create a PIC, the compiler must:
</p>

<ol>
<li>Use for all internal branches the <reg>ip</reg>-relative branches only rather than branches to absolute addresses.</li>

<li>Similarly, do not use absolute references to static data, instead use addressing with an offset relative to some standard base register.
If the code and data segments are guaranteed to be located at a known distance from each other (MAS),
then the function from the shared library can calculate the corresponding base address using <reg>ip</reg>.
Otherwise (SAS), the caller must set the base register as part of the call sequence.
</li>

<li>Use an additional level of indirection for each control transfer outside the monolithic PIC segment,
and for each call to static memory outside the corresponding data segment.
Indirectness allows you to save non-PIC target addresses in the DATA segment private for each instance of the program.
</li>
</ol>

<p>The position-independent code cannot contain absolute addresses directly in the instruction code,
but uses for addressing data and an offset code relative to the instruction counter.
A data-binding-independent code uses for code addressing the offset relative to the instruction counter,
but cannot address private data in the same way, but only relative to to the base registers.
</p>

<p>The Global Offset Table (GOT) stores absolute addresses and is part of the process's private data,
which makes addresses accessible without violating positional independence and sharing of program code.
Each program module refers to its GOT table in a position-independent manner and extracts absolute addresses from it.
So position-independent links are converted to absolute positions.
</p>

<p>Initially, the GOT contains information about relocation points (annotations for the dynamic linker).
After the system creates memory segments for the loaded object file,
the dynamic linker processes relocation points, some of which will refer to the GOT.
The dynamic linker determines the symbolic names associated with them, calculates their absolute addresses, and sets the appropriate values   in the corresponding GOT entries.
Although the absolute addresses are unknown to the link editor when it builds the object file,
but the dynamic linker knows the addresses of all memory segments and can therefore calculate the absolute addresses of the objects contained therein.
</p>

<p>If the program requires direct access to the absolute address of the object, this object will have an entry in the GOT.
Since the executable file and each shared object have separate GOTs, the address of a symbolic name may appear in several tables.
The dynamic linker processes all GOT relocations before transferring control to the process code,
which guarantees the availability of absolute addresses at runtime.
</p>

<p>Thanks to GOT, the system can select different addresses of memory segments for one shared object in different programs.
She can even choose different library addresses for different executions of the same program.
At the same time, memory segments do not change addresses after the process image is installed.
As long as the process exists, its segments are located at fixed addresses.
</p>

<p>Short summary: if the program has several data segments (private or shared),
then they are accessed indirectly through the GOT address table.
The GOT table is part of one selected <ndash/> DATA private data segment.
However, objects in the DATA segment itself can be addressed indirectly through the GOT table in DATA
(for example, if the distance of the relative displacement is too large for implementation in the instruction).
</p>

</section>

<section id = "abi_relocation">
<title>Program relocation</title>

<p>The relocation or unresolved link is a place in the code or static data,
reserved by the compiler to substitute the later calculated value <ndash/> at the stage of compilation or even later at the stage of loading,
or not containing data (field of zero bits), or containing incomplete information
(an additional term may be stored to calculate the allowed link).
Usually, a direct value is stored in the place of relocation, which is the absolute address or relative offset relative to the base address or counter of the bundles,
and used when accessing memory or address calculations.</p>

<p>There are as many <em>types of relocation</em> as there are different ways in the processor architecture of the processor to put an immediate value
in the code of the machine instruction (without taking into account the constants for the description of shifts and some other constants,
too short and therefore not used for relocation) or in the data object.
Link Editor uses these unfilled (under-calculated) line items.
at the assembly stage for embedding in the previously compiled code its information about the links in the program between individual segments, sections,
object modules and dynamically linked executable modules.</p>

<p>The compiler creates (for later use by the linker) a table of relocation (program moving) records as part of the object file.
Moving records describe how the linker (or later the loader) should modify the instruction or data field.</p>

<p>The following distinct <em>data relocation</em> types are defined for data sections in the <archname/> architecture:</p>

<ol>
<li><relocation>RELOC_WORD</relocation>. A 4-byte boundary aligned 32-bit field in any data section.
</li>
<li><relocation>RELOC_DWORD</relocation>. An 8-byte boundary aligned 64-bit field in any data section.
</li>
</ol>

<p>For code in the <archname/> architecture (according to the format of single-slot instructions and their extensions to the second slot)
The following distinct <em>code relocation</em> types are defined:</p>

<ol>
<li><relocation>RELOC_LD_IMM</relocation>.
A 28-bit signed immediate (or 64 bits for a long instruction) is embedded in the <mim>ld_imm</mim> instruction.

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="7">other</ignored>
    <jump>simm28</jump>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <reserved size = "6">0</reserved>
    <imm size = "36">simm64 (28+36)</imm>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_JUMP</relocation>.
A constant with a sign length of 28 bits (or 60 bits for a long instruction) for
<reg>ip</reg>-relative offset in the program segment <var>text</var> (or <var>rodata</var>)
embedded in <mim>call</mim>, <mim>jmp</mim> or <mim>lda_r</mim> instructions
(distance <plusmn/>2 GiB or <plusmn/>8 EiB for long instructions).

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size = "7">other</ignored>
    <jump>simm28x16</jump>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <reserved size="10">0</reserved>
    <imm size="32">simm60x16 (28+32)</imm>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_BRANCH</relocation>.
A signed 17-bit immediate (or 30-bit for a long instruction) for offset in the code segment
embedded in an instruction like <em>compare-and-branch</em> as a branch distance
(distance <formula><plusmn/>1</formula> MiB or <formula><plusmn/>8</formula> GiB for a long instruction).

<slot_table>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size = "18">other</ignored>
    <branch>simm17x16</branch>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <ignored size="29">other</ignored>
    <imm size="13">simm30x16 (17+13)</imm>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_BIN_SIMM</relocation>.
A constant with a 21-bit sign (or 63 bits for a long instruction) for
instructions <mim>ld_i8</mim>, <mim>ld_u8</mim>, <mim>add_imm_i64</mim>, <mim>subr_imm_i64</mim> and others.

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="14">other</ignored>
    <binimm>simm21</binimm>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <imm size="42">simm63 (21+42)</imm>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_BIN_UIMM</relocation>.
An unsigned constant of 21 bits (or 63 bits for a long instruction) for instructions <mim>max_imm_u32</mim>, <mim>min_imm_u64</mim>.

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="14">other</ignored>
    <binimm>uimm21</binimm>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <imm size="42">uimm63 (21+42)</imm>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_BRANCH_SIMM</relocation>.
A 11-bit signed constant (or 40-bit for a long instruction) is embedded in an instruction like <em>compare-with-constant-and-jump</em> as a constant to be compared.

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="7">other</ignored>
    <cbimm>simm11</cbimm>
    <ignored size="17">other</ignored>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <imm size="29">simm40 (11+29)</imm>
    <ignored size="13">other</ignored>
</slot></slot_table></li>

<li><relocation>RELOC_BRANCH_UIMM</relocation>.
A 11-bit unsigned constant (or 40-bit for a long instruction)
embedded in an instruction like <em>constant-compare-and-jump</em>
as a constant to be compared.

<slot_table>
<slotbits/><slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="7">other</ignored>
    <cbimm>uimm11</cbimm>
    <ignored size="17">other</ignored>
</slot></slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/><slot>
    <imm size="29">uimm40 (11+29)</imm>
    <ignored size="13">other</ignored>
</slot></slot_table></li>

</ol>

<p>Instruction-dependent basic relocation types further differ
in different ways of forming the implemented constant and conditions checked in this case.
The set of these methods depends on the program model used and additional features of the instruction set architecture.
</p>

<p>For example, the Intel X86 architecture has only one basic type of code relocation (in 32-bit mode) <ndash/> the 4-byte field as part of the instruction,
for which there are only two ways of forming the constant <ndash/>
just an absolute address for the data or <reg>ip</reg>-relative address for the code.
</p>

<p>The <archname/> system is oriented towards a position-independent code.
In addition, the special instructions <mim>lda_n</mim>, <mim>lda_r</mim>,
designed to optimize relative addressing, require special support from the linker.
Hence a large selection of possible ways of referencing an object of code or data
depending on the location of the object, the remoteness of the object from the base of relative addressing,
the presence of indirect links through the GOT table, the number of repeated calls to the same object or objects near it.
</p>

<p><def>The method of referencing an object in the place of relocation</def>
(a method of converting a symbol name into an embedded constant) is usually set in assembler
as a call to a special function when calculating the constant parameter of an instruction, or as a suffix added to the name of an object.
It should be understood that this is actually not a function call, but a mark
for the linker (hello to him from the compiler) <ndash/> exactly how to construct a relocation constant from the name of the object.
The set of relocation methods used depends on the architecture of machine instructions
(if, for example, long constants are synthesized from parts and divided between
several instructions, or several typical sizes of programs with different addressing methods are provided)
and from the selected program model (absolute code for the system kernel or user program).
The set of <archname/> assembler functions below is generally traditional for the 64-bit PIC program model
and is found (with some variations) in all 64-bit architectures: DEC Alpha, SGI MIPS, IBM PowerPC, Sun UltraSPARC, Intel Itanium.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Assembler functions to set the relocation method</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Group (scope)</th>
<th>Function (Method)</th>
<th>How, at runtime, an offset is obtained from the offset</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td rowspan="3">Absolute addresses (for data only)</td><td>symbol</td><td>symbol</td></tr>
<tr><td>expr</td><td>symbol+offset</td></tr>
<tr><td>got(symbol)</td><td>mem8[offsettee</td></tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">Private process data</td><td>pcrel (expr)</td><td>ip + offset</td></tr>
<tr><td>ltoff(expr)</td><td>mem8[ip+offsettee</td></tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">thread local data (main program)</td><td>tprel (expr)</td><td>tp + offset</td></tr>
<tr><td>@tprel@got(expr)</td><td>mem8 [tp + offset]</td></tr>
<tr><td>Private flow data (dynamic modules)</td>
<td>dtprel(expr)</td><td>mid = mem4 [gp + mid_offset] <br/> local_tp = mem8 [dtv + mid] <br/> ea = local_tp + offset</td></tr >
<tr> <td rowspan="2"> Support for <mim>lda_n</mim> instructions for all data types</td> <td> data_hi (expr)</td> <td> base + (offset <lshift/> 15)</td></tr>
<tr><td>data_lo(expr)</td><td>base+offset</td></tr>
<tr> <td rowspan="2"> Support for the <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction for all data types</td>
<td>text_hi(expr)</td><td>ip+16<times/>offset</td></tr>
<tr><td>text_lo(expr)</td><td>base+offset</td></tr>
<tr> <td rowspan="2"> Miscellaneous Functions</td>
<td>segrel(expr)</td><td>segbase+offset</td></tr>
<tr><td>secrel(expr)</td><td>secbase+offset</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>The mere mention of the <var>symbol</var> symbol means the absolute address of the <var>symbol</var> object.
The expression <var>expr</var> means a formula from the absolute address of the object and constant offset: <var>symbol + offset</var>.
Absolute addresses at runtime are not calculated and used as is.
Absolute addresses can be embedded in the instruction code only if it is an absolute program (system core, drivers).
</p>

<p>Function <function>got</function> (<var>symbol</var>) (global offset table)
means the absolute address in the GOT table for indirect access to the <var>symbol</var> object.
At the same time, this is a request to create a GOT record for the <var>symbol</var> object, if there is no such record yet.
</p>

<p>The <function>got</function> function cannot be used by itself, but only with <function>pcrel</function> or <function>tprel</function>,
e.g. like <function>@ pcrel @ got</function> (<var>expr</var>),
since the GOT table is divided in two (depending on the locality of the link objects <ndash/> process or thread)
and is part of the DATA and TDATA segments, and therefore should be addressed accordingly.
</p>

<p>The function <function>pcrel</function> (<var>expr</var>) (program counter relative) means the offset <var>offset</var> relative to the instruction counter.
The absolute address of the object is computed at run time as <formula><reg>ip</reg>+<var>offset</var></formula>.
Used to access the code and / or static data of the same module.
</p>

<p>Function <function>tprel</function> (<var>expr</var>) (thread pointer relative)
means offset <var>offset</var> relative to the base register <reg>tp</reg> when addressing the thread private data.
The absolute address of the object is calculated at runtime as <var><reg>tp</reg> + offset</var>.
The <var>expr</var> object must belong to the TDATA segment of the main module.
</p>

<p>Function <var>dtprel (expr)</var> (dynamic thread pointer relative) means the offset <var>offset</var> of the object <var>expr</var>
regarding the beginning of the thread private data of this module <var>dtv [ModID]</var>
(taken from the array <reg>dtv</reg> addressed by the register <reg>dtv</reg>).
The absolute address of the object is calculated at run time as <formula><var>dtv[ModID†+offset</var></formula>.
The <var>expr</var> object must belong to the TDATA segment of the <var>ModID</var> module itself.
</p>

<p>The function <var><function>data_lo</function>(offset)</var> describes the lower 15-bit part of the offset
<var>offset</var>: <var><function>data_lo</function>(offset) = sign_extend(offset, 15)</var>.
The offset <var>offset</var> is usually calculated for position-independent programs as <var><function>gprel</function>(expr)</var>
or <var><function>tprel</function>(expr)</var> depending on the location of the <var>expr</var> object.

Used for addressing relative to the intermediate base address, calculated earlier using the <mim>lda_n</mim> instructions.

This intermediate address can be reused for calls.
to an object or its nearest neighbors using short read / write instructions
(with offsets of minimum length <ndash/> not more than 16 bits per offset).</p>

<p>The <function>data_hi</function>(<param>offset</param>) function describes the older part of the <param>offset</param> offset:
<var><function>data_hi</function>(offset) = (offset- <function>sign_extend</function>(offset, 15)) <rshift/> 15</var>.
Used by <mim>lda_n</mim> instructions to calculate an intermediate base address before
using short read / write instructions.
These instructions calculate the absolute address no further than 16 kilobytes from the relative addressable object <var>expr</var>.
Long (over 32 kilobytes) offset <var>offset</var> relative to the base register
split into two parts <var>offset_hi</var> and <var>offset_lo</var>, so that
<var>offset = (offset_hi <lshift/> 15) + offset_lo</var>, so the younger part is <var>offset_lo</var>
always placed in a 16-bit constant with a sign, and the older part <var>offset_hi</var>
will be the argument of the <mim>lda_n</mim> instructions for calculating the intermediate base address.
</p>

<p>Objects in the TEXT segment (RODATA section with read-only data)
in a position-independent program, it should be addressed relative to the <reg>ip</reg> instruction counter.
However, with the <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction, you can get only the starting address of the 16-byte bundle,
that is, the address closest to the target is 16 bytes aligned.
The following instructions for accessing the memory should take into account the short offset (from 0 to 15 bytes long) from this starting address to the object.
</p>

<p>Function <function>text_hi</function> (<param>expr</param>)
means that part of the <reg>ip</reg>-relative offset in the segment
<segment>text</segment> used by the <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction
to calculate the absolute address closest to the object, aligned on a 16-byte boundary.
The <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction computes <reg>ip</reg>+16<times/> <function>text_hi</function>(symbol),
where <var><function>text_hi</function>(symbol)</var> is calculated by assembler as
<var>((symbol<minus/> <function>text_lo</function>(symbol)) <rshift/> 4)</var>.
The paired function <var><function>text_lo</function>(symbol)</var> describes the younger part
<reg>ip</reg> -relative offset as <var><function>sign_extend</function>(symbol, 4)</var>,
that is, the difference between the address of the object and the nearest 16-byte boundary.
This value is used for direct addressing in load/store instructions.
after calculating the intermediate address of the 16-byte bundle using the <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction.
</p>

<p>Function <function>segrel</function> (<var>expr</var>) (segment relative) describes the offset of the object <var>expr</var>
relative to the start of the segment. This relocation is for data structures,
which are placed in read-only shared segments but must contain pointers.
In this case, the relocation point and the relocation object must be located in one segment.
Applications using such relative pointers should be aware of their relativity and add the base address of the segment to them at runtime.
</p>

<p>Function <function>secrel</function> (<var>expr</var>)
(section relative) describes the offset of the <var>expr</var> object relative to the beginning of the section.
This relocation is for links from one section to another within the same segment.
</p>

<p>As a result, combining the type of relocation and the method of linking to an object, we get a complete set of all valid types of unresolved links,
which the linker should be able to handle (minus some never-seen combinations).
</p>

<table>
<caption> Types of Relocation Entries</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Group</th>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Relocation Method</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2"> absolute addressing (data only)</td>
<td>R_ADDR_WORD</td><td>sym+addend</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_ADDR_DWORD</td><td>sym+addend</td></tr> <tr>

<td rowspan="6"> relative to <reg>ip</reg></td>
<td>R_PCREL_JUMP</td> <td> pcrel (sym + addend), jump/call</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_PCREL_JUMP_EXT</td> <td> pcrel (sym + addend), jump/call</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_PCREL_BRANCH</td> <td> pcrel (sym + addend), compare-and-branch</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_PCREL_BRANCH_EXT</td> <td> pcrel (sym + addend), compare-and-branch</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_PCREL_LDA_R</td> <td> text_hi (pcrel (sym + addend), lda_r</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_PCREL_LDA_R_EXT</td> <td> text_hi (pcrel (sym + addend), lda_r.l</td></tr> <tr>

<td rowspan="2"> section-base relative</td>
<td>R_SECREL_WORD</td> <td> sym - SC + addend, .mem4</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_SECREL_DWORD</td> <td> sym - SC + addend, .mem8</td></tr> <tr>

<td rowspan="2"> segment-base relative</td>
<td>R_SEGREL_WORD</td> <td> sym - SB + addend, .mem4</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_SEGREL_DWORD</td> <td> sym - SB + addend, .mem8</td></tr> <tr>

<td rowspan="4"> base-relative</td>
<td>R_BASEREL_LDI</td> <td> L (sym - base + addend)</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_BASEREL_LDI_EXT</td> <td> L (sym - base + addend)</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_BASEREL_BINIMM</td> <td> sym - base + addend</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_BASEREL_BINIMM_EXT</td> <td> sym - base + addend</td></tr> <tr>

<td rowspan="5"> dynamic layout?</td>
<td>R_SETBASE</td> <td> Set base</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_SEGBASE</td> <td> Set SB</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_COPY</td> <td> dyn reloc, data copy</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_IPLT</td> <td> dyn reloc, imported PLT</td></tr> <tr>
<td>R_EPLT</td> <td> dyn reloc, exported PLT</td></tr>

<tr>
<td rowspan="9"> <reg>tp</reg> -relative</td>
<td>R_TPREL_WORD</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), .mem4</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_DWORD</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), .mem8</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_LDI</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), LDI</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_LDI_LONG</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), LDI</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_HI_BINIMM</td><td>data_hi(tprel(sym+addend))</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_HI_BINIMM_EXT</td><td>data_hi(tprel(sym+addend))</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_LO_BINIMM</td><td>data_lo(tprel(sym+addend))</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_BINIMM</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), load/store</td></tr>
<tr><td>R_TPREL_BINIMM_EXT</td> <td> tprel (sym + addend), load/store</td></tr>

</tbody>
</table>

<p>The assembler syntax must be consistent with the set of types of unresolved references that the linker can handle.
</p>

<p>For example, almost none of the assemblers/compilers can take into account and handle the subtraction of two addresses from the same segment as a immediate, although it is.
At the compilation stage, this subtraction is still unknown, but at the linking stage, when they can be defined,
the corresponding types of relocation are not provided in order to pose a similar task to the linker.
As a result, the compiler is forced to take these calculations to the stage of loading or executing the program.
</p>

<p>The most <quote>advanced</quote> compilation/linking systems support the ability to postpone to the link stage the unresolved links of arbitrary complexity,
if they would be reduced to a constant result.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "abi_tls">
<title>Thread local storage</title>

<p>Managing thread local storage (TLS) which is private for a thread isn't as simple as per-process private data.
TLS sections cannot simply be loaded from a file into memory and made available to the program.
Instead, multiple copies should be created (one for each thread)
and all of them must be initialized according to the primary image of the TLS section in the program file.
The creation of new threads can continue dynamically throughout the entire period of the program.</p>

<p>TLS support should avoid creating TLS data blocks if possible,
for example, using deferred memory allocation on the first request (first attempt to access TLS).
Most threads will probably never use private data of all dynamic modules at once.
Unfortunately, the mechanism of deferred memory allocation requires at least
introducing a separate functional level (layer) to control access to TLS objects, which may be too inefficient.</p>

<p>The problem is the very process of compiling TLS data and accessing it when there are many copies of it.
The TLS variable is characterized by two parameters: a reference to the TLS block of a particular dynamic module and an offset within this block.
To get the address of a variable, you need to somehow map these two parameters to the virtual address space at runtime.</p>

<p>The traditional TLS mapping approach is as follows.
One of the general registers (<reg>tp</reg> or thread pointer)
permanently stores the address of the static TLS block of data associated with the current thread.
The data block is conditionally divided into two parts:
a statically allocated single TLS data block of the main module (exe file) and the <reg>dtv</reg> vector (dynamic thread vector),
storing addresses of dynamically (possibly lazy) dedicated TLS blocks for dynamically loaded dynamic modules.
If the dynamic module is loaded into the program, then it is allocated one slot (a place to store the address) in the <reg>dtv</reg> vector.
</p>

<p>Knowing your <var>mid</var> number, the dynamic module can find the beginning of its TLS data
for the current thread in <var>dtv[mid]</var> or <formula>MEM (<reg>tp</reg> + mid + offset)</formula>,
where <var>offset</var> is the position of <reg>dtv</reg> relative to <reg>tp</reg> (usually 0).
Next, you can find the address of the variable as <formula><reg>dtv</reg>[mid] + var_offset</formula>,
where <var>var_offset</var> is the position of the variable relative to the dynamic TLS block.
</p>

<p><def>General dynamic model</def> TLS (general dynamic) is the most universal.
The code compiled for it can be used anytime, anywhere, and it can access TLS variables defined anywhere.
For example, from one dynamic module, access the TLS variable in another dynamic module.
By default, the compiler generates code for this model, and can use more limited TLS models only when explicitly allowed by the compiler options.
</p>

<p>For the code of this model for the TLS variable are unknown at the build stage (and especially compilation)
neither the module number (slot) in which it is located, nor the offset inside the TLS block of this module.
Module number (ModuleID) and offset in the TLS block are determined only at runtime
(taken from the GOT table where the loader writes them) and passed to a special function
<function>__tls_get_addr</function> (the standard name for many Unix),
which checks for the existence of a TLS block, creates if it is not, and returns the address of the variable for the current thread.
The implementation of this function is also a problem requiring the assistance of the OS.
</p>

<code>
addr1 = __tls_get_addr (GOT [ModuleID], GOT [offset1])
addr2 = __tls_get_addr (GOT [ModuleID], GOT [offset2])
</code>

<p>The code size and runtime are such that it is best to avoid this model altogether.
If the module number and / or offset are known, optimization or simplification is possible.</p>

<p><def>Local dynamic model</def> TLS (local dynamic) is an optimization of the general dynamic model.
The compiler uses this model if it knows that TLS variables are used in the same module in which they are defined.
Now the variable offsets (at least in the TLS block of this module itself) will be known at the linking stage.
The module number is unknown. Still need to call the function <function>__tls_get_addr</function>,
but now it can be called only once (with offset 0) to determine the start address of the <quote>block of its</quote> TLS variables.
The address of individual variables is simply determined by adding a known offset.
</p>

<code>
addr0 = __tls_get_addr (GOT [ModuleID], 0)
addr1 = addr0 + offset1
addr2 = addr0 + offset2
</code>

<p>Dynamic models using the <function> __tls_get_addr</function> function
allow lazy allocation of memory for TLS data at the first request to the block.</p>

<p><def>Static Load Model</def> TLS (initial exec) assumes
that a certain set of dynamic modules will always be loaded together with the main program.
Then the loader can calculate the total value of all TLS blocks of such modules and their location in a single TLS block.
Separate TLS blocks of different modules in this single block will be located at a fixed distance from the beginning of the block,
which the loader computes and stores in the GOT table.
Now, to calculate the address of the TLS variable, you do not need to call the function <function> __tls_get_addr</function>,
it's just a read from the GOT record, and you don't need to know the module number.
Allocation of a single block occurs immediately upon the start of a new thread (without delayed lazy allocation).
If such a model is used for a dynamic library, then it cannot be loaded dynamically, but only statically.
Addressing occurs relative to the selected register <reg>tp</reg> with the offset known at the loading stage (taken from GOT).
</p>

<code>addr = <reg>tp</reg> + GOT [offset]</code>

<p><def>Local static model</def> TLS (local exec) will be obtained if we combine the local dynamic model and the initial exec model,
then we get the local exec model: static loading and local calls (without dynamically linked modules).
The main module of the program (main) refers to the TLS variables defined in it.
Addressing occurs relative to the selected register <reg>tp</reg> with the offset known at the stage of layout.
</p>

<code>addr = <reg>tp</reg> + offset</code>

<p>The compiler usually (when compiling object modules separately, when creating libraries) doesn't have full information about the future program as a whole.
The compiler is forced to make the most careful decisions about the nature of the future program.
This usually comes down to the compiler using the most common mechanisms for addressing private data.
For TLS, this is the general dynamic addressing model.
</p>

<p>Therefore, it is important that the linker, when compiling the finished program, can optimize and make changes to
previously compiled object module, and replace for some variables the existing addressing method with another (optimized) one.
To do this, at a minimum, the linker must know such places (unresolved references to TLS sections),
and the compiler must create the addressing code so that it can be replaced by another.
This requires the equivalence of different TLS addressing methods in terms of code size, number, type and number of registers used, etc.
</p>

<p>If the optimized version is shorter than the original, after the replacement, the program may leave empty spaces filled with dummy <mim>nop</mim> instructions.
It happens that the optimized version is longer than the original, then the compiler must add the dummies in advance,
to allow future linker replacement with an optimized addressing option.
</p>

</section>

<comment>
<section id="object_files">
<title>Object file format</title>

<p>Starting the development of the object file format, you should formulate a model of the executable process,
the model of the executable program module, and the goals that we set for the link editor.
</p>

<ol>
<li>All programs must use ip-relative code.
This is facilitated by the fact that there is no direct addressing in the processor instruction architecture.
</li>

<li>The order of joining sections into segments should be fixed. The compiler must know
how the link editor combines sections into segments, since only between sections from the same segment relative addressing is allowed;</li>

<li>The compiler must be able to predict which segment this object belongs to,
to know what other objects from the same segment it can address relative to this object;</li>

<li>Programs in C/C++ and other high-level languages do not use non-standard sections;</li>

<li>Garbage collection required (exception of unused functions from the assembled module and variables),
for which you need to know the location, size, and alignment of all program objects;</li>

<li>When using an external link and importing the name, the segment must be specified with respect to which the link occurs;</li>

<li>When calculating an unresolved reference, it is possible to calculate formulas of arbitrary complexity,
not going beyond relative addressing within a segment.</li>

<li>It is necessary to optimize the code at the build stage to replace some addressing methods with others.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</comment>

<section id="abi_modules">
<title>Modules and private data</title>

<p>The <archname/> system is focused on code and translation table sharing.
It should be possible to replace shared libraries without recompiling their dependent applications.
Any software module can be used by several processes.
There should be no difference between application code and shared library code.
For addressing code and global data, the addressing relative to the instruction pointer is used with software reconfiguration to the conformant regions of private process/thread data.
</p>

<p>The one address range is used for mapping code sections of all program modules.
This address range is shared by all processes and is executable only.
For each process, another address range is allocated for static process data sections of all program modules.
For each thread, another address range is allocated for the sections of static data of the thread in all program modules.
All three address range types are the of the same size, a multiple of degree 2, and aligned to the same border.
</p>

<p>For each program module, the following three values ​​must be equal:
offset from the beginning of the code range to the beginning of the code section;
offset from the beginning of the private data range of the DATA process to the beginning of the DATA section;
offset from the beginning of the private data range of the TDATA stream to the beginning of the TDATA section.
Knowing only <reg>ip</reg> and the base address of the private range (stored in dedicated registers <reg>gp</reg> and <reg>tp</reg> for DATA and TDATA, respectively),
you can always calculate the location of positionally independent private data using the formula:</p>

<p> base = <reg> gp </reg> | <reg> ip </reg> {<regfield> gtssize </regfield> <minus /> 1: 0} </p>
<p> or indirectly </p>
<p> base = mem [<reg> gp </reg> + <reg> ip </reg> {<regfield>gtssize</regfield> <minus/> 1: 0} <rshift/> <regfield>tgsize</regfield>]
</p>


<p>Private static data can easily be found by library code.
It is not necessary to explicitly pass the correct address of the data segment of the module of the new <reg>gp</reg> (global pointer)
when called through the border of a module or when called through a pointer to a function.
A pointer to a function becomes just a pointer to a place in a code segment,
without additional levels of indirect access via <em>function descriptor</em>.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Sample map for several modules</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th rowspan="3">Address subranges</th>
<th colspan="40">Address granules (loaded modules, used granules)</th>
</tr><tr>
<th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
<th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
<th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
<th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
</tr><tr>
<td class="imm" colspan="3">m1</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3">-</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="5">m2</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="6">m3</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4">-</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="6">m4</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="5">m5</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="3">m6</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5">-</td>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td>TEXT (global)</td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>process A DATA</td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread A1 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread A2 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>process B DATA</td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread B1 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread B2 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread B3 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>process C DATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread C1 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread C2 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread C3 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>process D DATA</td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread D1 TDATA</td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>process E DATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="6"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="cpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread E1 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread E2 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr><tr><td>thread E3 TDATA</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="2"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="1"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
<td class="gpr" colspan="3"></td>
<td class="opx" colspan="5"></td>
</tr></tbody></table>

<p>When dynamically or statically loading a software module, the loader first determines if this module is presented among the loaded modules in the system.
If it isn't loaded, the loader determines for the module a maximum of three module sections:
<psection>CODE</psection>, <psection>DATA</psection> and <psection>TDATA</psection>.
The loader then looks at the system-wide loaded modules region map and looking for an sufficient size unoccupied address range.
According to the rules above, similar unoccupied address ranges exist in all three regions at the same distance from the beginning of each region.
Having found such a range, the loader reserves it for future use by this software module <strong>in all processes and threads</strong>.
</p>

<p>The module occupies the selected address range until the last process that uses this module terminates.
Then the system can unload the module and free the address range, so the next time the same module may be loaded into a different address range.
While the module is loaded, its the base address of the text section of the program module is <strong>unchanged</strong> for all processes using it.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "abi_asm_examples">
<title>Examples of assembler code</title>

<p>The following are examples of using <mim>lda_r</mim>, <mim>jmp</mim>, <mim>call_ri</mim>
to load constants, get procedure addresses, procedure calls.
</p>

<p>Literals and other local read-only data from the TEXT segment can be loaded using ip-relative addressing.
Loading Constant Group:</p>
<code>lda_r base, text_hi (_local_data)
ld_i32 gb, base, text_lo (_local_data) +0
ld_u32 gc, base, text_lo (_local_data) +4
ld_u64 gd, base, text_lo (_local_data) +8
</code>
<p>Getting the address of a static procedure
(within 64 MiB of the current <reg>ip</reg>):</p>
<code>lda_r base, _myfunc
</code>
<p>Getting the address of a static procedure
(further 64 MiB from the current <reg>ip</reg>):</p>
<code>lda_r.l base, _myfunc
</code>
<p>Getting the address of a dynamic procedure:</p>
<code>lda_r base, text_hi (_reloc_table)
ld_u64 gt, base, text_lo (_reloc_table) + __imp_myfunc
</code>
<p>Call a static procedure (within 8 GB of the current <reg>ip</reg>):</p>
<code>call _myfunc
_ret_label:
</code>
<p>Call a static procedure (beyond 8 GB of the current <reg>ip</reg>):</p>
<code>call.l _myfunc
_ret_label:
</code>
<p>Calling a procedure through a pointer (in the addr register):</p>
<code>call_ri lp, addr, gz
_ret_label:
</code>
<p>The call of the explicit dynamic procedure (correction of the call by the compiler):</p>
<code>lda_r base, text_hi (_reloc_table)
ld_u64 addr, base, text_lo (_reloc_table) + __imp_myfunc
call_ri lp, addr, gz
_ret_label:
</code>
<p>Invoking an Implicit Dynamic Procedure
(correction of the call by the linker using the stub function):</p>
<code>call _glu_myfunc
_ret_label:
...
_glu_myfunc:
lda_r gt, _reloc_table
ld_u64 gt, gt, _imp_myfunc
>call_ri gt, g0
_glu_ret_label:
</code>
<p>Private process data (distance up to 1 MiB):</p>
<code>ld_u64 gt, gp, _local_data
</code>
<p>Private process data (distance greater than 1 MiB):</p>
<code>lda_n gt1, gp, data_hi (_local_data)
ld_u64 gt2, gt1, data_lo (_local_data)
</code>
<p>thread local data (distance less than 1 MiB):</p>
<code>ld_u64 gt, gp, _local_data
</code>
<p>thread local data (distance greater than 1 MiB):</p>
<code>lda_n g30, tp, data_hi (_local_data1)
ld_u64 g31, g30, data_lo (_local_data1)
lda_n g31, tp, data_hi (_local_data2)
ld_u64 g32, g31, data_lo (_local_data2)
</code>

</section>
</chapter>
