<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="debugging_and_monitoring">
<title>Debugging and monitoring</title>

<preface>
<p>The <archname/> architecture provides debugging tools that enable hardware and software debugging features,
such as step-by-step program execution, instruction breakpoints, and data breakpoints.
</p>

<p>Debugging tools consist of a special debugging control register <reg>dbscr</reg> (<regname>debug status and control register</regname>),
a set of debugging events as a subset of interrupts,
special registers for comparing instruction addresses <reg>ibr</reg> (<regname>instruction breakpoint register</regname>),
special registers for comparing data addresses <reg>dbr</reg> (<regname>data breakpoint register</regname>).
</p>

<p>Debug registers are available for program execution,
but they are intended for use only by special debuggers and debugging software,
not general software or operating system code.
</p>

<p>Monitoring tools include the following resources:
special registers and/or bit fields controlling the monitoring,
implemented types of counted events,
a fixed number of event counters,
additional type of interrupts for processing the monitoring counter overflow events.</p>
</preface>

<section id="debug_events">
<title>Debug Events</title>

<p>Debugging tools are based on a special group of debug interrupts built into the general interrupt mechanism.
Debug type interrupts can be thrown for various reasons that can be analyzed in the handler of this interrupt.
There are seven types of predefined debugging events:
</p>

<table>
<caption>Debug events (in priority order)</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Event Type</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>IB</td><td><error>Instruction address match</error> debug event occurs on instruction address match.
If the address of a instruction bundle matches one of the criteria,
specified in the debug registers <reg>ibr</reg>, a instruction debugging event is raised (if the instruction is not canceled).
One or more debug events <reg>ibr</reg> occur, if the execution of instructions at the address which matches the criteria specified in the registers <reg>ibr</reg>.
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>DB</td><td><error>Data address match</error> debug event occurs on data address match.
If the address for accessing data in memory meets one of the criteria, specified in the debug registers <reg>dbr</reg>.
Data Debug errors are only reported if the qualification predicate is true.
The reported trap code returns the matching state of the first 4 <reg>dbr</reg> registers that matched during the execution of the instruction.
Zero, one or more <reg>dbr</reg> registers can be reported as matching.
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>TR</td><td>Software Trap</td></tr>
<tr><td>TB</td><td><error>Taken branch</error> trap occurs on each taken branch instruction received if <regfield>psr.tb</regfield>=1.
This trap is useful for profiling a program.
After the trap, <reg>iip</reg> and <regfield>ipsr.rs</regfield> point to the branch destination instruction,
and <reg>iipa</reg> and <regfield>cause.ei</regfield> to the branch instruction that caused the trap.
The case of debugging <error>taken branch</error> (TB) occurs if <regfield>psr.tb</regfield>=1
(that is, debug events <error>taken branch</error> are allowed), the branch instruction is executed
(i.e., either an unconditional branch, or a conditional branch in which the branch condition is satisfied),
and <regfield>psr.de</regfield>=1 or <regfield>dbcr0.idm</regfield>=0.
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>SS</td><td><error>Single step</error> trap occurs on each successfully finished instruction if <regfield>dbsc.rss</regfield>=1 (step-by-step debugging events are allowed).
After the trap, <reg>iip</reg> and <regfield>ipsr.rs</regfield> point to the next instruction to be executed.
<reg>iipa</reg> and <regfield>cause.ei</regfield> point to the caught instruction.
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>lp</td><td>An interrupt has occurred.
The debug event <error>an interrupt occurred</error> (IRPT) occurs,
if <regfield>dbcr.irpt</regfield>=1 (that is, a debug event of the interrupt occurred is allowed) and any
non-critical interruption occurs while <regfield>dbcr.idm</regfield>=1,
or any critical or non-critical interrupt occurs while <regfield>dbcr.idm</regfield>=0.
Abort Accepted Debug Events, may occur regardless of the installation of <regfield>psr.de</regfield>.
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>IR</td><td>Returns from Interrupt</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Debug events include instruction and data breakpoints.
These debug events set the status bits in the DBSR debug status register.
The existence of a set bit in the DBSCR register is considered as a debug exception.
Debug exceptions, if allowed, cause debugging interruptions.
The debug status and control register (DBSCR) is used to set the allowed debug events,
manage timer operations during debugging events, and set processor debugging mode.
It contains the status of debug events.
</p>

<p>The group of bits DBE (debug enabled events) of the DBSCR register is set in supervisor mode and cannot be changed by the program.
Bit groups DBTE (debug taken enabled event) and DBT (debug taken event) of the DBSCR register
installed by hardware, they can be read and cleaned programmatically.
The contents of the DBSCR register can be read into the general register by the instruction <mim>get_spr</mim>.
</p>

<p>Debug events are used to force debug exceptions. be registered in the DBSCR debug status register.
</p>

<p>To enable the debug event, you need to set the corresponding bit
from the DBE group of the DBSCR register and thus raise a debug exception
a certain type of event must be allowed by the corresponding bit or bits
in the dbcr debug control registers. Once the DBSCR register bit is set and,
if debug interrupts are enabled (a bit from the DBE group is 1), a debug interrupt will be generated.</p>

<p>The bit in the special DBSCR debug control register must be
set to 1 to allow debugging interrupt corresponding to this bit.
Debugging events are not allowed to occur when the corresponding bit in the DBSCR register is 0.
In such situations, no debug exception of this type occurs.
and no bits of this type of DBSCR register are set.
</p>

<p>If the corresponding bit in the register <reg>dbscr</reg> is 1
(that is, debugging interrupts of this type are allowed) during this debug exception,
interruption of debugging will occur immediately
(if there is no exception with a higher priority,
which is allowed to cause interrupts), the execution of the instruction,
causing the exception will be suppressed, and CSRR0 will be set to the address of this instruction.
</p>

<p>If debug interrupts of this type are blocked during a debug exception,
interruption of debugging will not occur, and the instruction will complete execution
(provided, the instruction doesn't cause some other exception,
which generates an allowed interrupt).
</p>

<note>If an instruction is suppressed due to an instruction,
that raised some other exception that allows the generation of an interrupt,
then the attempted implementation of that instruction does no Cause the instruction Complete debugging case.
The <mim>trap</mim> instruction doesn't fall into the category of instructions whose execution is suppressed,
starting with instructions, it actually completes execution and then generates an interruption to the system call.
In this case, the finished debug exclusion command will also be installed.
</note>

<p>A trap debugging event (<mim>trap</mim>) occurs if <regfield>dbscr.trap</regfield>=1
(that is, Trap debugging events are allowed) and the Trap instruction is unconditional or the conditions for the trap are met.
</p>

<p>Interrupt instruction error <ndash/> execution of <mim>trap</mim> instruction results in the Interrupt instruction error.
An interrupt can be used to profile, debug, and enter the operating system.
(although the instruction to enter the privileged code (<mim>syscall</mim>) is recommended, since it has lower costs).
</p>

<p>If <regfield>dbcr.trap</regfield>=0 (that is, trap-type debugging interrupts are blocked)
during the exception of debugging a trap, interruption of debugging will not occur,
and the type of exception for the Trap. A Program Interruption will occur instead if the trap condition is met.
</p>

<p>Trap <error>Decrease privilege level</error>.
when <regfield>psr.lp</regfield>=1, and the transition that occurs lowers the privilege level
(<regfield>psr.cpl</regfield> becomes 1), this trap occurs.
This trap allows the debugger to keep track of privilege drops, for example,
to remove permissions granted to higher privileged code.
After the trap <reg>iip</reg> and <regfield>ipsr.rs</regfield>
point to the effective address of the branch, and <reg>iipa</reg> and <regfield>cause.ei</regfield> to the branch instruction that caused the trap.
</p>

<p>When <regfield>dbcr.idm</regfield>=1, only non-critical interrupts can trigger debugging events of the interrupt that occurred.
This is because all critical interrupts automatically clear <regfield>psr.de</regfield>,
which would always prevent the associated debugging interrupt from appearing accurately.
Also, debug interrupts directly are <ndash/> critical class interrupts, and thus any debug interrupt
(for any other debugging case) would always end up during installation
an additional exception to <regfield>dbsr.irpt</regfield> after entering the debug interrupt handler.
At this point, the debug interrupt routine is unable to determine
Is the interruption a valid debugging event? It was related to the initial debugging event.
</p>

<p>When <regfield>dbcr.idm</regfield>=0,
then critical and non-critical class interruptions can cause the Abort Accepted debugging event.
In this case, the assumption is that debugging events are not used to cause interruptions.
(software can vote DBSR instead)
and therefore it's proper to record an exception in DBSR even though
that the critical interrupt that causes the interrupt is an accepted debug event, will clear <regfield>psr.de</regfield>.
</p>

<p>Debug event <error>Interception return from interrupt</error>
(a call to the <mim>ret</mim> instruction) occurs if <regfield>dbcr.ret</regfield>=1
(i.e. debugging events are allowed when returning from an interrupt)
and an attempt was made to execute the <mim>rfi</mim> instruction.
When a debug event occurs on return, <regfield>dbsr.ret</regfield> is set to 1 to record a debug exception.
</p>

</section>

<section id="debug_registers">
<title>Debug registers</title>

<p>Debug registers are designed to organize the interception of program calls to
specific address ranges for specific purposes (e.g. execution or writing),
and allow the debugger to verify the correctness of the program.
Their number depends on the implementation. Read/write ability depends on the priority level, processor model.
They are used in pairs, with at least 4 pairs for instructions and 4 for data.
</p>

<p>The 128-bit instruction breakpoint registers <reg>ibr</reg> are for debug comparing instruction addresses.
A debugging event can be allowed to occur after trying to execute a instruction at an address range specified by a <reg>ibr</reg> register.
Since all instruction addresses must be aligned on the border of the bundle,
the four least significant bits of the <reg>ibr</reg> register are reserved and do not participate in comparison with the address of the instruction bundle.
</p>

<reg_table>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="64">address</imm>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <bitfield>x</bitfield>
    <reserved size="3">0</reserved>
    <bitfield size="4">plm</bitfield>
    <imm size="52">mask</imm>
    <reserved size="4">0</reserved>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>The 128-bit data breakpoint registers <reg>dbr</reg> are for debug comparing data addresses.
A debugging event can be allowed to occur after loads, stores, or atomic instructions to an address range specified by a <reg>dbr</reg> register.
</p>

<reg_table>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="64">address</imm>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <bitfield>r</bitfield>
    <bitfield>w</bitfield>
    <reserved size="2">0</reserved>
    <bitfield size="4">plm</bitfield>
    <imm size="56">mask</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>The contents of the register <reg>dbr</reg> are compared with the address computed by the memory access instruction.
Data debugging event occurs, if enabled, attempted execution of the data memory access instruction, and type, address,
and maybe even the meaning of the data access memory matches the criteria specified in the <reg>dbr</reg>.
</p>

<p>All load instructions are treated as reads regarding debugging events, while all store instructions are treated as a write regarding debugging events.
Additionally, cache management instructions, and some special cases handled as follows.
</p>

<p>The <regfield>cmp</regfield> bits determine whether all or some of the bits of the instruction address should
match the contents of debug register, whether the address should be inside or beyond a specific range specified by a <reg>ibr</reg> register for a debugging event to occur.
</p>

<p>There are four modes for comparing instruction addresses.</p>
<ul>
<li>bit matching mode: if <reg>ip</reg> AND <regfield>ibr.mask</regfield> == <regfield>ibr.address</regfield> AND <regfield>ibr.mask</regfield>.</li>
<li>interval containing mode: For ibr debug events, if the instruction address is greater than or equal to the content of ibr.high and less than the content of inr.low, matching instruction address occurs.</li>
<li>Exceptional interval mode: For ibr debug events, if the instruction address is less than the content of ibr.high or greater than or equal to the content of ibr.low, matching instruction address occurs.</li>
</ul>

<p>High register part contains breakpoint addresses, low part contains offset or breakpoint mask.
At least 4 data and instruction registers are implemented on all processor models.
The first registers after zero by number are implemented.
</p>

<p>The instruction and data memory addresses provided for compliance are always in the implemented address space.
Programming an unimplemented physical address in <reg>ibr</reg>/<reg>dbr</reg> ensures that the physical addresses provided by ibr/dbr will never match.
Similarly, programming unimplemented virtual addressing in <reg>ibr</reg>/<reg>dbr</reg> ensures that the virtual addresses submitted by <reg>ibr</reg>/<reg>dbr</reg> will never match.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Debug breakpoint register fields (<reg>dbr</reg>/<reg>ibr</reg>)</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Field</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Address<br/>63:0</td><td><def>Matching address</def><ndash/>
64-bit virtual or physical breakpoint address.
The address is interpreted as virtual or physical depending on
<regfield>psr.dt</regfield> and <regfield>psr.it</regfield>.
The trap <error>Instruction data breakpoint address</error> occurs when load, store, semaphore instruction.
For fetching instructions, the lower four bits of ibr.addr{3:0} are ignored when comparing addresses.
All 64 bits are implemented on all processors, regardless of the number of address bits implemented.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>mask<br/>55:0</td><td><def>mask for the address</def> determines which address bits
in the corresponding address register will be compared when determining the conformity of the control point.
Address bits for which mask bits are 1 must match the address of the breakpoint, otherwise, the address bit is ignored.
Address bits {63:56} for which there are no corresponding mask bits, always compared.
All 56 bits are implemented on all processors, regardless of the number implemented bits of the address.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>plm<br/>59:56</td><td><def>Mask for all privilege levels</def> <ndash/>
Allows data breakpoints that match the specified privilege level.
Each bit corresponds to one of 4 privilege levels.
Bit 56 corresponds to privilege level 0, bit 57 to level 1, etc.
A value of 1 indicates that debugging comparisons are allowed at this privilege level.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>w<br/>62</td><td><def>Write</def> - When <regfield>dbr.w</regfield>=1,
any not canceled store, semaphore, probe.w.fault or probe.rw.fault to the address, causes the breakpoint to the corresponding address register.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>r<br/>63</td><td><def>Read</def> - When <regfield>dbr.r</regfield>=1,
any unannounced load, semaphore, lfetch.fault, probe.r.fault or probe.rw.fault at the address corresponding to the address register causes a breakpoint.
When <regfield>dbr.r</regfield>=1, PT access that matches dbr
(except those for the tak instruction) will cause an error <error>Missing in Instruction/Data TLB</error>.
If <regfield>dbr.r</regfield>=0 and <regfield>dbr.w</regfield>=0, the data breakpoint register is locked.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>x<br/>63</td><td><def>Execution</def> - When <regfield>ibr.x</regfield>=1,
executing instructions at the address corresponding to the address register causes a breakpoint.
If <regfield>ibr.x</regfield>=0, then the instruction breakpoint register is locked.
Control points for instructions will be reported, even the instruction is canceled.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>ig<br/>62:60</td><td>Ignored</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The registers <reg>dbr</reg>/<reg>ibr</reg> can only be accessed at the highest privilege level 0,
otherwise, the <error>privileged operation</error> error occurs.
</p>

<p>Debug register changes are not necessarily observed with the following instructions.
The software must use the data serialization to ensure that modifications to <reg>dbr</reg>,
<regfield>psr.db</regfield>, <regfield>psr.tb</regfield> and <regfield>psr.lp</regfield>
observed before the dependent instruction is executed.
Because changing the registers <reg>ibr</reg> and the flag <regfield>psr.db</regfield>,
affect the subsequent instruction fetching, the software must execute the instruction serialization.
</p>

<p>In some implementations, a hardware debugger may use two or more registers for its own use.
When a hardware debugger is applied, only 2 <reg>dbr</reg> and only 2 <reg>ibr</reg> are available for program use.
The software should be able to run with fewer implemented <reg>ibr</reg> and/or <reg>dbr</reg> registers if a hardware debugger is present.
When a hardware debugger is not implemented, at least 4 <reg>ibr</reg> and 4 <reg>dbr</reg> are available for programmatic use.
</p>

<p>Implemented debug registers used by the attached hardware debugger,
arranged by number first (for example, if only 2 <reg>dbr</reg> are available software, the registers <reg>dbr</reg>[0-1]) are available.
</p>

<note>When a hardware debugger is implemented and it uses two or more of debug registers,
the processor doesn't force registers between the program and the hardware debugger,
that is, the processor doesn't prohibit the program from reading or changing any of the debug registers.
However, if the program modifies any of the registers used by the hardware debugger,
the processor and/or hardware operation of the debugger may become undefined; the processor and/or hardware debugger may crash.
</note>

<p>The instructions <mim>get_ibr</mim> (get instruction breakpoint register), <mim>set_ibr</mim> (set instruction breakpoint register),
<mim>get_dbr</mim> (get data breakpoint register), <mim>set_dbr</mim> (set data breakpoint register) are used to indirectly read/write instruction/data debug registers.
The sum of general register and simm10 is used to pass index of monitor register number.
</p>

<code>get_ibr  ra, rb  # ra = <reg>ibr</reg>[rb+imm]
set_ibr  ra, rb  # <reg>ibr</reg>[rb+imm] = ra
get_dbr  ra, rb  # ra = <reg>dbr</reg>[rb+imm]
set_dbr  ra, rb  # <reg>dbr</reg>[rb+imm] = ra
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>instruction format for debug registers read/write</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>target</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <stride>simm10</stride>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id="monitor_registers">
<title>Monitoring registers</title>

<p>Monitoring Registers are designed to count various internal events when executing an instruction thread.
Their number depends on the implementation (minimum 4).
Read/write ability depends on the priority level, processor model.
</p>

<reg_table>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="64">counter for the number of such events</imm>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <ignored size="56">0</ignored>
    <bitfield size="8">event type</bitfield>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>There are at least 8 128-bit performance monitoring registers (<reg>mr0</reg><hellip/><reg>mr7</reg>).
Unimplemented monitoring registers when reading give zero, writing to them is ignored.
Each monitoring register is associated with a specific event for which it is counting.
</p>

<table width="50%">
<caption>The counted events types</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Event</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td></td><td>Page access</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>DTLB miss</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>ITLB miss</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>I1-cache miss</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>D1-cache miss</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>D1-cache write-back</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>L2-cache miss</td></tr>
<tr><td></td><td>L2-cache write-back</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>An overflow of monitor counter raises an asynchronous event.
</p>

<p>The instructions <mim>get_mr</mim> (get monitor register) and <mim>set_mr</mim> (set monitor register) are used to indirectly read/write monitor registers.
The sum of general register and simm10 is used to pass index of monitor register number.
</p>

<code>get_mr  ra, rb  # ra = MR[rb+imm]
set_mr  ra, rb  # MR[rb+imm] = ra
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>instruction format for <mim>get_mr</mim>, <mim>set_mr</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>target</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <stride>simm10</stride>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

</chapter>
