<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="exceptions">
<title>The software exceptions support</title>

<preface>
<p><def>Software exceptions</def> are for C++-like throw/try/catch exceptions and for more common SEH-like exceptions.
The <archname/> is planned to support deterministic exception handling via frame-based unwinding with sufficient hardware support.
The really zero-cost for exception usage is expected for no-exception cases and fast unwinding for exception cases.
</p>

<p>The 128-bit link register <reg>r0</reg> preserves 18-bit eip offset, which allow alternate return point in case of exception.
The exception landing pad address should be after current return address no further than 4 MiB offset.
The return instructions may jump to usual return address or to the landing pad depending on exception state.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Link register format <reg>r0</reg></caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="60">return address</reserved>
    <reserved size="2">0</reserved>
    <reserved size="2">rs</reserved>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="32">preserved caller future</reserved>
    <imm size="18">eip offset</imm>
    <reserved size="7">out-size</reserved>
    <reserved size="7">framesize</reserved>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>
alternate_retaddr = retaddr + 16 <times/> ZEXT(eip_offset)
</p>

</preface>

<section id="exception_state">
<title>Program state for exception</title>

<p>Special register <reg>eip</reg> always holds the address of next proper part of unwinding code.
This register is automatically restored during normal subroutine return.
It's modified during object construction and destruction.
Special register <reg>eca</reg> holds the throwing value (usually the address of throwing object).
</p>

<p>Two return address will be saved to link register during subroutine call: for normal return and for exception return.
Because registers are 128 bits long, it's enough place for both.
But because we need store also frameinfo and previous future vector, exception return address is stored as an positive offset from normal return address.
Exception landing pad should be after function body near 4MiB.
</p>

<p>So we don't need to return some optional pair (normal return value and optional exception info),
and always do the check after each call for possible software exception.
Excepted subroutine finally return directly to the proper next part of unwinding code.
</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>eh_throw</mim> sets special register <reg>eca</reg> to the value (<param>src</param> + simm21).
Usually it should be the address of exception context.
This triggers execution to jump to eip address.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>eh_throw</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <binimm>simm21</binimm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>eh_adj</mim> should be called after the successful construction of the object which requires destruction.
It checks the current eca context and jumps to current <reg>eip</reg> if exception is set.
Otherwize, it adjusts <reg>eip</reg> register to the new actual unwinding code address and continues normally to the next instruction.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>eh_adj</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <jump>simm28(60)x16</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>eh_catch</mim> copys the exception context <reg>eca</reg> to general register, clears <reg>eca</reg>,
and adjust new <reg>eip</reg> value to <reg>ip</reg>+displacement<times/>16.
</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>eh_catch</mim> should be called before the catch block or before the object destructor.
For the catch block it adjusts <reg>eip</reg> register to the end of catch block.
Before object destructor it should adjusts <reg>eip</reg> register to the position after destructor.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>eh_catch</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <branch_opx_res>0</branch_opx_res>
    <branch>simm17(30)x16</branch>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>eh_next</mim> should be called after the object destructor.
It restores exception context saved in ehcatch before destructor call and checks for possible double exception fault.
If it is the second software exception at the time of unwinding first software exception, then hardware exception occurs.
Otherwise, if it is normal destructor call during unwinding first software exception, execution continues to new eip address.
Otherwise, if it is normal destructor call without any unwinding, execution continues to next instruction.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>eh_next</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <branch_opx_res>0</branch_opx_res>
    <branch>simm17(30)x16</branch>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>
</chapter>
