<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter id="cpu_extended">
<title>Extended instruction set</title>

<preface>
<p>This chapter describes the <em>extended</em> virtual processor instruction set which was not included in the basic set.
</p>
</preface>

<section id = "conditional_traps">
<title>Conditional trap instructions</title>

<p>Conditional trap instructions check condition and if true trap execution to exception vector <quote>program_trap</quote>.
Hardware instructions exist for EQ, NE, LT-signed, LT-unsigned conditions.
Other conditions may be implemented via arguments swapping, changing the immediate sign, adjusting immediate by 1.
</p>

<p>Syntax:</p>
<code>INSTRUCTION_NAME    rb, rc, simm</code>

<table>
<thead><tr>
<th>Instruction</th>
<th>Operation</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td><mim>teq</mim></td><td>trap if Rb == Rc + simm</td><td>64bit</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>tne</mim></td><td>trap if Rb != Rc + simm</td><td>64bit</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>tlt</mim></td><td>trap if Rb &lt; Rc + simm</td><td>64bit, signed</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>tltu</mim></td><td>trap if Rb &lt; Rc + simm</td><td>64bit, unsigned</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format for conditional traps</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>src1</gpr>
    <gpr>src2</gpr>
    <binimm>simm21 (63)</binimm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id = "load_address">
<title>Helper Address Calculation Instructions</title>

<p>To simplify addressing, several instructions have been introduced that calculate addresses without going to memory.
The <mim>ldax</mim> instruction returns the destination address as in indexed addressing.</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>ldax</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <scale>scale</scale>
    <idisp>disp</idisp>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Data addressing relative to the instruction counter is missing in the <archname/> architecture.
Therefore, to use the standard (basic with offset) addressing, you need a way to get the relative address in the base register.
The instruction <mim>ldar</mim> (<miname>load address relative</miname>) is used to calculate the base address relative to the current instruction counter <reg>ip</reg>.
The first argument is the number of the result register, the second is the distance in the instruction bundles from the current position
(in assembler, this is a label in the code section, or a label in the immutable data section, aligned on a 16-byte boundary).
It is used to get the base address of immutable data from a code section, function address or label.
The instruction doesn't generate interrupts.
</p>

<code>ldar dst, label</code>

<p>This instruction is necessary for position-independent code to get the absolute address of objects,
stored at a fixed distance from the current position, for example, intra-module procedures or unchanged local module data.
On systems like MAS (<em>Multiple Address Spaces</em>) with multiple address spaces,
where the module's private data is stored at a fixed distance from the code section,
it can also be used to obtain the base absolute address of the module's private data.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>ldar</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <jump>label (28 bits)</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <reserved size = "10">0</reserved>
    <imm size = "32">label (expanding to 60 bits instead of 28)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction is formed according to the ldar rule. The result register is followed by a 28-bit field for encoding the offset relative to the instruction counter.
The data block must be aligned with at least a 16-byte boundary, since the offset expresses the distance in instruction bundles, not bytes.
The general formula for obtaining the address:</p>

<p>gr [dst] = <reg>ip</reg> + 16 <times/> sign_extend(label)</p>

<p>Offset field 28 bits long (64 bits for double instruction) after sign extension
and left shift by 4 positions is added to the contents of the instruction counter <reg>ip</reg>,
to produce a 64-bit effective address.
The <mim>ldar</mim> instruction allows the continuation of the immediate value in the instruction code
to the next slot of the bundle with the formation of a dual-slot instruction.</p>

<p>The maximum distance for a short instruction is 2 GiB on either side of the instruction counter.
It is more convenient to store constant data not after each procedure, but to collect in larger blocks
in order to reduce the overhead of aligning cache lines and for optimal
use separate TLB (translate lookaside buffer) for code and data.
</p>

<p>The <mim>ldar</mim> instruction might be also used to organize access to static data of the module.
But special for this the instruction <mim>ldr</mim> is intended, which allow to address any byte address.
To use <mim>ldr</mim>, the distance from the point of contact to the data should not exceed 256 MiB.
The linker can increase the size of the code section by moving procedures,
accessing static data (usually a minority) closer to the data section.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>ldr</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <jump>label (28 bits)</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <reserved size = "6">0</reserved>
    <imm size = "36">label (expanding to 64 bits instead of 28)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>gr [dst] = <reg>ip</reg> + zero_extend(label)</p>


<p>If a constant with a sign is fits in 28 bits, then it's more efficient to use the <mim>ldi</mim> instruction,
and if fits in 56 bits then <mim>ldi</mim> along with <mim>ldan</mim>.
However, when loading constants in bulk, a single <mim>ldar</mim> instruction falls on several loading instructions,
and then a pair of <mim>ldi</mim> and <mim>ldan</mim> <ndash/> instructions is less compact than a single <mim>ldw</mim> instruction.
As for loading 8-byte integer constants, real constants, vector constants, then
using <mim>ldar</mim> along with <mim>ld8</mim>, <mim>ld4</mim> and other download instructions,
is the recommended, and often the only possible way to load such constants.
</p>

<p>Base with offset addressing allows 1 MiB addressing to both sides of the base address when using one-slot instructions (21-bit offset).
If the object is beyond 1 MiB, you will have to use dual-slot instructions.
But usually, by virtue of the principle of <strong>locality of calls</strong>,
with a high probability the program will next turn to objects located near the first.
This fact can be used, and once calculate the base address, from which several necessary objects
are located no further than 1 MiB, and then use one-slot instructions to address them.
</p>

<p>Nearest Base Address Calculation Instructions <mim>ldan</mim> (<miname>load address near</miname>).
It is used to optimize local (by place and time) memory access without using dual-slot instructions and long offsets.
</p>

<code>ldan dst, base, simm</code>

<p>First argument is the result register number,
second is base address register number,
the third is an immediate value is 21 bits long (or 63 bits for a long instruction), extended to 64 bits.
The instruction allows the continuation of the immediate value in the instruction code up to 63 bits to the next slot of the bundle with the formation of a dual-slot instruction.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>ldan</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <binimm>simm (21 bits)</binimm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <ignored size="18">0</ignored>
    <imm size="24">(63 bits instead of 21)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The target 64-bit address is calculated (for ldan) as:</p>
<p>gr [dst] = gr [base] + (simm <lshift/> 20)</p>

<p>The following example shows how to use the <mim>ldan</mim> instruction
to access a group of closely spaced (no more than 1 MiB from each other),
but far-away data (the distance to the <param>sym</param> object is more than 1 MiB from the base address).
</p>

<p>Without using <mim>ldan</mim> (4 double instructions, 8 slots)
</p>

<code>ldsw.l	g11, base, sym + 4
ldw.l	g12, base, sym + 8
std.l	g12, base, sym + 16
ldd.l	g13, base, sym + 32</code>

<p>Using <mim>ldan</mim> (5 single instructions, 5 slots)
</p>

<code>ldan	tmp, base, data_hi (sym); put the nearest address in tmp
ldsw	g11, tmp, data_lo (sym) +4; tmp addressing
ldw	g12, tmp, data_lo (sym) +8
std	g12, tmp, data_lo (sym) +16
ldd	g13, tmp, data_lo (sym) +32</code>

</section>

<section id="multprecision">
<title>Multiprecision arithmetic</title>

<p>For hardware support for long arithmetic, it is advisable to add special instructions.
In the general case, for intermediate addition/subtraction of parts of high precision numbers
it is required to specify the incoming carry (borrow), two operands, the result and the outgoing carry (borrow).
</p>

<p>When explicitly coding all dependencies and not using global flags (which is good for parallel/pipeline execution of instructions)
it requires 5 parameters: the result, two operands, input and output carry/borrow.
There is not enough space in the instructions for all five parameters.
Therefore, the high part of 128-bit registers is used to return the carry/borrow.
</p>

<p>A special instruction <mim>mulh</mim> (<miname>multiply high</miname>) was introduced for hardware support for multiplying long numbers
calculating the upper half of a 128-bit product of two 64-bit numbers.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>addc</mim>, <mim>subb</mim>, <mim>mulh</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <gpr>rc</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>addaddc</mim>, <mim>subsubb</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <gpr>rc</gpr>
    <gpr>rd</gpr>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Syntax:</p>
<code>addc      ra, rb, rc
addaddc   ra, rb, rc, rd
subb      ra, rb, rc
subsubb   ra, rb, rc, rd
mulh      ra, rb, rc
</code>

<table>
<caption>Fused instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Operation</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td><mim>addc</mim></td><td><miname>add with carry</miname></td><td>ra = carry (rb + rc), sum (rb + rc)</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>subb</mim></td><td><miname>subtract with borrow</miname></td><td>ra = borrow (rb <minus/> rc), rb-rc</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>addaddc</mim></td><td><miname>add and add with carry</miname></td><td>ra = carry (rb + rc + rd. high), rb + rc + rd.high</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>subsubb</mim></td><td><miname>subtract and subtract with borrow</miname></td><td>ra = borrow (rb <minus/> rc <minus/>rd.high),rb<minus/>rc<minus/>rd.high</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>
It is assumed that numbers of arbitrary length are already loaded into the registers.
For example, the addition of 256-bit numbers will occur as follows:
</p>
<code>addc      a1, b1, c1      ; sum of lower parts, first carry-out
addaddc   a2, b2, c2, a1  ; sum of middles and carry-in, next carry-out
addaddc   a3, b3, c3, a2  ; sum of middles and carry-in, next carry-out
addaddc   a4, b4, c4, a3  ; sum of higher and carry-in, last carry-out
</code>

</section>

<section id="syscall">
<title>Software interrupts, system calls</title>

<p>The instruction <mim>syscall</mim> (<miname>system call</miname>) does the call to the kernel of the system to process the system request.
The system call code computed as gr[base] + offset.
</p>

<p>Unlike interrupts, a system call is an analogue of a function call, and has similarly implemented return from it to the next bundle.
Therefore, after the instruction <mim>syscall</mim> in assembler, you need to put a label to ensure that the subsequent instructions fall into the new bundle.
Bits of future predication are cleared.
</p>

<p>The first <reg>frame</reg> registers are rotated, and return address is stored in zero register in the new frame.
Subsequent local registers contain syscall arguments.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>syscall</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>frame</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <stride>offset</stride>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The <mim>sysret</mim> (<miname>system return</miname>) instruction returns from the system request handler, which was called using <mim>syscall</mim>.
The instruction use the return address and frame state from zero register.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>sysret</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>int</mim> (<miname>interrupt</miname>) is provided for sending interrupts to the current core themselves programmatically.
The sent interrupt doesn't happen synchronously to the instruction thread, but it can be delayed until the moment when this vector is unmasked.
For the user-mode program, when all interrupts are unmasked, the sent interrupt is happen synchronously to the instruction thread.
The interrupt index is calculated as gr[src] + simm21.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>int</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <regzero>src</regzero>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <stride>offset</stride>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The <mim>rfi</mim> instruction (<miname>return from interruption</miname>) returns from the interrupt handler.
It returns to the beginning of the bundle containing the interrupted incomplete instruction (in case of an error),
or to a bundle containing the subsequent instruction (in the case of a trap).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>rfi</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id = "cpu_atomic">
<title>Atomic instructions</title>

<p>The processor implementation must follow the programmatic order of executing the instructions of a single-threaded program.
But the effects of the actions of one thread on the memory can be observed by other threads not in the programmatic order of this thread 
Depending on the guarantees that the architecture explicitly gives and the permissions that the implementation is explicitly allowed,
talk about a stricter or weaker ordering of memory.
<archname/> is an architecture with weak memory ordering.
There are no obvious restrictions on the visibility of third-party processors or other devices
(for example, input-output) actions on the memory of the current thread.
Similarly, the current thread has no explicit guarantees on the order of visibility of the actions of other agents.
</p>

<p>Special instructions <quote>load-atomic</quote> and <quote>store-atomic</quote>
used to push the visibility of changes from one thread to another.
relaxed - normal operation, acquire - acquire changes, release - submit changes, acquire-release - sequential-consistent.
Before changing the general data, the thread performs acquire by load-acquire from the watchdog variable.
Similarly, after a change is made to the general data, the stream pushes the changes, executing release by store-release to the watchdog variable.
</p>

<code>ld1a   dst, base, mo
ld2a   dst, base, mo
ld4a   dst, base, mo
ld8a   dst, base, mo
ld16a  dst, base, mo
st1a   src, base, mo
st2a   src, base, mo
st4a   src, base, mo
st8a   src, base, mo
st16a  src, base, mo
</code>

<p>These instructions are one-way barriers.
They do not allow speculative and out-of-order execution of operations with memory through themselves.
Acquire doesn't allow the subsequent instructions to move forward, and release doesn't let the instructions before it lag behind.
With the correct (pairwise) use of acquire-release, a closed section of code is obtained, locked at the top (acquire) and at the bottom (release).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format for atomic load/store</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst/src</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <memorder>mo</memorder>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>All subsequent atomic instructions are categorized as RMW (read-modify-write) and contain as an option the memory order for the read and write stages (field <strong>mo</strong>).
Accordingly, the order is possible: acquire, release, acquire-release (acqrel), and simply relaxed without a barrier.
</p>

<p>The atomic instruction group atomic modification (fetch-op) copies the old value of a variable from memory to register,
and sets a new value in memory (test-and-set), or obtained from the old (fetch-and-add and analogues).
</p>

<code>ea = gr [base]
dst = mem [ea]
mem [ea] = dst op src
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>fetch-op</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <memorder>mo</memorder>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<code>amoXXX dst, base, src, order</code>

<table width="75%">
<caption>atomic instructions fetch-op</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Instruction</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><mim>amoswap4</mim></td><td>test-and-set 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoswap8</mim></td><td>test-and-set 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoadd4</mim></td><td>addition, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoadd8</mim></td><td>addition, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoand4</mim></td><td>bitwise AND, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoand8</mim></td><td>bitwise AND, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoor4</mim></td><td>bitwise OR, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoor8</mim></td><td>bitwise OR, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoxor4</mim></td><td>bitwise XOR, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amoxor8</mim></td><td>bitwise XOR, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomin4</mim></td><td>signed minimum, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomin8</mim></td><td>signed minimum, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomax4</mim></td><td>signed maximum, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomax8</mim></td><td>signed maximum, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amominu4</mim></td><td>unsigned minimum, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amominu8</mim></td><td>unsigned minimum, 8 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomaxu4</mim></td><td>unsigned maximum, 4 bytes</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>amomaxu8</mim></td><td>unsigned maximum, 8 bytes</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Instructions
<mim>cas4</mim> (<miname>compare and swap 4-byte</miname>),
<mim>cas8</mim> (<miname>compare and swap 8-byte</miname>),
<mim>cas16</mim> (<miname>compare and swap 16-byte</miname>)
Designed for non-blocking interactions in a multi-threaded multiprocessor environment.
Both instructions are atomic indivisible memory operations that cannot be partially performed.
</p>

<p>The <mim>cas</mim> instruction reads an N-byte number from memory at the address from the <param>base</param> register,
and compares it with the value in the register <param>dst</param>.
If the values match, the instruction saves the new value from the <param>src</param> register at this address.
Otherwise, the instruction doesn't save anything at this address.
The base address must be aligned at the N-byte boundary.
The read value is stored in the register <param>dst</param>.
</p>

<code>value = mem [base]
if (value == gr [dst]) {
 mem [base] = gr [src]
}
gr [dst] = value
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of instructions <mim>casX</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <memorder>mo</memorder>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Using the following procedure, a stream can modify the contents of a memory cell even if there is a possibility that the stream
can be interrupted and replaced by another thread that will update the cell,
or that a thread on another processor can simultaneously modify a cell.
First, an 8-byte number is entirely loaded into the register.
Then, the updated value is computed and placed in another <param>sval</param> register.
Then the <mim>cas16</mim> instruction is executed with parameters
<param>test</param> (register number where the initial value),
<param>base</param> (base address register number) and
<param>sval</param> (register number that contains the updated value).
If the modification was completed successfully, the original value will be returned.
If the memory cell doesn't contain the original value
(the current thread was interrupted or the thread of another processor interrupted), the update will not be successful,
general register with the number <param>dst</param> of the instruction <mim>cas16</mim> contains the new current value of the memory cell.
If the memory cell doesn't contain an original value, the thread may try to repeat the procedure again using the new current value.
</p>

<code>
loop:
<mim>ldd</mim> test, base, 0
<mim>mov</mim> save, test
...
<mim>addi</mim> sval, dst, 12; some kind of modification
...
<mim>cas8</mim> sval, base, test
<mim>bne</mim> save, test, loop
</code>

<p>The instruction <mim>cas8</mim> can be used for controlled sharing of a common data area,
including the ability to send messages (to a linked message list) when a common area is in use.
To achieve this, an 8-byte number in memory can be used as a control number.
A value of zero indicates that the common area is not in use, and that no messages exist.
A negative value indicates that the area is in use by someone, and that no messages exist.
A positive value indicates that the shared area is in use,
and that the value is the address of the most recent message added to the list.
Therefore, any number of threads wishing to capture a common area,
can use <mim>cas8</mim> to update the check number,
to indicate that the area is in use or add messages to the list.
The only thread that has captured the shared area can also safely use <mim>cas16</mim> to remove messages from the list.
</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>cas16</mim> can be used similarly to <mim>cas8</mim>.
Additionally, it has other uses.
Consider a linked data list, with a check number used to address the first message in the list, as described above.
If multiple threads are allowed to delete messages using <mim>cas8</mim>
(and not just the only thread that captured the common area), then the list will probably be incorrectly modified.
This can happen if, for example, after one thread reads the address
the very last message to move the message, another thread will delete the first two messages,
and then adds the first message back to the linked list (<quote>ABA</quote> issue in IBM terminology).
The first thread, continuing the interrupted execution, will not be able to determine that the list has changed.
By increasing the size of the control word to a pair of 8-byte numbers,
containing the address of the first message and the modification tag (change number),
which increases by 1 each time the list is modified, and using <mim>cas16</mim> to update both fields together,
the possibility of incorrect list updating can be reduced to an insignificant level.
Namely, incorrect modification can occur only if the first stream
was interrupted and during this time the number of changes to the list is exactly a multiple of 2<sup>64</sup>,
and only if the last change to the list uses the original address of the message.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "cipher_instructions">
<title>AES cipher instructions</title>

<table width="80%">
<caption>AES instructions</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Operation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aesdec</mim>      ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td><miname>aes decrypt round</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aesdeclast</mim>  ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td><miname>aes decrypt last round</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aesenc</mim>      ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td><miname>aes encrypt round</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aesenclast</mim>  ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td><miname>aes encrypt last round</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aesimc</mim>      ra, rb</pre></td><td><miname>aes inverse mix columns</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aeskeygen</mim>   ra, rb, imm14</pre></td><td><miname>aes key generation assist</miname></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aesenc</mim>, <mim>aesenclast</mim>, <mim>aesdec</mim>, <mim>aesdeclast</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src1</gpr>
    <gpr>src2</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aesimc</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aeskeygen</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <stride>round constant</stride>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id = "random_generator">
<title>Random number generation instruction</title>

<p>The special instructions <mim>rdrand</mim> and <mim>rdseed</mim> are designed to generate random variables.
Reading from it returns the next 64-bit random number.
Both <mim>rdrand</mim> and <mim>rdseed</mim> return random numbers
that are compliant to the <quote>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</quote> standards on random number generators.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>rdrand</mim>, <mim>rdseed</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<table>
<thead>
<tr><th>Instruction</th><th>Source</th><th>NIST Compliance</th></tr>
</thead><tbody>
<tr><td>rdrand</td><td>Cryptographically secure pseudorandom number generator</td><td>SP 800-90A</td></tr>
<tr><td>rdseed</td><td>Non-deterministic random bit generator</td><td>SP 800-90B &amp; C (drafts)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The numbers returned by <mim>rdseed</mim> are referred to as "seed-grade entropy" and are the output of a true random number generator (TRNG),
or an enhanced non-deterministic random number generator (ENRNG) in NIST-speak.
<mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for use by software vendors who have an existing PRNG, but would like to benefit from the harsware entropy source.
With <mim>rdseed</mim> you can seed a PRNG of any size.
</p>

<p>The numbers returned by <mim>rdseed</mim> have multiplicative prediction resistance.
If you use two 64-bit samples with multiplicative prediction resistance to build a 128-bit value,
you end up with a random number with 128 bits of prediction resistance (<formula>2<sup>128</sup><times/>2<sup>128</sup> = 2<sup>256</sup></formula>).
Combine two of those 128-bit values together, and you get a 256-bit number with 256 bits of prediction resistance.
You can continue in this fashion to build a random value of arbitrary width and the prediction resistance will always scale with it.
Because its values have multiplicative prediction resistance <mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for seeding other PRNGs.
</p>

<p>In contrast, <mim>rdrand</mim> is the output of a 128-bit PRNG that is compliant to <quote>NIST SP 800-90A</quote>.
It is intended for applications that simply need high-quality random numbers.
The numbers returned by <mim>rdrand</mim> have additive prediction resistance because they are the output of a pseudorandom number generator.
If you put two 64-bit values with additive prediction resistance togehter,
the prediction resistance of the resulting value is only 65 bits (<formula>2<sup>64</sup>+2<sup>64</sup>=2<sup>65</sup></formula>).
To ensure that <mim>rdrand</mim> values are fully prediction-resistant when combined together to build larger values
you can follow the procedures in the <quote>DRNG Software Implementation Guide</quote> on generating seed values from <mim>rdrand</mim>,
but it's generally best and simplest to just use <mim>rdseed</mim> for PRNG seeding.
</p>

<p>The decision for which instruction to use is based on what the output will be used for.
Use <mim>rdseed</mim> if you wish to seed another pseudorandom number generator (PRNG), use <mim>rdrand</mim> for all other purposes.
<mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for seeding a software PRNG of arbitrary width.
<mim>rdrand</mim> is intended for applications that merely require high-quality random numbers.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "cpuid">
<title>CPU identification instructions</title>

<p>The <mem>cpuid</mem> instruction is used to dynamically identify which features of <archname/> are implemented in the running processor during the execution of the software.
The realization of the functional characteristics of these instruction systems is recorded in the series of configuration information words.
One configuration information word can be read once the <mem>cpuid</mem> instruction is executed.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption><mem>cpuid</mem> instruction format</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <stride>offset</stride>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Syntax:</p>
<code>cpuid ra, rb, imm14</code>

<p>When using the <mem>cpuid</mem> instruction, the number of the configuration information word to be accessed is calculated as gr[base]+offset,
and the configuration information word information read after the instruction is executed is written into the general register dst.
Each configuration information word is 64 bits, which is written into the result register after the zero extension.
</p>

<p>The configuration information word contains series of configuration bits (fields).
For example, The PALEN field of the number of physical address bits supported by the 11th to 4th digits of the configuration word No.1 is recorded as cpuid.1.PALEN[11:4].
</p>

<p>The configuration information accessible by the <mem>cpuid</mem> instruction is listed in the table below.
<mem>cpuid</mem> access to undefined configuration words causes general protection exception.
The reserved fields in the defined configuration words read back zero values.
</p>

<table>
<thead><tr>
<th>Word number</th>
<th>Bit field</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0</td><td>31:0</td>
<td>number of implemented configuration words</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">1</td>
<td>47:32</td>
<td>vendor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31:16</td>
<td>version</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15:0</td>
<td>revision</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>1</td><td>63:0</td><td>capabilities flags</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1I info</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>63:0</td><td>L2D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>63:0</td><td>L3D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1 ITLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>7</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1 DTLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>8</td><td>63:0</td><td>L2 TLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>9</td><td>63:0</td><td>PMR info</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

</section>

<section id = "emulator">
<title>Instructions for the emulation support</title>

<p>Currently the OS and standard libraries are not implemented for the virtual processor,
therefore, a few special instructions have been added to mimic their minimal emulation.
</p>

<p>The <mim>ldr</mim> instruction for the forward address loading should not be used for storing result in <reg>r0</reg> register, which contains link info.
So writing to <reg>r0</reg> is ignored and this <mim>ldr</mim> instruction form is used for formatting output.
</p>

<p>The <mim>write</mim> pseudo-instruction is for outputting a formatted string.
An unsigned 28-bit <reg>ip</reg>-relative offset gives a maximum distance of 256 MiB forward from the current position for a one-slot instruction
and all available address space for a long instruction.
The <mim>write</mim> instruction allows the continuation of the immediate value in the instruction code to the next bundle slot with the formation of a dual-slot instruction.
It is assumed that the effective address point to a zero-terminated string.
In assembler, you can use both labels on strings in the rodata section, and directly strings
(the assembler will place them in the rodata section and insert the offset into the instruction).
</p>

<p>ea = <reg>ip</reg> + zext(disp)</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>write</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>r0</gpr>
    <jump>disp (28 bits)</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The following formatters are used to display the content of the current core registers.
The common syntax is <quote>%formatter(register)</quote> or <quote>%m(command)</quote>.
</p>

<table width="88%">
<caption>write formatters</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th width="40%">formatter</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>%%</td><td>%</td></tr>
<tr><td>%c</td><td>low part of general register as a 1-byte character</td></tr>
<tr><td>%i8, %i16, %i32, %i64</td><td>low part of general register as a signed decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%u8, %u16, %u32, %u64</td><td>low part of general register as a unsigned decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%x8, %x16, %x32, %x64, %x128</td><td>low part of general register as a unsigned hexadecimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%b8, %b16, %b32, %b64</td><td>low part of general register as a binary value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%f32, %f64, %f128</td><td>low part of general register as a floating-point value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vf32, %vf64</td><td>general register as a vector of floating-point values</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vi8, %vi16, %vi32, %vi64</td><td>general register as a vector of signed decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vu8, %vu16, %vu32, %vu64</td><td>general register as a vector of unsigned decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vx8, %vx16, %vx32, %vx64</td><td>general register as a vector of hexadecimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%m(dump)</td><td>full core state dump</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>An instruction without parameters <mim>halt</mim> is used to shut down the emulator.
In fact, it is intended to be hardware, and serves to turn off the processor core
(the deepest level of sleep, without saving a state, from which you can exit only by the reset signal, which is equivalent to disconnecting),
but implemented as emulator.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>halt</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

</chapter>
