<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="cpu_extended">
<title>Extended instruction set</title>

<preface>
<p>This chapter describes the <em>extended</em> virtual processor instruction set which was not included in the basic set.
</p>
</preface>

<section id = "load_address">
<title>Helper Address Calculation Instructions</title>

<p>To simplify addressing, several instructions have been introduced that calculate effective addresses without going to memory.
The <mim>lda_xi64</mim>, <mim>lda_xu64</mim>, <mim>lda_xi32</mim>, <mim>lda_xu32</mim> instructions return the effective address as indexed addressing.</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>lda_x</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <scale>scale</scale>
    <indexed_opx>opx</indexed_opx>
    <idisp>simm7</idisp>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>lda_r</mim> (<miname>compute address relative</miname>) calculates the <reg>ip</reg>-relative base address as jump instruction.
The first argument is the number of the result register, the second is the distance in the instruction bundles from the current position
(in assembler, this is a label in the code section, or a label in the immutable data section, aligned on a 16-byte boundary).
It is used to get the base address of immutable data from a code section, function address or label.
The instruction doesn't generate interrupts.
</p>

<code>lda_r dst, label</code>

<p>This instruction is necessary for position-independent code to get the absolute address of objects,
stored at a fixed distance from the current position, for example, intra-module procedures or unchanged local module data.
On systems like MAS (<em>Multiple Address Spaces</em>) with multiple address spaces,
where the module's private data is stored at a fixed distance from the code section,
it can also be used to obtain the base absolute address of the module's private data.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>lda_r</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <jump>simm28x16</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <reserved size="10">0</reserved>
    <imm size="32">simm60x16 (28+32)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction is formed according to the LDA_R rule.
The result register is followed by a 28-bit field for encoding the displacement relative to the instruction counter.
The data block must be aligned with at least a 16-byte boundary, since the displacement expresses the distance in instruction bundles, not bytes.
The general formula for obtaining the address:</p>

<p><param>dst</param> = <reg>ip</reg> + 16 <times/> sign_extend(<param>offset</param>)</p>

<p>Displacement field 28 bits long (64 bits for double instruction) after sign extension
and left shift by 4 positions is added to the contents of the instruction counter <reg>ip</reg>,
to produce a 64-bit effective address.
The maximum distance for a one-slot instruction is 2 GiB on either side of the instruction counter.
The <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction allows the continuation of the immediate value in the instruction code
to the next slot of the bundle with the formation of a double-slot instruction.</p>

<p>The <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction might be used to compute address of the static module data.
But specially for this the another instruction <mim>lda_iprel</mim> is intended (compute address forward relative),
which allow to address any address, not only 16-byte bundle-aligned.
It computes effective address same as all <reg>ip</reg>-relative load/store instructions.
This reduces the maximal available distance 16 times, so only forward references with unsigned displacement are possible, so distance reduction is 8 times only.
To use <mim>lda_iprel</mim>, the distance from the current bundle to the data should not exceed 256 MiB.
Usually 256 MiB is enough for any module.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>lda_iprel</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <jump>uimm28</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <reserved size="6">0</reserved>
    <imm size="36">uimm64(28+36)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p><param>dst</param> = <reg>ip</reg> + zero_extend(<param>label</param>)</p>


<p>If a constant with a sign is fits in 28 bits, then it's more efficient to use the <mim>ld_imm</mim> instruction,
and if fits in 56 bits then <mim>ld_imm</mim> along with <mim>lda_n</mim>.
However, when loading constants in bulk, a single <mim>lda_r</mim> instruction falls on several loading instructions,
and then a pair of <mim>ld_imm</mim> and <mim>lda_n</mim> <ndash/> instructions is less compact than a single <mim>ld_u32</mim> instruction.
As for loading 8-byte integer constants, real constants, vector constants, then
using <mim>lda_r</mim> along with <mim>ld_u64</mim>, <mim>ld_u32</mim> and other download instructions,
is the recommended, and often the only possible way to load such constants.
</p>

<p>Base plus displacement addressing allows 1 MiB addressing to both sides of the base address when using one-slot instructions (21-bit displacement).
If the object is beyond 1 MiB, you will have to use double-slot instructions.
But, according to the principle of <strong>access locality</strong>,
with a high probability the program will access next objects located near the first one.
This fact can be used, and once calculate the base address, from which several necessary objects
are located no further than 1 MiB, and then use one-slot instructions to address them.
</p>

<p>Nearest Base Address Calculation Instructions <mim>lda_n</mim> (<miname>compute address near</miname>).
It is used to optimize local (by place and time) memory access without using double-slot instructions and long displacements.
Another nearest base address instruction <mim>lda_nrc</mim> (<miname>compute address near relative consistent</miname>).
</p>

<code>lda_n   dst, base, simm
lda_nrc dst, base, simm</code>

<p>First argument is the result register number,
second is base address register number,
the third is an immediate value is 14 bits long (or 56 bits for a long instruction), extended to 64 bits.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>lda_n</mim>, <mim>lda_nrc</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <mid_binimm>simm14</mid_binimm>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <imm size="42">simm56(14+42)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The target 64-bit address is calculated (for <mim>lda_n</mim> and <mim>lda_nrc</mim>) as:</p>

<p><param>dst</param> = <param>base</param> + (simm14 <lshift/> 20)</p>
<p><param>dst</param> = <reg>ip</reg> + <param>base</param> + (simm14 <lshift/> 20)</p>

<p>The following example shows how to use the <mim>lda_n</mim> instruction
to access a group of closely spaced (no more than 512 KiB from each other),
but far-away data (the distance to the <param>sym</param> object is more than 512 KiB from the base address).
</p>

<p>Without using <mim>lda_n</mim> (4 double instructions, 8 slots)
</p>

<code>ld_i32.l  %r1, base, sym + 4
ld_u32.l %r2, base, sym + 8
st_i64.l  %r2, base, sym + 16
ld_u64.l %r3, base, sym + 32</code>

<p>Using <mim>lda_n</mim> (5 single instructions, 5 slots)
</p>

<code>lda_n   tmp, base, data_hi (sym); put the nearest address in tmp
ld_i32  g11, tmp, data_lo (sym) +4; tmp addressing
ld_u32  g12, tmp, data_lo (sym) +8
st_i64  g12, tmp, data_lo (sym) +16
ld_u64  g13, tmp, data_lo (sym) +32</code>

</section>

<section id="multprecision">
<title>Multiprecision arithmetic</title>

<p>For hardware support for long arithmetic, it is advisable to add special instructions.
In the general case, for intermediate addition/subtraction of parts of high precision numbers
it is required to specify the incoming carry (borrow), two operands, the result and the outgoing carry (borrow).
</p>

<p>When explicitly coding all dependencies and not using global flags (which is good for parallel/pipeline execution of instructions)
it requires 5 parameters: the result, two operands, input and output carry/borrow.
There is not enough space in the instructions for all five parameters.
Therefore, the high part of 128-bit registers is used to return the carry/borrow.
</p>

<p>A special instruction <mim>mulh</mim> (<miname>multiply high</miname>) was introduced for hardware support for multiplying long numbers
calculating the upper half of a 128-bit product of two 64-bit numbers.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>addc</mim>, <mim>subb</mim>, <mim>mulh</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <gpr>rc</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>add_addc</mim>, <mim>sub_subb</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <gpr>rc</gpr>
    <gpr>rd</gpr>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Syntax:</p>
<code>addc_u64      ra, rb, rc
add_addc_u64  ra, rb, rc, rd
subb_u64      ra, rb, rc
sub_subb_u64  ra, rb, rc, rd
mulh          ra, rb, rc
</code>

<table>
<caption>Fused instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Operation</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td><mim>addc_u64</mim></td><td><miname>add to u128</miname></td><td>ra = (u128 zext u64:rb) + (u128 zext u64:rc)</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>subb_u64</mim></td><td><miname>subtract to u128</miname></td><td>ra = (u128 zext u64:rb) - (u128 zext u64:rc)</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>add_addc_u64</mim></td><td><miname>add 3 with carry</miname></td><td>ra = (u128 zext u64:rb) + (u128 zext u64:rc) + (u128:rd >> 64)</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>sub_subb_u64</mim></td><td><miname>subtract 3 with borrow</miname></td><td>ra =  (u128 zext u64:rb) - (u128 zext u64:rc) - (u128:rd >> 64)</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>
It is assumed that numbers of arbitrary length are already loaded into the registers.
For example, the addition of 256-bit numbers will occur as follows:
</p>
<code>addc_u64      a1, b1, c1      ; sum of lower parts, first carry-out
add_addc_u64  a2, b2, c2, a1  ; sum of middles and carry-in, next carry-out
add_addc_u64  a3, b3, c3, a2  ; sum of middles and carry-in, next carry-out
add_addc_u64  a4, b4, c4, a3  ; sum of higher and carry-in, last carry-out
</code>

</section>

<section id="syscall">
<title>Software interrupts, system calls</title>

<p>The instruction <mim>syscall</mim> (<miname>system call</miname>) does the call to the kernel of the system to process the system request.
The system call number is obtained from <reg>r1</reg>, arguments from subsequent registers.
</p>

<p>Unlike interrupts, a system call is an analogue of a function call, and has similarly implemented return from it to the next bundle.
Therefore, after the instruction <mim>syscall</mim> in assembler, you need to put a label to ensure that the subsequent instructions fall into the new bundle.
Bits of future predication are cleared.
</p>

<p>The first <reg>frame</reg> registers are rotated, and return address is stored in zero register in the new frame.
Subsequent local registers contain syscall arguments.
</p>

<p>The <mim>sysret</mim> (<miname>system return</miname>) instruction returns from the system request handler, which was called using <mim>syscall</mim>.
The instruction use the return address and frame state from zero register.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>syscall</mim>, <mim>sysret</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The instruction <mim>int</mim> (<miname>interrupt</miname>) is provided for sending interrupts to the current core themselves programmatically.
The sent interrupt doesn't happen synchronously to the instruction thread, but it can be delayed until the moment when this vector is unmasked.
For the user-mode program, when all interrupts are unmasked, the sent interrupt is happen synchronously to the instruction thread.
The interrupt index is calculated as <formula><param>src</param> + simm10</formula>.
The instruction support both styles of interrupt code passing: hardcoded codes with zero register <reg>gz</reg> or dynamic code pasing.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>int</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <stride>simm10</stride>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The <mim>rfi</mim> instruction (<miname>return from interruption</miname>) returns from the interrupt handler.
It returns to the beginning of the bundle containing the interrupted incomplete instruction (in case of an error),
or to a bundle containing the subsequent instruction (in the case of a trap).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>rfi</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id = "cipher_hash_instructions">
<title>Cipher and hash instructions</title>

<table>
<caption>AES/hash instructions</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Operation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_dec</mim>           ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>aes decrypt round</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_dec_last</mim>      ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>aes decrypt last round</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_enc</mim>           ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>aes encrypt round</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_enc_last</mim>      ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>aes encrypt last round</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_imc</mim>           ra, rb</pre></td><td>aes inverse mix columns</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>aes_keygen_assist</mim> ra, rb, uimm8</pre></td><td>aes key generation assist</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>clmul_ll</mim>          ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>carry-less multiply low parts</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>clmul_hl</mim>          ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>carry-less multiply high and low parts</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>clmul_hh</mim>          ra, rb, rc</pre></td><td>carry-less multiply high parts</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>crc32c</mim>            ra, rb, rc, rd</pre></td><td>crc32c hash</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aes_enc</mim>, <mim>aes_enc_last</mim>, <mim>aes_dec</mim>, <mim>aes_dec_last</mim>, <mim>clmul</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src1</gpr>
    <gpr>src2</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aes_imc</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>aes_keygen_assist</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <stride>round constant</stride>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>crc32c</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>prev</gpr>
    <gpr>data</gpr>
    <gpr>len</gpr>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The <mim>crc32c</mim> instruction computes crc32c hash.
The new hash value is based on previous hash value <quote>prev</quote>.
The hashed data is in register <quote>data</quote>.
The len parameter may be any value. If it is bigger than 16, only 16 bytes of data in register data is used.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "random_generator">
<title>Random number generation instruction</title>

<p>The special instructions <mim>random</mim> are designed to generate random variables.
Reading from it returns the next 64-bit random number.
The instruction returns random numbers that are compliant to the <quote>U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</quote> standards on random number generators.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>random</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The src operand specifies the used random generator.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr><th>Instruction</th><th>Source</th><th>NIST Compliance</th></tr>
</thead><tbody>
<tr><td>rdrand(0)</td><td>Cryptographically secure pseudorandom number generator</td><td>SP 800-90A</td></tr>
<tr><td>rdseed(1)</td><td>Non-deterministic random bit generator</td><td>SP 800-90B &amp; C (drafts)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The numbers returned by <mim>rdseed</mim> are referred to as "seed-grade entropy" and are the output of a true random number generator (TRNG),
or an enhanced non-deterministic random number generator (ENRNG) in NIST-speak.
<mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for use by software vendors who have an existing PRNG, but would like to benefit from the harsware entropy source.
With <mim>rdseed</mim> you can seed a PRNG of any size.
</p>

<p>The numbers returned by <mim>rdseed</mim> have multiplicative prediction resistance.
If you use two 64-bit samples with multiplicative prediction resistance to build a 128-bit value,
you end up with a random number with 128 bits of prediction resistance (<formula>2<sup>128</sup><times/>2<sup>128</sup> = 2<sup>256</sup></formula>).
Combine two of those 128-bit values together, and you get a 256-bit number with 256 bits of prediction resistance.
You can continue in this fashion to build a random value of arbitrary width and the prediction resistance will always scale with it.
Because its values have multiplicative prediction resistance <mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for seeding other PRNGs.
</p>

<p>In contrast, <mim>rdrand</mim> is the output of a 128-bit PRNG that is compliant to <quote>NIST SP 800-90A</quote>.
It is intended for applications that simply need high-quality random numbers.
The numbers returned by <mim>rdrand</mim> have additive prediction resistance because they are the output of a pseudorandom number generator.
If you put two 64-bit values with additive prediction resistance togehter,
the prediction resistance of the resulting value is only 65 bits (<formula>2<sup>64</sup>+2<sup>64</sup>=2<sup>65</sup></formula>).
To ensure that <mim>rdrand</mim> values are fully prediction-resistant when combined together to build larger values
you can follow the procedures in the <quote>DRNG Software Implementation Guide</quote> on generating seed values from <mim>rdrand</mim>,
but it's generally best and simplest to just use <mim>rdseed</mim> for PRNG seeding.
</p>

<p>The decision for which generator to use is based on what the output will be used for.
Use <mim>rdseed</mim> if you wish to seed another pseudorandom number generator (PRNG), use <mim>rdrand</mim> for all other purposes.
<mim>rdseed</mim> is intended for seeding a software PRNG of arbitrary width.
<mim>rdrand</mim> is intended for applications that merely require high-quality random numbers.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "cpuid">
<title>CPU identification instructions</title>

<p>The <mim>cpuid</mim> instruction is used to dynamically identify which features of <archname/> are implemented in the running processor.
The realization of the functional characteristics of these instruction systems is recorded in the series of configuration information words.
One configuration information word can be read once the <mim>cpuid</mim> instruction is executed.
The configuration information word number to be accessed is computed as <param>index</param>+sext(imm10).
The 64-bit configuration information is written into the general register dst.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption><mim>cpuid</mim> instruction format</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <stride>simm10</stride>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Syntax:</p>
<code>cpuid ra, rb, simm10</code>

<p>The configuration information accessible by the <mim>cpuid</mim> instruction is listed in the table below.
<mim>cpuid</mim> access to undefined configuration words causes general protection exception.
The reserved fields in the defined configuration words read back zero values.
</p>

<table>
<thead><tr>
<th>Word number</th>
<th>Bit field</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0</td><td>31:0</td>
<td>number of implemented configuration words</td></tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">1</td>
<td>47:32</td>
<td>vendor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31:16</td>
<td>version</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15:0</td>
<td>revision</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>1</td><td>63:0</td><td>capabilities flags</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1I info</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>63:0</td><td>L2D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>63:0</td><td>L3D info</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1 ITLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>7</td><td>63:0</td><td>L1 DTLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>8</td><td>63:0</td><td>L2 TLB</td></tr>
<tr><td>9</td><td>63:0</td><td>PMR info</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

</section>

<section id = "emulator">
<title>Instructions for the emulation support</title>

<p>Currently the OS and standard libraries are not implemented for the virtual processor.
Therefore, a few special instructions have been added to mimic their minimal emulation.
</p>

<p>The <mim>write</mim> instruction is for outputting a formatted string.
It uses the forward ip-relative addressing to address the format string.
An unsigned 28-bit <reg>ip</reg>-relative displacement gives a maximum distance of 256 MiB forward from the current position for a one-slot instruction
and all available address space for a long instruction.
The <mim>write</mim> instruction allows the continuation of the immediate value in the instruction code
to the next bundle slot with the formation of a double-slot instruction.
It is assumed that the effective address point to a zero-terminated string.
In assembler, you can use both labels on strings in the rodata section, and directly strings
(the assembler will place them in the rodata section and insert the displacement into the instruction).
</p>

<p>ea = <reg>ip</reg> + zext(disp)</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>write</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <jump>uimm28(64)</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The following formatters are used to display the content of the current core registers.
The common syntax is <quote>%formatter(register)</quote> or <quote>%m(command)</quote>.
</p>

<table>
<caption>write formatters</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>formatter</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>%%</td><td>%</td></tr>
<tr><td>%c</td><td>low part of general register as a 1-byte character</td></tr>
<tr><td>%i8, %i16, %i32, %i64</td><td>low part of general register as a signed decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%u8, %u16, %u32, %u64</td><td>low part of general register as a unsigned decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%x8, %x16, %x32, %x64, %x128</td><td>low part of general register as a unsigned hexadecimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%b8, %b16, %b32, %b64</td><td>low part of general register as a binary value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%f32, %f64, %f128</td><td>low part of general register as a floating-point value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vf32, %vf64</td><td>general register as a vector of floating-point values</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vi8, %vi16, %vi32, %vi64</td><td>general register as a vector of signed decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vu8, %vu16, %vu32, %vu64</td><td>general register as a vector of unsigned decimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%vx8, %vx16, %vx32, %vx64</td><td>general register as a vector of hexadecimal value</td></tr>
<tr><td>%m(dump)</td><td>full core state dump</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The instruction <mim>halt</mim> without parameters is intended to turn off the processor core,
switching it to the deepest level of sleep, without saving a state, from which core may exit only by the reset signal.
But in emulator this instruction serves to shut down the emulator.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>halt</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<note>The <mim>halt</mim> instruction is not used in unittests,
because it is automatically added for each test source by test scripts.
</note>

</section>

</chapter>
