<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="pal">
<title>PAL (Privileged Architecture Library)</title>

<preface>
<p>In a family of binary compatible machines, application and operating system developers require
so that the hardware functions are implemented sequentially (uniformly).
When functions correspond to a common interface, code using these functions
can be used by several different architecture implementations without modification.</p>

<p>These can be such functions as: binary code of instructions and data, exception mechanisms, synchronization primitives.
Some of these functions can be implemented cost-effectively in hardware,
other functions are impractical to carry out directly in the equipment.
These features include low-level hardware features such as
miss buffer translation routines; interrupt handling; interrupt vector control.
They also include support for privileged and atomic operations that require long sequences of instructions.</p>

<p>In earlier architectures, these functions were usually provided with microcode.
Modern architectures try not to use microcode mechanisms.
However, it is still desirable to provide an architectural interface to these functions, which will be compatible for the entire family of machines.
The Privileged Architecture Library or PAL (Privileged Architecture Library) provides a mechanism for implementing these functions without microcode.</p>

<p>Three main components of Privileged Architecture Library:
Processor Abstraction Layer (PAL), System Abstraction Layer (SAL),
Extensible Firmware Interface (EFI).
PAL, SAL, and EFI together initialize the processor and system before and for loading the operating system.
PAL and SAL also provide machine check abort handling and other processor and system functions that may vary from implementation to implementation.</p>

<p><def>Extensible Firmware Interface</def> (EFI) is the firmware layer that isolates the operating system loader from the details (differences)
in the implementation of the platform and processor and organizes the basic functionality for controlling a machine without an OS.</p>

<p><def>System Abstraction Layer</def> (SAL) is the firmware layer that isolates the operating system, the overlying EFI layer,
and other high-level software from the details (differences) in the implementation of the platform.</p>

<p><def>Processor Abstraction Layer</def> (PAL) is a software layer that abstracts the details of the processor implementation and isolates them from all:
from the operating system, from the EFI layer and from the SAL layer.
PAL is independent of the number of processors in the system.
PAL encapsulates processor functions that are likely to change from implementation to implementation, so that SAL, EFI, and OS are independent of the processor version.
This includes non-performance-critical functions, such as processor initialization, configuration, and correction of internal errors.
PAL consists of two components:</p>

<ul>
<li>Entry points that are called directly by special hardware interrupts,
such as RESET (hardware cold start), INIT (software warm restart),
CHECK (error recovery), PMI (platform management interrupt).</li>
<li>Procedures that may be called by the upper layers of the software to obtain information
about identification, configuration, processor implementation capabilities;
to perform implementation-dependent functions, such as cache initialization;
or to allow software to interact with the hardware through such functions
like power management or enable/disable processor features.</li>
</ul>

<p>The PAL address space occupies a maximum of 2 GB of physical address space.
The PAL space contains addresses from <hex>0x80000000</hex> to <hex>0xffffffff</hex> inclusive.
Code execution after restart starts with the address <hex>0x80000000</hex>.</p>

</preface>

<section id="pal_instructions">
<title>PAL instructions and functions</title>

<p>PAL should perform the following functions:</p>
<ul>
<li>instructions that perform a complex sequence as an atomic operation;</li>
<li>privileged instructions;</li>
<li>memory management, including translation buffer management (TLB);</li>
<li>change of context;</li>
<li>handling interruptions and exceptions;</li>
<li>power-on initialization and boot (zero OS);</li>
<li>low-level console output functions;</li>
<li>instruction emulation without hardware support.</li>
</ul>

<p>The architecture allows these functions to be implemented in standard machine code, which residently resides in main memory.
The PAL library is written in standard machine code with some implementation-specific extensions,
to provide access to low-level hardware.
This allows the implementation to make various project exchanges based on the used hardware technology.
The PAL library allows you to abstract these differences and make them invisible to system software.</p>

<p>The PAL environment differs from the normal environment in the following ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>Complete machine state management.</li>

<li>Interrupts are blocked.</li>

<li>Implementation-specific hardware functions are allowed as described below.</li>

<li>Memory management should prevent the execution thread from being captured
(disable display for PAL code, display PAL with a fixed TLB input, or other mechanisms).</li>
</ul>

<p>Full control of the state of the machine allows you to manage all the functions of the machine.
Disabling interrupts allows you to provide sequences of several instructions as atomic operation.
Providing implementation-specific hardware features allows access to low-level system hardware.
Preventing memory management Captures I-stream allows PAL to implement memory management functions such as filling the translation buffer.</p>

<p>Special Features Required for PAL</p>

<p>PAL uses the <archname/> instruction set for most of its operations.
A small number of additional functions are required to implement PAL.
Some of the free primary and/or extended opcodes can be used for PAL functions.
These instructions generate an error if executed outside the PAL environment.</p>

<ul>
<li>PAL needs a mechanism to maintain the current state of the machine and branch to PAL.</li>
<li>PAL needs a set of instructions to access the hardware control registers.</li>
<li>PAL needs a hardware mechanism to transition the machine from a PAL environment to a non-PAL environment.
This mechanism loads <reg>ip</reg>, allows interrupts, allows display, and disables PAL privileges.</li>
</ul>

<p>Having PAL will have only one effect on system code.
Because PAL can fit in main memory and support privileged data structures in main memory,
the operating system code that allocates the physical memory cannot use all of the physical memory.
The amount of memory required by the PAL is small, so the loss for the system is negligible.</p>

</section>

<section id="pal_changes">
<title>PAL replacement</title>

<p><archname/> systems require that you can replace PAL with a version defined by the operating system.
The following functions can be implemented in PAL code, not directly in the hardware, to facilitate the replacement with different versions.</p>

<p><strong>Fill translation buffer.</strong> Various operating systems may wish to replace the translation buffer fill (TLB) routines.
Substitution routines will use different data structures for page tables.
Therefore, no part of the TLB padding tools that would change with a change in the page tables can be placed in hardware,
if it cannot be canceled by the PAL code.</p>

<p><strong>Process structure.</strong> Various operating systems may wish to replace the process context switch routines.
Substitution routines will use different data structures.
Therefore, no part of the context switching threads that would change with a change in the structure of the process can be placed in hardware.</p>

<p>PAL consists of three components:</p>
<ul>
<li>chip/architecture components</li>
<li>platform hardware component</li>
<li>operating system component</li>
</ul>

</section>

<comment>
<p>PAL should be written modularly to facilitate easy replacement or conditional expression of each component.
This practice simplifies the integration of CPU hardware,
system hardware platform, console programmable equipment,
operating system software, and translators.
PAL subsections, which are usually subordinate to modification, include:</p>

<ul>
<li>fill the translation buffer;</li>
<li>process structure and context switch;</li>
<li>interruption and exception create format and standard dispatch;</li>
<li>privileged PAL instructions;</li>
<li>transitions to console mode IO and back;</li>
<li>reset or power on.</li>
</ul>

<subsection id="barriers">
<title>Barriers</title>

<p>The first register is the result. The second and third are operands. Extended opcode takes 6 bits.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>OPX</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>EXCB</td><td>Exception barrier</td><td>4</td></tr>
<tr><td>TRAPB</td><td>Trap barrier</td><td>5</td></tr>
<tr><td>MB</td><td>Memory barrier</td><td>6</td></tr>
<tr><td>WMB</td><td>Write memory barrier</td><td>7</td></tr>
<tr><td>get_spr</td><td>get special register</td><td>8</td></tr>
<tr><td>set_spr</td><td>set special register</td><td>9</td></tr>
<tr><td>DSSTOP</td><td>Stops cache touches for MASK stream</td><td>10</td></tr>
<tr><td>DSTL</td><td>Cache touches for N loads</td><td>12</td></tr>
<tr><td>DSTS</td><td>Cache touches for N stores</td><td>13</td></tr>
<tr><td>LDDL</td><td>load double word locked</td><td>14</td></tr>
<tr><td>STDC</td><td>store double word conditional</td><td>15</td></tr>
<tr><td>LDQL</td><td>load quadruple word locked</td><td>16</td></tr>
<tr><td>STQC</td><td>store quadruple word conditional</td><td>17</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Instructions EXCB, TRAPB, MB, WMB - barriers used for serialization of instructions and synchronization.
EXCB Exceptions barrier completion of all instructions that may cause an interrupt
TRAPB Trap barrier completion of all instructions that may cause an interrupt
MB Memory barrier completion of all load/store operations with shared memory
WMB Write memory barrier completion of all write operations to shared memory
Optional instructions LDDL, STDC, LDWL, STWC are used to organize blocked access to shared memory.
</p>

<code>LDDL a = dword [b], lock
STDC dword [b] = a, unlock
LDWL a = word [b], lock
STWC word [b] = a, unlock
</code>

</subsection>
</comment>

</chapter>

