<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="physical_memory">
<title>Physical memory</title>

<preface>
<p>From the most applications point of view, memory is defined as a linear array of bytes,
indexed from 0 to <formula>2<sup>64</sup><minus/>1</formula>.
Each byte is identified by its index or address, and each byte contains a value.
This information is sufficient for programming applications that do not require
special features in any system environment.
Other objects are constructed as sequences of bytes.
</p>

<p>The architecture supports composite types of size 1,2,4,8,16 bytes.
It is considered that the word size is 4 bytes.
The following is the terminology used in this guide for composite data types:
<def>byte</def> is a 8 contiguous bits starting at an arbitrarily addressable byte boundary.
<def>halfword</def> is a 2 contiguous bytes starting on an arbitrary (usually multiple of two) byte boundary.
<def>word</def> is a 4 contiguous bytes starting on an arbitrary (usually multiple of four) byte boundary.
<def>doubleword</def> is a 8 contiguous bytes starting on an arbitrary (usually multiple of eight) byte boundary.
<def>quadword</def> is a 16 contiguous bytes starting on an arbitrary (usually multiple of 16) byte boundary.</p>

<p>The bits inside each type are numbered from right to left from 0 to maximum.</p>

<p>This chapter additionally defines physical addressing, physical memory map, physical memory properties, memory ordering.
</p>

<p>An extension of simple memory model include:
virtual memory, cache, memory mapped IO,
multiprocessor systems with shared memory, and, together with services,
provided by the operating system, describes the mechanism
which allows explicit management of this extended memory model.
</p>

<p>A simple sequential execution model allows at most one memory access at a time and requires
so that all memory accesses seemed to be executed in program order.
Unlike this simple model, a relaxed memory model is further defined.
In multiprocessor systems that allow multiple locations of data copies,
aggressive architecture implementations can allow time intervals during which different copies have different meanings.
</p>

<p>The program accesses the memory using the effective address calculated by the processor,
when it performs a download, write, jump, or cache management instruction, and when it selects the next sequential instruction.
The effective address is converted to a physical address according to the translation procedures.
The physical address is used by the memory subsystem to execute memory access.
The memory model provides the following features:
</p>

<p>Architecture allows memory to take advantage of benefits
efficiency from poor sequencing of memory access between processors or between processors and external devices.
</p>

<p>Memory accesses by a single processor seem to be completed sequentially from the point of view of the programming model,
but this may not end in order with respect to the final position in the memory hierarchy.
Order is guaranteed at every level of the memory hierarchy just to access the same address from the same processor.
</p>

<p>The architecture must provide instructions to allow the programmer to guarantee
consistent and ordered state of memory.
</p>

<p>The following defines the resources of the operating system for translating virtual addresses to physical addresses, physical addressing,
memory sequencing and physical memory properties, status registers to support virtual memory management, virtual memory errors.
</p>

</preface>

<section id="mem_physical_addressing">
<title>Physical addressing</title>

<p>The blocks of RAM, ROM, flash, memory mapped IO and other control blocks occupy a common 64-bit physical address space with byte addressing.
Accesses to RAM and the IO address ranges can be performed either through virtual addressing,
by mapping to a 64-bit physical address space, or directly through physical addressing.
</p>

<p>While software should always consider physical addressing as 64-bit,
in fact, only <def>PALEN</def> less than 64 bits of the physical address can be implemented in hardware.
As shown below, the physical address consists of two parts: unimplemented and implemented bits.
At least 40 bits of physical addressing must be implemented.
</p>

<p>The system software can determine the specific value of PALEN by reading the PALEN field of the configuration word with the <mim>cpuid</mim> instruction.
</p>

<p>Not all of these available addresses have real devices under them.
The hardware at startup maps the available address blocks to the physical memory ranges and notifies the system about mapping.
Similarly, the control ranges of the registers of external devices are mapped to physical addresses.
Most physical addresses usually remain unused.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>64-bit physical address</caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="16">reserved</reserved>
    <imm size="48">implemented physical address bits</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>When the processor model doesn't implement all the bits of the physical address, the missing bits must be zero.
If the software generates physical addresses with non-zero unimplemented bits, a runtime error occurs.
Accessing instructions for unimplemented physical addresses results in the error <error>unimplemented instruction address</error>.
Accessing data by unimplemented physical addresses results in the error <error>unimplemented data address</error>.
Any accesses to the implemented but unused addresses end with an asynchronous <error>machine check abort</error> when the platform reports an operation timeout.
The exact machine behavior of the check is implementation-dependent.
</p>

</section>

<section id="mem_alignment">
<title>Data alignment and atomicity</title>

<p>Memory accesses give a significant performance hit when accessing operands, which are not <em>aligned</em> at the natural address boundary.
A naturally-aligned 2-byte number in memory has a zero bit in the low order of the address.
A naturally-aligned 4-byte number in memory has two zero bits in the least significant bits of the address.
A naturally-aligned 8-byte number in memory has three zero bits in the least significant bits of the address.
A 16-byte number, naturally aligned in memory, has four zero bits in the least significant bits of the address.
In general, a naturally aligned object of size <formula>2<sup>N</sup></formula> bytes has N zero bits in the least significant bits of the address.
</p>

<p>Struct data types must provide natural alignment for all of their fields by inserting (<em>paddings</em>).
Additionally, it should be possible to use the structs as elements of an array,
by using the final padding with the strictest alignment among all struct fields.
</p>

<p>Using the example of the following <var>S</var> C language structure,
containing a set of various scalars and a character string, the location of the fields in memory is shown.
</p>

<code>
struct {
   int       a;    /* usual 4 bytes */
   double    b;    /* usual 8 bytes */
   int       c;    /* usual 4 bytes */
   char      d[7];
   short     e;    /* usual 2 bytes */
   int       f;
} S;
</code>

<p>C language rules for mapping structures allow the use of paddings (byte skipping)
to align scalars in memory on natural boundaries.
</p>

<table width="85%">
<caption>Aligned representation of the structure in memory</caption>
<tr>
<td class="bit">0</td>
<td class="bit">1</td>
<td class="bit">2</td>
<td class="bit">3</td>
<td class="bit">4</td>
<td class="bit">5</td>
<td class="bit">6</td>
<td class="bit">7</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="imm" colspan="4">4 bytes (a)</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4">padding</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="fpr" colspan="8">8 bytes (b)</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="gpr" colspan="4">4 bytes (c)</td>
<td class="tdb">d[0]</td>
<td class="tdb">d[1]</td>
<td class="tdb">d[2]</td>
<td class="tdb">d[3]</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="tdb">d[4]</td>
<td class="tdb">d[5]</td>
<td class="tdb">d[6]</td>
<td class="opx">padding</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="2">2 bytes (e)</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="2">padding</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="cpr" colspan="4">4 bytes (f)</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="4">final padding</td>
</tr></table>

<p>In the example, to map the structure to memory, alignment was made along the boundary that is natural for each scalar.
This alignment gives an additional four missing bytes between <var>a</var> and <var>b</var>,
one byte between <var>d</var> and <var>e</var>, and two bytes between <var>e</var> and <var>f</var>.
Since the alignment for the double precision number <var>b</var> is the strictest for this structure,
then the whole structure should be aligned on an 8-byte boundary.
This gives 4 more bytes at the end of the struct.
</p>

<p>Unaligned memory accesses may throw an error <error>Unaligned data address</error>.
<archname/> may not contain any hardware support for unaligned memory accesses,
limiting itself to the installed program handler of the corresponding interrupts.
Therefore, the software is preferred to align all scalar values on their natural boundaries in memory.
</p>

<p>Since the instruction fetch, aligned load/store, and operations with semaphores operate only on aligned target addresses, they are atomic.
The operation is <strong>atomic</strong> if for other agents working with memory (other processors, IO devices),
memory access from our processor is an indivisible transaction (and vice versa).
If our processor stores data to memory, then no other agent will be able to read from memory a mixture of old data and the newly written data replacing them.
Similarly, if our processor reads data, then it will never read from memory a mixture of old data and new-write data replacing them from another agent.
Of course, at the machine architecture level, these rules only apply to <strong>atoms</strong> memory,
that is, correctly aligned objects of 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 bytes in size.
For arbitrary objects in memory, the atomic nature of their change is not guaranteed by architecture, and software tricks must be applied.
</p>

</section>

<section id="mem_byteorder">
<title>Byte order</title>

<p>If scalars (individual data elements or instructions) were indivisible, then there would be no concept of <quote>byte order</quote>.
It makes no sense to consider the order of bits or groups of bits within the smallest addressable memory atom,
because this order for an atom cannot be observed and determined.
The question of order arises only when scalars, which the programmer and processor refer to as indivisible objects,
occupy more than one addressable memory atom.
</p>

<p>For most existing computer architectures, the smallest addressable memory atom is a 8-bit bytes.
Other scalars consist of groups of 2, 4, 8, or 16 bytes in length.
When a 4-byte scalar moves from register to memory, it occupies four consecutive byte addresses.
Thus, it becomes necessary to establish the order of byte addresses relative to the scalar value:
which byte contains the most significant eight bits of the scalar, which byte contains the next eight bits of importance, and so on.
</p>

<p>For a scalar consisting of several atoms (bytes) of memory, the choice of byte order in memory is essentially arbitrary.
There is N! ways to determine the order of N bytes within a long number, but only two of these orderings are actually used.
</p>

<p>The order in which the smallest address is assigned to a byte that contains eight bits of a scalar of the lowest order (the rightmost bits),
the next consecutive address is next in ascending order of eight bits, and so on.
This order is called <def>little-endian</def> because it is least significant (from <em>to the smaller</em> end)
the bits of the scalar, regarded as a binary number, are the first to go into memory.
Intel-X86 is an example of an architecture using this byte order.
</p>

<p>In a little-endian machine, bytes within a large number are numbered from right to left
in decreasing order of byte addresses, so the low byte is stored in memory at the lowest address.
This is a direct byte order (a format for storing and transmitting binary data, in which the least (least significant) bit (byte) is transmitted first.
</p>

<table width="85%">
<tr>
<td class="bit">7</td>
<td class="bit">6</td>
<td class="bit">5</td>
<td class="bit">4</td>
<td class="bit">3</td>
<td class="bit">2</td>
<td class="bit">1</td>
<td class="bit">0</td>
</tr></table>

<p>The order in which the smallest address is assigned to a byte that contains eight bits of a scalar of the highest order (the leftmost bits),
the next consecutive address is the next in descending order of eight bits, and so on.
This order is called <def>big-endian</def> because the most significant ones (from the <em>larger</em> end)
the bits of the scalar, regarded as a binary number, are the first to go into memory.
IBM PowerPC is a sample architecture using this byte order.
</p>

<p>In a big-endian machine, bytes within a large number are numbered from left to right
in ascending order of byte addresses, so the low byte is stored in memory at the highest address.
This is the reverse byte order (a format for storing and transmitting binary data in which the most significant (most significant) byte is transmitted or stored first.
The terms <def>little/big-endian</def> comes from <em>Gulliver's Travel</em> Jonathan Swift.
</p>

<table width="85%"><tr>
<td class="bit">0</td>
<td class="bit">1</td>
<td class="bit">2</td>
<td class="bit">3</td>
<td class="bit">4</td>
<td class="bit">5</td>
<td class="bit">6</td>
<td class="bit">7</td>
</tr></table>

<p>Using the example of the following <var>S</var> structure of the C language containing a set of various scalars and a character string,
shows the location of fields in memory under different conventions on byte order.
Comments show values for each element of the structure.
These values show how the individual bytes that make up each element of the structure are mapped into memory.
</p>

<code>
struct {
   int     a;     /* 0x1112_1314 (4 bytes) */
   double  b;     /* 0x2122_2324_2526_2728 (8 bytes) */
   int     c;     /* 0x3132_3334 (4 bytes) */
   char    d[7];  /* "A","B","C","D","E","F","G" bytes array */
   short   e;     /* 0x5152 (2 bytes) */
   int     f;     /* 0x6162_6364 (4 bytes) */
} S;
</code>

<p>C language rules for mapping structures allow the use of inserts (byte skipping)
to align scalars in memory at desired (natural) boundaries.
In the examples below, the mapping of the structure into memory is done with natural alignment
border for each scalar. This alignment gives an additional four missing bytes
between <var>a</var> and <var>b</var>, one byte between <var>d</var> and <var>e</var>,
and two bytes between <var>e</var> and <var>f</var>.
The same amount of padding is present in big-endian and little-endian mappings.
</p>

<p>The contents of each byte, as defined in the <var>S</var> structure, are displayed as a hexadecimal number or character (for line elements).
Cell addresses (offsets from the beginning of the structure) are shown below the data stored at this address.
</p>

<table width="85%">
<caption>Little-endian structure mapping <var>S</var></caption>
<tr>
<td class="imm">0x14<br/>0</td>
<td class="imm">0x13<br/>1</td>
<td class="imm">0x12<br/>2</td>
<td class="imm">0x11<br/>3</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>4</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>5</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>6</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>7</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="fpr">0x28<br/>8</td>
<td class="fpr">0x27<br/>9</td>
<td class="fpr">0x26<br/>10</td>
<td class="fpr">0x25<br/>11</td>
<td class="fpr">0x24<br/>12</td>
<td class="fpr">0x23<br/>13</td>
<td class="fpr">0x22<br/>14</td>
<td class="fpr">0x21<br/>15</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="gpr">0x34<br/>16</td>
<td class="gpr">0x33<br/>17</td>
<td class="gpr">0x32<br/>18</td>
<td class="gpr">0x31<br/>19</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>A</quote><br/>20</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>B</quote><br/>21</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>C</quote><br/>22</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>D</quote><br/>23</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="tdb"><quote>E</quote><br/>24</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>F</quote><br/>25</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>G</quote><br/>26</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>27</td>
<td class="tdz">0x52<br/>28</td>
<td class="tdz">0x51<br/>29</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>30</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>31</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="cpr">0x64<br/>32</td>
<td class="cpr">0x63<br/>33</td>
<td class="cpr">0x62<br/>34</td>
<td class="cpr">0x61<br/>35</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>36</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>37</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>38</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>39</td>
</tr></table>

<table width="85%">
<caption>Big-endian structure mapping <var>S</var></caption>
<tr>
<td class="imm">0x11<br/>0</td>
<td class="imm">0x12<br/>1</td>
<td class="imm">0x13<br/>2</td>
<td class="imm">0x14<br/>3</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>4</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>5</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>6</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>7</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="fpr">0x21<br/>8</td>
<td class="fpr">0x22<br/>9</td>
<td class="fpr">0x23<br/>10</td>
<td class="fpr">0x24<br/>11</td>
<td class="fpr">0x25<br/>12</td>
<td class="fpr">0x26<br/>13</td>
<td class="fpr">0x27<br/>14</td>
<td class="fpr">0x28<br/>15</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="gpr">0x31<br/>16</td>
<td class="gpr">0x32<br/>17</td>
<td class="gpr">0x33<br/>18</td>
<td class="gpr">0x34<br/>19</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>A</quote><br/>20</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>B</quote><br/>21</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>C</quote><br/>22</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>D</quote><br/>23</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="tdb"><quote>E</quote><br/>24</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>F</quote><br/>25</td>
<td class="tdb"><quote>G</quote><br/>26</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>27</td>
<td class="tdz">0x51<br/>28</td>
<td class="tdz">0x52<br/>29</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>30</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>31</td>
</tr><tr>
<td class="cpr">0x61<br/>32</td>
<td class="cpr">0x62<br/>33</td>
<td class="cpr">0x63<br/>34</td>
<td class="cpr">0x64<br/>35</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>36</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>37</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>38</td>
<td class="opx">padding<br/>39</td>
</tr></table>

<p>For <archname/> architecture, the primary is the little-endian direct order.
All operations on data in registers/memory are carried out according to this order.
Implementations may include optional support for big-endian addressing for loading/storing numbers.
</p>

<p>The bit numbering within bytes doesn't affect the byte numbering convention (big-endian or little-endian).
The byte numbering convention doesn't matter when accessing the full aligned data in memory.
However, the numbering agreement is important when accessing less or not aligned data,
or when manipulating data in registers, as follows:
</p>

<p>Retrieving the 5th byte from an 8-byte number into the low byte of the register requires a right shift
5 bytes according to the little-endian agreement, but the right shift is 2 bytes according to the big-endian agreement.
</p>

<p>The manipulation of data in the register is almost the same for both conventions.
In both integers and floating-point numbers store the sign bits in the leftmost byte and their least significant bit in the rightmost byte,
so the same integer instructions and floating-point instructions are used unchanged for both conventions.
However, big-endian character strings have their most significant character on the left,
while little-endian strings have their most significant character on the right.
</p>

<p>In addition to <strong>little-endian</strong> and <strong>big-endian</strong>,
there are other (combined) options for storing long scalars in memory.
For example, some architecture (PDP-11?) stores double-byte numbers according to the little-endian order,
but 4-byte numbers as pairs of double-byte numbers but according to big-endian order.
It happens that integers are stored according to one principle, and real ones according to another,
for example, if a floating-point coprocessor (ARM, TMS320C4x) is added to the integer processor later.
</p>

</section>

<section id="memory_consistency_model">
<title>Memory consistency model</title>

<p>There are several memory-consistency models for SMP systems:</p>

<ol>
<li>Sequential consistency (all reads and all writes are in-order).</li>
<li>Relaxed consistency (some types of reordering are allowed):</li>
<li><ul>
<li>loads can be reordered after loads (for better working of cache coherency, better scaling),</li>
<li>loads can be reordered after stores,</li>
<li>stores can be reordered after stores,</li>
<li>stores can be reordered after loads.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Weak consistency (reads and writes are arbitrarily reordered, limited only by explicit memory barriers)</li>
</ol>

<p>Atomic operations can be reordered with loads and stores.</p>

<p>The instruction fetching is incoherent with data,
so self-modifying code can't be executed without special instruction cache flush/reload instructions plus maybe jump instructions.
</p>

<p>The <archname/> follows the weak memory model.
And same the weak memory model with acquire loads and release stores also called release-consistency model.
Only the acquire/release atomic instructions are synchronization points.</p>

<table>
<caption>Memory ordering in some architectures</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2" width="20%">Architecture</th>
<th colspan="2" width="20%">Loads can be reordered after</th>
<th colspan="2" width="20%">Stores can be reordered after</th>
<th colspan="2" width="20%">Atomics can be reordered with</th>
<th rowspan="2" width="10%">Dependent loads can be reordered</th>
<th rowspan="2" width="10%">Incoherent instruction cache/<br/>pipeline</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>loads</th>
<th>stores</th>
<th>loads</th>
<th>stores</th>
<th>loads</th>
<th>stores</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Alpha</td>      <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>ARM</td>        <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>RISC-V WMO</td> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>RISC-V TSO</td> <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>PA-RISC</td>    <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    </tr>
<tr><td>POWER</td>      <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>SPARC RMO</td>  <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>SPARC PSO</td>  <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>SPARC TSO</td>  <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>x86</td>        <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>AMD-64</td>     <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    </tr>
<tr><td>IA-64</td>      <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
<tr><td>IBM-Z</td>      <td></td>    <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    <td></td>    </tr>
<tr><td>Postrisc</td>   <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <bit>+</bit> <td></td>    <bit>+</bit> </tr>
</tbody></table>

<note>On Alpha the dependent loads can be reordered.
If the processor first fetches a pointer to some data and then the data,
it might not fetch the data itself but use stale data which it has already cached and not yet invalidated.
Allowing this relaxation makes cache hardware simpler and faster but leads to the requirement of memory barriers for readers and writers.
On Alpha hardware (like multiprocessor Alpha 21264 systems) cache line invalidations sent to other processors are processed in lazy fashion by default,
unless requested explicitly to be processed between dependent loads.
The Alpha architecture specification also allows other forms of dependent loads reordering,
for example using speculative data reads ahead of knowing the real pointer to be dereferenced.
</note>

</section>

<section id="memory_atomics">
<title>Atomic/synchronization instructions</title>

<p>The processor implementation must follow the programmatic order of executing the instructions of a single-threaded program.
But the effects of the actions of one thread on the memory can be observed by other threads not in the programmatic order of this thread 
Depending on the guarantees that the architecture explicitly gives and the permissions that the implementation is explicitly allowed,
talk about a stricter or weaker ordering of memory.
<archname/> is an architecture with weak memory ordering.
There are no obvious restrictions on the visibility of third-party processors or other devices
(for example, input-output) actions on the memory of the current thread.
Similarly, the current thread has no explicit guarantees on the other agents actions visibility order.
</p>

<p>Special <quote>fence</quote> instructions are memory barriers.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format for atomic fences</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<table>
<caption>atomic fence instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Fence instruction</th>
<th>Memory ordering</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><mim>fence_a</mim></td><td>acquire</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>fence_r</mim></td><td>release</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>fence_ar</mim></td><td>acquire-release (acq_rel)</td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>fence_sc</mim></td><td>sequential-consistent (seq_cst)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Special instructions <quote>load-atomic</quote> and <quote>store-atomic</quote>
used to push the visibility of changes from one thread to another.
relaxed - normal operation, acquire - acquire changes, release - submit changes.
Before changing the general data, the thread performs acquire by load-acquire from the watchdog variable.
Similarly, after a change is made to the general data, the stream pushes the changes, executing release by store-release to the watchdog variable.
</p>

<code>INSN_MNEMONIC target, base</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format for atomic load/store</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>target</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>These instructions are one-way barriers.
They do not allow speculative and out-of-order execution of operations with memory through themselves.
Acquire doesn't allow the subsequent instructions to move forward, and release doesn't let the instructions before it lag behind.
With the correct (pairwise) use of acquire-release, a closed section of code is obtained, locked at the top (acquire) and at the bottom (release).
</p>

<table>
<caption>atomic load-store instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Ordering</th>
<th>Instructions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td rowspan="2">load atomic</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">store atomic</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_st_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amq_st_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The <def>load-op</def> atomic instructions copy the old value of a variable from memory to register,
and sets a new value in memory (test-and-set), or obtained from the old (fetch-and-add and analogues).
The possible memory orderings: <type>relaxed</type>, <type>acquire</type>, <type>release</type>, <type>acq_rel</type> (acquire-release).
</p>

<code>ea = <param>base</param>
<param>dst</param> = mem[ea]
mem[ea] = OP(<param>dst</param>, <param>src</param>)
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>load-op</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<code>ld_op_type dst, base, src</code>

<table>
<caption>atomic instructions load-op</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Ordering</th>
<th>Instructions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td rowspan="4">swap</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_swap_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_swap_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_swap_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_swap_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">addition</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">bitwise AND</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">bitwise OR</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">bitwise XOR</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">signed minimum</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">signed maximum</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">unsigned minimum</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="4">unsigned maximum</td><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_ld_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The <def>store-op</def> atomic instructions update value in memory via corresponing operation.
Comparing to <def>load-op</def>, they don't return old variable value from memory to register,
so may be implemented as a one-way communication.
The possible memory orderings: <type>relaxed</type>, <type>acquire</type>, <type>release</type>,
<type>acq_rel</type> (acquire-release), <type>seq_cst</type> (sequentially-consistent).
</p>

<code>ea = <param>base</param>
mem[ea] = mem[ea] op <param>src</param>
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>store-op</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>src</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<code>store_op_type base, src</code>

<table>
<caption>atomic instructions store-op</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Ordering</th>
<th>Instruction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td rowspan="2">addition</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_add_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">bitwise AND</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_and_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">bitwise OR</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_or_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr><td rowspan="2">bitwise XOR</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_xor_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td rowspan="2">signed minimum</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_min_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td rowspan="2">signed maximum</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_max_[i8|i16|i32|i64|i128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td rowspan="2">unsigned minimum</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_min_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_min_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td rowspan="2">unsigned maximum</td>
<td>relaxed</td><td><mim>amx_st_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr><tr>
<td>release</td><td><mim>amr_st_max_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Instructions <mim>cas</mim> (<miname>compare and swap</miname>),
Designed for non-blocking interactions in a multi-threaded multiprocessor environment.
Both instructions are atomic indivisible memory operations that cannot be partially performed.
</p>

<p>The <mim>cas</mim> instruction reads an N-byte number from memory at the address from the <param>base</param> register,
and compares it with the value in the register <param>dst</param>.
If the values match, the instruction saves the new value from the <param>src</param> register at this address.
Otherwise, the instruction doesn't save anything at this address.
The base address must be aligned at the N-byte boundary.
The read value is stored in the register <param>dst</param>.
</p>

<code>value = mem[base]
if (value == expected) {
  mem[base] = desired
}
dst = value
</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of instructions <mim>casX</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>expected</gpr>
    <gpr>desired</gpr>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<table>
<caption>atomic CAS instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Ordering</th>
<th>Instruction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>relaxed</td>
    <td><mim>amx_cas_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acquire</td>
    <td><mim>amq_cas_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>release</td>
    <td><mim>amr_cas_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
<tr><td>acq_rel</td>
    <td><mim>amz_cas_[u8|u16|u32|u64|u128]</mim></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Using the following procedure, a stream can modify the contents of a memory cell even if there is a possibility that the stream
can be interrupted and replaced by another thread that will update the cell,
or that a thread on another processor can simultaneously modify a cell.
First, an 8-byte number is entirely loaded into the register.
Then, the updated value is computed and placed in another <param>sval</param> register.
Then the <mim>cas_u128</mim> instruction is executed with parameters
<param>test</param> (register number where the initial value),
<param>base</param> (base address register number) and
<param>sval</param> (register number that contains the updated value).
If the modification was completed successfully, the original value will be returned.
If the memory cell doesn't contain the original value
(the current thread was interrupted or the thread of another processor interrupted), the update will not be successful,
general register with the number <param>dst</param> of the instruction <mim>cas_u128</mim> contains the new current value of the memory cell.
If the memory cell doesn't contain an original value, the thread may try to repeat the procedure again using the new current value.
</p>

<code>
loop:
<mim>amx_ld_i64</mim> old, base
<mim>mov</mim> save, test
...
<mim>add_imm_i64</mim> new, old, 12; some kind of modification
...
<mim>amx_cas_u64</mim> found, base, old, new
<mim>br_ne_i64</mim> found, old, loop
</code>

<p>The instruction <mim>cas_u64</mim> can be used for controlled sharing of a common data area,
including the ability to send messages (to a linked message list) when a common area is in use.
To achieve this, an 8-byte number in memory can be used as a control number.
A value of zero indicates that the common area is not in use, and that no messages exist.
A negative value indicates that the area is in use by someone, and that no messages exist.
A positive value indicates that the shared area is in use,
and that the value is the address of the most recent message added to the list.
Therefore, any number of threads wishing to capture a common area,
can use <mim>cas_u64</mim> to update the check number,
to indicate that the area is in use or add messages to the list.
The only thread that has captured the shared area can also safely use <mim>cas_u128</mim> to remove messages from the list.
</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>cas_u128</mim> can be used similarly to <mim>cas_u64</mim>.
Additionally, it has other uses.
Consider a linked data list, with a check number used to address the first message in the list, as described above.
If multiple threads are allowed to delete messages using <mim>cas_u64</mim>
(and not just the only thread that captured the common area), then the list will probably be incorrectly modified.
This can happen if, for example, after one thread reads the address
the very last message to move the message, another thread will delete the first two messages,
and then adds the first message back to the linked list (<quote>ABA</quote> issue in IBM terminology).
The first thread, continuing the interrupted execution, will not be able to determine that the list has changed.
By increasing the size of the control word to a pair of 8-byte numbers,
containing the address of the first message and the modification tag (change number),
which increases by 1 each time the list is modified, and using <mim>cas_u128</mim> to update both fields together,
the possibility of incorrect list updating can be reduced to an insignificant level.
Namely, incorrect modification can occur only if the first stream
was interrupted and during this time the number of changes to the list is exactly a multiple of 2<sup>64</sup>,
and only if the last change to the list uses the original address of the message.
</p>

</section>

<section id="memory_attributes">
<title>Memory attributes</title>


<p>The architecture of any processor needs a simple and effective mechanism for distinguishing memory accesses
and IO operations for IO devices mapped to the address space.
When accessing the memory, it is possible to cache data with a write back, blocking operations with semaphores are allowed,
optimizing reordering of load/store operations and optimizing write-combining(coalescing) of write operations are available.
For operations with mapped IO devices, write through is strictly necessary and cannot be cached,
possible side effects even when reading, you need a strict order (sequential) without permutations/merges.
</p>

<p>In addition, a dedicated, fixed address range must exist in the physical address space for the bootloader code.
It's some analog of the PC EPROM and BIOS.
It contains entry point from which the execution starts after the system restart, and other embedded code,
implementation-dependent (processor-dependent code or PDC) and platform (system-dependent code or SDC).
It is a read-only memory block, although updating may be permitted.
</p>

<p>Memory attributes define speculativeness, cacheability, orderliness, and write policy.
If virtual addressing is enabled, the memory attributes that define the actually displayed physical page are determined by the TLB.
If physical addressing is enabled, memory attributes are determined based on the physical address.
</p>

<p>The software must use the correct address subspaces when using physical addressing.
Otherwise, incorrect access to IO devices with side effects is possible.
</p>

<p>An address range can be either cacheable or non-cacheable.
If the range is <def>cacheable</def>, the processor is allowed to distribute a local copy
corresponding physical memory at all levels of the processor cache hierarchy.
Distribution can be changed by cache management instructions.
</p>

<p>The cached page is memory coherent, i.e. the processor and memory system guarantee
that there is a consistent representation of memory for each processor.
Processors support multiprocessor cache coherence based on physical addresses
between all processors in the coherence domain (tightly coupled multiprocessors).
Coherence doesn't depend on virtual aliases, since they are forbidden.
</p>

<p>The processor is not required to support coherence between local instruction and data caches;
that is, locally, the entry may not be observable by the local instruction cache.
Moreover, multiprocessor coherence is not required from the instruction cache.
However, the processor must ensure that the operations of other IO agents like <quote>Direct Memory Access</quote> (DMA) are physically coherent with a cache of data and instructions.
</p>

<p>For an uncached access, the processor doesn't provide any coherence mechanisms.
The memory system must ensure that a consistent memory representation is seen by each processor.
</p>

<p>When writing to cached memory with <def>write-back</def>,
only the processor-owned local copy of the data cache line changes.
Writing to a lower level cache system (or to the level of the physical arrangement of data in memory)
occurs when a changed cache line is explicitly (or implicitly) pushed out of a higher level cache.
With <def>write through</def> policy, data changes affect all levels of caching immediately.
</p>

<p>For non-cached address ranges, a <def>write-combining</def> (coalescing) can be set,
which tells the processor that multiple writes to a limited memory area (typically 32 bytes) can be
assembled together in the <def>write buffer</def> and made later as one large combined write.
The processor can combine writes for an indefinite period of time.
Several writes can be combined into one large, which accumulates in the buffer.
Write-combining <ndash/> means to increase processor efficiency.
A processor with multiple write buffers should provide the preemptive order,
using buffers approximately the same, even if some buffers are only partially full.
</p>

<p>The processor can flush data from write buffers to memory in any order.
The combined writes aren't performed in the original order.
Write-combining can be either spatial or time-based.
For example, writing bytes 4 and 5 and writing bytes 6 and 7 are combined into a single writing of bytes 4, 5, 6, and 7.
In addition, writing bytes 5 and 6 is combined with subsequent writing of bytes 6 and 7,
into a single write of bytes 5, 6, and 7 (with the removing of the first write to the byte 6).
</p>

<p>The memory attributes may be defined in several ways.</p>

<p>Memory attributes may be defined via special registers at the level of physical address ranges.
In X86 the special <def>memory type range registers</def> (MTRRs) are a set of processor supplementary capability control registers
that provide system software with control of how accesses to memory ranges by the CPU are cached.
It uses a set of programmable model-specific registers (MSRs) which are special registers provided by most modern CPUs.
Possible access modes to memory ranges can be uncached, write-through, write-combining, write-protect, and write-back.
In write-back mode, writes are written to the CPU's cache and the cache is marked dirty, so that its contents are written to memory later.
Write-combining allows bus write transfers to be combined into a larger transfer before bursting them over the bus to allow more efficient writes to system resources like graphics card memory.
This often increases the speed of image write operations by several times, at the cost of losing the simple sequential read/write semantics of normal memory.
Additional bits, added in AMD64, allow the shadowing of ROM contents in system memory (shadow ROM), and the configuration of memory-mapped I/O.
</p>

<p>Memory attributes may be defined at the level of virtual addresses via virtual page properties as an additional part of cached translation info.
Then such per-page memory attributes may redefine previous per-range physical address atributes or restrict them in compatible manner.
</p>

<!--
For <em>virtual</em> memory accesses, physical properties of memory are described by the <regfield>ma</regfield> (<em>memory attributes</em>) field of each virtual translation.
<p>Encoding virtual memory address attributes (incomplete)
</p>
<p>Insert TLB (itc) instruction that attempts to insert stored attributes
memory (Table 4-10) in increasing TLB Saved Register/Region errors.
External system operation is undefined if software inserts
memory attribute supported by the processor but not supported by the external system.

<p>If the software changes the memory attributes for the page,
software should flush any copies of the processor cache for the following changes to the memory attribute:

<p>Speculative/non-speculative, cacheable/uncacheable (for transitions from cacheable to uncacheable), and sequence.
The software should flush any connecting buffers if the page is changed (replaced) from the connection to any other attribute.

<p>It is recommended that processor models report a machine emergency.
Validation terminates if any of the following attribute aliases is detected:
o Connecting a buffer click on a non-connecting page.
o clicking on a cache on a non-cached page, other than as a destination local or remote stream cache (fc) instruction.
-->

<p>Memory attributes may be determined by physical memory mapping only.
In this case, fixed address ranges have specified memory attributes.
Memory attributes are set implicitly during the initial physical address ranges mapping at reset and can't be changed further.
</p>

<p>In the <archname/>, the last way will be choosen.
Memory attributes of physical address ranges are defined from their mapping to corresponding physical adreess ranges.
They can't be redefind further via special registers and/or page properties.
So the physical address space is divided into fixed parts with mmio-like and memory-like address ranges.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Classification of physical addresses</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Addresses</th>
<th>Use</th></tr>
</thead><tbody>
<tr><td>0 to 1 GiB</td><td>mmio-like for compatible devices (not 64-bit ready).</td></tr>
<tr><td>1 to 4 GiB</td><td>memory-like for compatible devices (not 64-bit ready).</td></tr>
<tr><td>4-256 GiB</td><td>mmio-like for 64-bit ready devices</td></tr>
<tr><td>over 256 GiB</td><td>memory-like main space.</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

</section>

<section id="cpu_memory_map">
<title>Memory map</title>

<p>From the system point of view, the physical address space is a bunch of devices, each of which is mapped to continuous address range.
Everything is the memory-mapped device:
memory RAM units are devices, external io devices are naturally memory-mapped devices, even processor cores are memory-mapped devices.
</p>

<p>The bus controller which controls memory mapping is also the memory-mapped device.
The special <quote>device array</quote> device maps all device configuration spaces (similar to PCI root complex).
Each device has 4 KiB configuration space maximum in device array.
</p>

<p>At least one block address in the physical memory map should be fixed in architecture:
starting address in ROM for code execution after reset.
Other blocks layout may be also fixed.
Or may be known from the ROM code.
</p>

<table>
<thead><tr>
<th>start</th>
<th>end</th>
<th>size</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><pre>0x0000000000000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x00000000ffffffff</pre></td><td>4GiB</td><td>reserved</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre>0x0000000100000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x00000001000fffff</pre></td><td>1MiB</td><td>chipset control</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre>0x00000001f0000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x00000001ffffffff</pre></td><td>256MiB</td><td>ROM</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre>0x0000000200000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x00000002ffffffff</pre></td><td>4GiB</td><td>PCIE ECAMs (16x256MiB)</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre>0x0000004000000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x0000004fffffffff</pre></td><td>64GiB</td><td>PCIE BARs</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre>0x0000010000000000</pre></td><td><pre>0x000003ffffffffff</pre></td><td>2TiB</td><td>RAM</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The memory map should be consistent with memory attributes.
Chipset control, PCIE config spaces, memory-mapped io: should be mapped to mmio-like ranges.
Memory devices: should be mapped to memory-like ranges.
ROM devices: may be both, but the startup ROM should be memory-like.
</p>

</section>

<section id = "cpu_memory_related_instructions">
<title>Memory-related instructions</title>

<p>Instructions to clear the cache <mim>icbf</mim> (<miname>instruction cache block flush</miname>)
and <mim>dcbf</mim> (<miname>data cache block flush</miname>) supplant the entire contents of the write buffers,
whose addresses are no more than 32 bytes from the aligned address (at the boundary of 32 bytes),
specified by <mim>icbf</mim> or <mim>dcbf</mim>, forcing the data to become visible.
The <mim>icbf</mim> and <mim>dcbf</mim> instructions may also preempt additional write buffers.
</p>

<p>Instruction without parameters <mim>msync</mim> (<miname>memory synchronize</miname>) <ndash/>
this is a hint for the processor to speed up the flushing out of all pending (buffered) stores, regardless of their addresses.
This makes pending entries visible to other memory agents.
</p>

<p>There is no way to know when the preemption of writes will be completed.
The ordering of joined records is not guaranteed, so that later writes may occur before previous writes.
To ensure that preceding linked entries are made visible before later entries,
software must serialize between entries.
</p>

<p>The processor can at any time flush connected writes to memory in any order before the software explicitly requires it.
</p>

<p>Pages that allow writes to be joined are not necessarily coherent with write buffers or caches of other processors, or with local processor caches.
Downloads to connected pages of memory by the processor see the results of all previous writes by the same processor in the same connected page of memory.
Memory calls made by a connecting buffer (such as buffer streams) have an unordered non-sequential memory ordering attribute.
</p>

<p>The MMGR family includes instructions for working with special registers, barrier instructions,
cache management, dynamic procedure calls, interprocess communication, etc.
</p>

<slot_table>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <cacheopx>opx</cacheopx>
    <jump>uimm28</jump>
</slot>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <cacheopx>opx</cacheopx>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <binimm>simm21</binimm>
</slot>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <cacheopx>opx</cacheopx>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <scale>scale</scale>
    <indexed_opx>opx</indexed_opx>
    <idisp>simm7</idisp>
</slot></slot_table>

<p>The second register contains the base address (only the address register).
The rest of the instruction is reserved for storing the displacement, a 7-bit signed number.
Formulas to get the effective address:</p>

<p><reg>ip</reg> + 16 <times/> sign_extend(label23)</p>
<p>gr [base] + sign_extend(disp)</p>
<p>gr [base] + (gr [index] <lshift/> scale) + sign_extend(disp)</p>

<p>Instructions ECB (Evict cache block), FETCH (Prefetch data), FETCHM (Prefetch data, modify intent), WH64 (Write hint 64 bytes)
regulate the use of cache resources.</p>

<p>FETCH - load the block into the cache for reading N times (if N=0, then free the block).
</p>

<p>FETCHM - load a block into the cache for modification N times (if N=0, then push the block out of the cache into memory).
</p>

<!--
<p>Any issued operation or instruction of a barrier, force - data was connected,
to become visible before the instruction itself becomes visible.</p>
-->

</section>

</chapter>
