<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="predication">
<title>Predication</title>

<preface>
</preface>

<section id="isa_predication">
<title>Conditional execution of instructions</title>

<p>The architecture defines a model in which the control flow is passed to the next sequential instruction in memory,
unless otherwise directed by a jump instruction or interrupt.
The architecture requires the program to appear that the processor is executing instructions in the order
in which they are located in memory, although in reality the order can be changed inside the processor.
The instruction execution model described in this chapter provides a logical representation of the steps involved in executing the instruction.
The branch and interrupt sections show how flow control can be changed during program execution.
</p>

<p>If the branch direction is incorrectly predicted, the branch instruction causes the pipeline to stop.
All speculatively launched instructions are reset from the fetch stage to the stage of writing results <ndash/> for almost the entire length of the pipeline.
</p>

<p><def>Predication</def> is a conditional execution of instructions.
The purpose of conditional execution is to remove badly predicted branches from the program.
In this case, any instruction becomes a hardware-executed conditional branch operator.
For example:
</p>

<p>if (a) b = c + d.</p>
<p><mim>add</mim> (a) b = c, d</p>

<p>The optional argument <quote>a</quote> (<def>predicate</def>) sets the logical condition <ndash/> to execute the instruction or not.
This technology replaces a control dependency with a data dependency and shifts a possible pipeline shutdown closer to the pipeline end.
All instructions issued with a false value of the predicate are rejected at the completion stage (retire) or earlier (up to the decode stage) without interruptions.
</p>

<p>The instruction predication may be explicit or implicit.
With <def>explicit</def> predication, each instruction contains an additional argument <ndash/> a one-bit predicate register,
and, accordingly, the architecture contains a file of several predicate registers (16 predicates in the ARM-32 architecture, 64 in Intel-Itanium).
</p>

<p>When <def>implicit</def> predication, the architecture contains a special register-mask for storing information about the conditionality of the execution of future instructions.
Before executing the instruction, the first bit from this register is taken as its predicate.
Then the register is shifted by one bit, while the current bit is lost. The subsequent instruction takes the second bit as the predicate.
The register is constantly updated from the other end with <quote>clean</quote> bits corresponding to unconditionally executed instructions.
</p>

<p>Some instructions may write data to this register, thereby canceling the unconditional execution of some future instructions according to the bitmask.
These are the so-called <def>nullification instructions</def>.
For example, using mask 0b10011 containing 3 1-bits, the 3 instructions (1, 2, and 5th) after the nullification instruction will be canceled.
</p>

<p>The advantage of conditional execution is the elimination of most branches in short conditional calculations, and hence the pipeline stops.
However, this is a purely power method, which boils down to simultaneously issuing instructions from several execution branches under different predicates on the pipeline.
In addition, when explicitly predicting, a place in the instruction is required to explicitly encode the optional argument <ndash/> the predicate register.
</p>

<p>Predication is more suitable for short conditional calculations.
It makes no sense to apply predication for loops, or conditional statements longer than the gain from the continuous operation of the pipeline without branches.
However, it is the only means of removing downtime for poorly predictable branches (for example, a conditional branch depending on unpredictable data).
</p>

<p>An implicit predication scheme was chosen for the <archname/> architecture.
This is due to the fact that according to statistics collected for other architectures where there is a predication,
approximately 90% of instructions are executed without using predication, so spending several bits for the predicate in each instruction is not profitable.
On the other hand, the remaining 10% of the instructions depend on unpredictable data and, without predication, introduce a significant delay in the pipeline operation.
Therefore, architecture without predication will also be suboptimal.
</p>

<p>The special field <reg>psr.future</reg> is used to control the nullification of the subsequent instructions.
The least significant bit of the register corresponds to the current instruction, other bits correspond to the subsequent instructions.
At the end of the instruction, a right shift occurs.
In the case of the branch, the future mask is completely cleared, thereby canceling all possible established nullifications.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of nullification instructions</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <ignored size="18">nullification condition</ignored>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Based on the condition of nullification (for different instructions consists of 2 registers, or register and shift, or register and immediate value)
either the next <quote>n-yes</quote> instructions are nullified or the next <quote>n-no</quote> subsequent instructions (after first block <quote>n-yes</quote> instructions) are nullified in the <reg>psr.future</reg>.
</p>

<p>The following are examples of removing branches from short conditional statements and the corresponding use of nullification.
In all cases, the management dependency is converted to data dependence and masking for future instructions.
Everywhere it is assumed that the calculation of conditions gives side effects in the form of possible exceptional situations and should occur strictly predictively.
If there can be no side effects in the form of exceptional situations, then, naturally,
the calculation of a difficult condition can be done without predication and reduce unnecessary manipulations.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Schematic examples of using predication</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Conditional statement</th>
<th>Predication</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1) {x1; }
else {x2; }</code>
</td>
<td>
<code>c1 c1yes, c1no
x1 (c1no)
x2 (c1yes)</code>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1) {
 x1;
 if (c2) x2;
 else x3;
 x4;
} else {
 x5;
 if (c3) x6;
 else x7;
 x8;
}</code>
</td>
<td>
<code>c1 c1yes, c1no
x1 (c1no)
c2 c2yes, c2no (c1no)
x2 (c1no, c2no)
x3 (c1no, c2yes)
x4 (c1no)
x5 (c1yes)
c3 c3yes, c3no (c1yes)
x6 (c1yes, c3no)
x7 (c1yes, c3yes)
x8 (c1yes)</code>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1) {x1;
} else if (c2) {x2;
} else if (c3) {x3;
} else {x4;
}</code>
</td>
<td>
<code>c1 c1yes, c1no
c2 c2yes, c2no (c1yes)
c3 c3yes, c3no (c1yes, c2yes)
x1 (c1yes)
x2 (c2yes)
x3 (c3no)
x4 (c3yes)</code>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1 &amp; &amp; c2) {x1; }
else {x2; }
</code>
</td>
<td>
<code>c1 c1yes, c1no
c2 c2yes, c2no (c1no)
x1 (c1no, c2no)
x2 (c2yes)</code>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1 || c2) {x1;
} else {x2;
}</code>
</td>
<td>
<code>c1 c1yes, c1no
c2 c2yes, c2no (c1yes)
x1 (c2no)
x2 (c1yes, c2yes)</code>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<code>if (c1 || (c2 &amp; &amp; c3)) {
 x1;
} else {
 x2;
}</code></td>
<td> <code>c1 (p0) p2, p3
c2 (p3) p4, p5 (unc)
c3 (p4) p2, p3
x1 (p2)
x2 (p3)</code></td></tr>
<tr><td> <code>if (c1 &amp; &amp; (c2 || c3)) {
 x1;
} else {
 x2;
}</code></td>
<td> <code>c1 (p0) p2, p3
c2 (p2) p4, p5 (unc)
c3 (p5) p4, p5 (unc)
x1 (p4)
x2 (p3)</code>
</td></tr>

</tbody>
</table>
</section>

<section id = "nullification_insn">
<title>Nullification Instructions</title>

<p>Nullification instructions mark in the special field <reg>psr.future</reg> the fact that the execution of the subsequent instructions was canceled.
Nullification instructions create mask of 1s for nullified instruction for if or else block, and or them with current future mask.
Nullification instructions assume that the <quote>if</quote>-block precedes the <quote>else</quote>-block.
</p>

<p>Next instructions cancel future instructions depending on the result of comparing two registers.
</p>

<table>
<caption>reg-reg nullification instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Instruction</th>
<th>Operation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><mim>nul_eq_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ne_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if not equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_lt_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if signed less</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ge_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if signed greater or equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_lt_[u32|u64|u128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if unsigned less</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ge_[u32|u64|u128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if unsigned greater or equal</miname></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Nullification instruction format compare-regs</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <branch_opx>opx</branch_opx>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Next instructions cancel future instructions depending on the result
of comparing the register and the 14(40)-bit immediate value, with or without a sign.
The conditions are the same as for compare with immediate and branch instructions.
</p>

<table>
<caption>reg-imm nullification instructions</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Instruction</th>
<th>Operation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><mim>nul_eq_imm_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ne_imm_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if not equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_lt_imm_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if less</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_lt_imm_[u32|u64|u128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if less unsigned</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ge_imm_[i32|i64|i128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if greater or equal</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_ge_imm_[u32|u64|u128]</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if greater or equal unsigned</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_mask_all</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if mask all bit set</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_mask_any</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if mask any bit set</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_mask_none</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if mask none bit set</miname></td></tr>
<tr><td><mim>nul_mask_notall</mim></td><td><miname>nullify if mask not all bit set</miname></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of nullification instructions compare-with-immediate</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <cbimm>imm11</cbimm>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <imm size="29">imm40 (11+29)</imm>
    <reserved size="13">0</reserved>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Instructions <mim>nul_bs</mim> (<miname>nullify if bit set</miname>)
and <mim>nul_bs_imm</mim> (<miname>nullify if bit set immediate</miname>)
cancel future instructions depending on whether or not a bit is set in the register.
</p>

<p>Analogous instructions <mim>nul_bc</mim> (<miname>nullify if bit clear</miname>)
and <mim>nul_bc_imm</mim> (<miname>nullify if bit clear immediate</miname>)
cancel future instructions depending on whether or not a bit is clear in the register.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Nullification instruction format <mim>nul_[bs|bc]</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <branch_opx>opx</branch_opx>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of nullification instructions <mim>nul_[bs|bc]_imm</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <bitpos>shift</bitpos>
    <branch_opx>opx</branch_opx>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Floating-point scalar values may be checked for nullification.
Two registers may be compared.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of nullification instructions fp compare</caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>ra</gpr>
    <gpr>rb</gpr>
    <branch_opx>opx</branch_opx>
    <nmask>dist-no</nmask>
    <nmask>dist-yes</nmask>
    <nullify_opx>opx</nullify_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id="nulllification_in_assembler">
<title>Nullification in assembler</title>

<p>Assembler eliminates the need to manually set predication distances.
You can use named markers whose distances are computed automatically.
General syntax:
</p>

<p><mim>INSTRUCTION NAME</mim> regular_parameters (pred1, pred2, pred3, ...)</p>

<p>The predicate list indicates in which previously defined predicate instruction this instruction is the last in if or else-block.
These predicates should be mentioned in previous nullification instructions
no higher than 31 instructions from the current one for <quote>yes</quote> predicate and 63 instructions from the current one for <quote>no</quote> predicate.
</p>

<code>write    "test nullification (explicit distances)"
ld_imm   %r10, 0
nul_eq_i64  %r10, %r10, 5, 4
write    "0" ; nullified in 5
write    "1" ; nullified in 5
write    "2" ; nullified in 5
write    "3" ; nullified in 5
write    "4" ; nullified in 5
write    "5" ; nullified in 4
write    "6" ; nullified in 4
write    "7" ; nullified in 4
write    "8" ; nullified in 4
</code>

<code>write    "test nullification (predicate names)"
ld_imm      %r10, 0
nul_eq_i64    %r10, %r10, equal, nonequal
write    "0"
write    "1"
write    "2"
write    "3"
write    "4" (equal)
write    "5"
write    "6"
write    "7"
write    "8" (nonequal)
</code>

<p>Both variants print <quote>5 6 7 8</quote> (4 instructions else-block)
and avoid printing <quote>0 1 2 3 4</quote> (5 instructions if-block) due to predication.
</p>

<p>The else-block may be empty if both <quote>yes</quote> and <quote>not</quote> distances refer to same instruction (dist_yes == dist_not).
To create zero-length else-block, the last instruction of if-block should be marked as last for else-block also.
To create zero-length if-block, the nullification instruction itself should be marked as last in if-block.
</p>

<p>In the next sample all 3 subsequent instructions will be nullified, because nullification condition is true.
And there is no else-block.
Both markers of block ends <quote>(equal)</quote> and <quote>(nonequal)</quote> are on same instruction.
</p>

<code>nul_eq_i64    r10, r10, equal, nonequal
write    "0"                     ; part of equal-block
write    "1"                     ; part of equal-block
write    "2" (equal, nonequal)   ; part of equal-block
</code>

<p>In the next example all 3 subsequent else-block instructions will be executed, because nullification condition is false,
and if-block for true nullification condition isn't presented.
The <quote>(equal)</quote> marker or if-block is set just on predication instruction, so the size of if-block is zero - the distance from end of block to nullification instruction.
</p>

<code>nul_eq_i64    r10, r12, equal, nonequal (equal)
write    "0"                ; part of nonequal-block
write    "1"                ; part of nonequal-block
write    "2" (nonequal)     ; part of nonequal-block
</code>

</section>

</chapter>
