<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<preface>
<title>The <archname/> architecture</title>

<p>This document describes the architecture of a non-existent <em>virtual</em> processor.
The processor instruction set architecture and the processor itself are referred to as <strong><archname/></strong>.
This name is because <quote>POST-RISC</quote> is a common name for projects of hypothetical processors,
replacing processors with the RISC architecture (Reduced Instruction Set Computer).
The virtual processor <archname/> combines the best (as it seems to me) qualities of existing and past architectures.
</p>
<p>Main features of the <archname/> architecture:
</p>
<ul>
<li><em>fixed</em> format based on packed bundles of instructions</li>
<li>a large number of universal registers (128) of 128 bits, for deep loop <em>unrolling</em> and <em>rescheduling</em></li>
<li><em>register rotation</em> (implemented a general-purpose hardware circular buffer)</li>
<li><em>load/store</em> architecture with strong data alignment restrictions</li>
<li>implicit <em>predication</em> (all instructions allow conditional execution under the control of predicate mask)</li>
<li><em>fused operations</em> (<quote>multiply-add</quote>, shift with addition or subtraction,
indexed with scaling and memory access, compare and branch, addition with compare and branch)</li>
<li><em>position independent code</em> only</li>
<li><em>vector</em> SIMD-like instructions (128-bit universal registers can be used as vectors of integers or real numbers)</li>
<li>hardware implementation of 128-bit (quadruple) floats</li>
<li>additional hardware protection against software vulnerabilities</li>
</ul>

<p>Sources are available at <link href="https://github.com/bdpx/postrisc">https://github.com/bdpx/postrisc</link>.
This documentation XML sources are available at <link href="sources.html">sources.html</link>.
</p>

<p>This repository contains source code, sample programs for <archname/>, this description of the virtual processor.
To build programs you need cmake and g++, to build this documentation from xml xsltproc.
The <strong>postrisc</strong> is a console application for all basic tasks.
Uses standard streams for input/output that need to be redirected from file or to file.
It is called with different keys from the command line (table below).
Additional parameters are set in the <quote>postrisc.ini</quote> file.
The <strong>qtpostrisc</strong> is a graphical application with assembler editor, debugger, etc (Qt5 required).
</p>

<table>
<thead><tr>
<th width="40%">Command line options</th>
<th>Operation description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>scan &lt; <param>source.s</param></strong></td>
<td>scan and recognize individual tokens (tokens) of the source program in assembler virtual processor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>scanhtml &lt; <param>source.s</param></strong></td>
<td>scan and mark as html source program in assembler virtual processor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>assemble &lt; <param>source.s</param> &gt; <param>source.bin</param></strong></td>
<td>assemble the program <param>source.s</param> in the object file <param>source.bin</param></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>assemble_c &lt; <param>source.s</param> &gt; <param>source.cpp</param></strong></td>
<td>assemble the program <param>source.s</param> in the file <param>source.cpp</param> as an array for implementation in a C++ program
(for an emulator being implemented in another program)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>disasm &lt; <param>source.bin</param></strong></td>
<td>disassemble the file <param>source.bin</param></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>dumpbin &lt; <param>source.bin</param></strong></td>
<td>disassemble the <param>source.bin</param> file with binary representation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>execute &lt; <param>source.bin</param></strong></td>
<td>execute the program <param>source.bin</param> in the emulator</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong><minus/><minus/>html &gt; <param>out.html</param></strong></td>
<td>output html-text with information about the syntax of assembler instructions, the format of machine instructions, operation codes, statistics for the instruction set</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>If this tutorial on instruction architecture and assembler syntax doesn't exactly match the sample program (not yet updated),
then this file contains a complete list of instructions automatically generated by the assembler.
</p>

<p>
<link href="gen.html">gen.html</link>
</p>

<p>Example program for assembler <archname/>:
</p>

<p>
<link href="program.html">program.html</link>
</p>

<p>This program does nothing sensible but uses all machine instructions and pseudo-instructions of assembler, all sections of the program, all addressing modes,
and its only meaning is joint testing of assembler, disassembler, emulator in the process of writing them.
</p>

<p>The author is grateful in advance for reporting errors and inaccuracies in the virtual processor description and in the source code (which is far from error-free).
</p>

<p>A set of tools for working with <archname/> (assembler, disassembler, emulator is implemented)
not complete and incomplete (no macro processor, linker, debugger, no compiler).
Further directions for improvement (the number in brackets like [2] characterizes the comparative complexity of the tasks):
</p>

<ol>

<li>Development of a <em>set of sample programs</em> to illustrate the capabilities of the virtual processor and assembler <archname/> [1].
</li>

<li>Development of a <em>macroprocessor</em> for the assembler <archname/>[3].
</li>

<li>Refactoring the <em>formula calculation unit</em> to introduce strict control over the use of object names in formulas
(according to sections and segments of the program and the relocation types) [2].
</li>

<li>Development of the <em>object file format</em> for a virtual processor compatible with the ELF standard, processing assembler for ELF [2].
</li>

<li>Development of <em>separate compilation tools</em>,
support for relocation records according to the ELF standard (Executable and Linkable Format) in assembler and the development of the linker [2].
</li>

<li>Development of the <em>block of floating-point calculations</em> in the emulator (implemented), and support for real constants in assembler [3].
</li>

<li>Development of a <em>visual debugger</em> for the emulator <archname/> [2].
</li>

<li>Development of a <em>text editor</em> with syntax highlighting of the assembler virtual processor [2].
</li>

<li>Adding new <quote>hardware</quote> tools to the virtual processor architecture and its emulator:
cache management, virtual memory and translation buffer [2].
</li>

<li>Development of a <em>simulator</em> (cycle-accurate emulator) of the possible hardware implementation of a virtual processor,
with the simulation of hardware such as multi-level instruction/data caches,
translation buffers, branch prediction cache, return prediction stack, and other modern hardware. [5]
</li>

<li>Development of a <em>target description</em> for the back-end compiler code generator
GCC (GNU Compiler Collection), which includes a description of the architecture of the virtual processor
<archname/> according to the rules used by GCC MD (machine description), and a set of specialized functions for code generation,
(Requires knowledge of the basics of GCC, the MD syntax for GCC, the principles of extending GCC to new architectures)
or back-end development for the LLVM compiler. [6]
</li>

</ol>

</preface>
