<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="register_stack">
<title>The register stack</title>

<preface>
</preface>

<section id="register_rotation">
<title>Registers rotation</title>

<p>Traditionally (in most architectures) the register file is a global resource, where all registers are visible to all program procedures.
If the procedure wants to use a register, the contents of this register must be stored in memory, and later restored from memory.
The work of saving/restoring registers is usually divided between the procedure that makes the call (<em>caller</em>) and the one that is called (<em>callee</em>).
For example, the first 14 registers out of 32 existing may be required to save caller, then the remaining 18 registers must save callee.
The optimal split depends on the processor architecture: the number of registers and their universality (orthogonality),
and for new architectures it is usually determined experimentally by comparing the code effectiveness for different variants,
based on the analysis of a statistically large codebase.
</p>

<p>Within one procedure, you can optimize the use of registers well,
but in the case of several procedures, and especially if they are compiled separately, the use of register resources becomes suboptimal.
A typical example of extreme inefficiency is recursive procedures.
Even if the recursive procedure uses only one of the N available registers,
each recursive call to such a procedure wants to use exactly <em>this</em> specific register,
therefore, this register is repeatedly spilled/filled, despite the presence of many unused registers.
</p>

<p>Summing up these arguments, we can say that a significant percentage of all memory accesses are the operations of spilling/filling registers,
which in essence are not related to useful work.
This fraction is not very dependent on the total number of registers due to the binding of the procedure code to specific registers.
So an increase in the number of registers, although it helps to improve the efficiency of large and complex procedures, doesn't help in any way to reduce inter-procedure save and restore registers.
This proportion grows with an increase in the number of procedures and a decrease in their average size (as is usually the case for object-oriented programming languages).
</p>

<p>The solution to this problem is to implement hardware <def>registers rotation</def>.
The registers is no more global resource.
Each procedure called gets its own working subset of registers.
The registers saving/restoring is not required while the registers working set of several called procedures fits in the register file.
</p>

<p>For example, in the <archname/> architecture, a file of 128 general-purpose registers is divided into two subsets:
up to 120 rotable or stackable registers <reg>r0</reg> - <reg>r119</reg> (locally visible only to the current procedure)
and 8 static registers <reg>g0</reg> - <reg>g3</reg>, <reg>tp</reg>, <reg>fp</reg>, <reg>sp</reg>, <reg>gz</reg> (globally visible to all procedures).
The mechanism of the register stack is implemented through the circular renaming of registers as a side effect of procedure calls and returns from procedures.
The renaming mechanism is not visible to the program.
There 128 rotate registers in the hardware circular buffer, which allows an easy way to cyclically calculate the remainder.
In total, the general-purpose logical file of registers has 136 (128 + 8) registers, of which up to 128 maximum are simultaneously available to the program.
</p>

<p>Static registers must be maintained and restored at the procedure boundary in accordance with programmatic conventions (APIs).
Stackable registers are automatically saved and restored by the corresponding hardware mechanism without the explicit participation of the program.
All other register files are visible for all procedures and must be saved/restored programmatically in accordance with program agreements.
</p>

<table width="96%">
<caption> General Purpose Registers (Hardware Model)</caption>
<thead> <tr>
<th width="85%" colspan="25">circular register buffer (128)</th>
<th width="15%">Global (8)</th>
</tr></thead> <tbody>
<tr>
<td class="imm" colspan="8" width="32%">local A</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="17" width="68%">not available</td>
<td class="tdb"> global</td>
</tr> <tr>
<td class="tdz" colspan="6" width="24%">not available</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="7" width="28%">local B</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="12" width="48%">not available</td>
<td class="tdb"> global</td>
</tr> <tr>
<td class="tdz" colspan="11" width="44%">not available</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="5" width="20%">local C</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="9" width="36%">not available</td>
<td class="tdb"> global</td>
</tr> <tr>
<td class="imm" colspan="5" width="20%">local D (cont)</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="9" width="36%">not available</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="11" width="44%">local D</td>
<td class="tdb"> global</td>
</tr> <tr>
<td class="tdz" colspan="4" width="16%">not available</td>
<td class="imm" colspan="8" width="32%">local E</td>
<td class="tdz" colspan="13" width="52%">not available</td>
<td class="tdb"> global</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>The above diagram shows the process of using the hardware buffer of local rotate registers.
Five procedures A, B, C, D, E call each other, pass call arguments through the register buffer, place their local variables in the buffer.
As the hardware circular buffer is exhausted (in procedure D), the registers are flushed onto the stack in memory and the buffer is reused from the beginning.
Of course, not the entire buffer is discarded, but the necessary count to create a new frame.
</p>

<table width="85%">
<caption> Register buffer (dividing into parts, looped back)</caption>
<tr>
<td class="opx" colspan="10"> clean</td>
<td class="qpr" colspan="30"> dirty</td>
<imm size="24"> local</imm>
<td class="spr" colspan="14"> invalid</td>
<td class="opx" colspan="10"> clean</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>In general, the register buffer contains the following five parts (order matters):
</p>

<table>
<caption>Register ring buffer parts</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Part</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>clean</td>
<td>these registers belong to inactive frames and have already been flushed to the stack in memory,
but have not yet been used by other frames (if there is an advanced reset of registers to memory or advanced recovery from memory)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>dirty</td>
<td>these registers belong to inactive frames and have not yet been flushed to the stack in memory
(obligatory dumping to memory is required before using under other frames)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>local</td>
<td>these are local registers of the active frame</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>invalid</td>
<td>is garbage left over from past procedure calls, or registers that have never been used
(can be used to expand the current active frame, to create a new active frame,
or to expand the zone of clean-registers when returning from procedures or when reading registers from memory ahead of time)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<table width="86%">
<caption>General purpose registers (visible to the program model)</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th width="85%" colspan="20">Local (120)</th>
<th width="15%">Global (8)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><imm size="8" width="40%">local A</imm><reserved size="12">not available</reserved><td class="tdb">global</td></tr>
<tr><imm size="7" width="35%">local B</imm><reserved size="13">not available</reserved><td class="tdb">global</td></tr>
<tr><imm size="5" width="25%">local C</imm><reserved size="15">not available</reserved><td class="tdb">global</td></tr>
<tr><imm size="16" width="80%">local D</imm><reserved size="4">not available</reserved><td class="tdb">global</td></tr>
<tr><imm size="8" width="40%">local E</imm><reserved size="12">not available</reserved><td class="tdb">global</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>Each procedure <quote>sees</quote> only its local registers, and the first physical local register is visible under the logical number <reg>r0</reg>.
</p>

<p>The diagram below shows an example of working with the register stack.
First, we have a register frame for the current function of 17 registers (<reg>r0</reg> - <reg>r16</reg>).
The last 5 of them (<reg>r12</reg> - <reg>r16</reg>) the function uses to place the parameters for calling the next function.
The return address when calling will fall into the first register parameter (<reg>r12</reg>),
as well as the number of stored registers and output frame size (12, 5) - these two numbers can be packed together with return address in link register.
This register number for the return address, as the boundary between the stored registers and the output parameters, is indicated in the call instructions.
</p>

<p>After the call, the second function has at its disposal a register frame of 5 registers.
The return address is visible in the register <reg>r0</reg>.
Then the second function expands its register frame to the required number of registers for local computing (up to 10 registers).
</p>

<p>After completion of work, the second function restores the saved part of the frame of the first function, and gives the parameter registers back to it.
The number of registers to be returned is indicated in the instructions for returning from the function,
and, according to ABI, it must match the number of incoming parameter registers.
</p>

<table width="75%">
<thead><tr>
<th>physical numbering</th>
<th>caller function registers</th>
<th>callee registers immediately after the call (input parameters)</th>
<th>callee extends the register frame</th>
<th>caller registers after returning</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td class="gpr">0</td>
<reserved rowspan="4">are hidden</reserved>
<reserved rowspan="16">are hidden</reserved>
<reserved rowspan="16">are hidden</reserved>
<reserved rowspan="4">are hidden</reserved></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">1</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">2</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">3</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">4</td><td class="gpr">r0</td><td class="gpr">r0</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">5</td><td class="gpr">r1</td><td class="gpr">r1</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">6</td><td class="gpr">r2</td><td class="gpr">r2</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">7</td><td class="gpr">r3</td><td class="gpr">r3</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">8</td><td class="gpr">r4</td><td class="gpr">r4</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">9</td><td class="gpr">r5</td><td class="gpr">r5</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">10</td><td class="gpr">r6</td><td class="gpr">r6</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">11</td><td class="gpr">r7</td><td class="gpr">r7</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">12</td><td class="gpr">r8</td><td class="gpr">r8</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">13</td><td class="gpr">r9</td><td class="gpr">r9</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">14</td><td class="gpr">r10</td><td class="gpr">r10</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">15</td><td class="gpr">r11</td><td class="gpr">r11</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">16</td><td class="gpr">r12</td><td class="gpr">r0</td><td class="gpr">r0</td><td class ="gpr">r12</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">17</td><td class="gpr">r13</td><td class="gpr">r1</td><td class="gpr">r1</td><td class ="gpr">r13</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">18</td><td class="gpr">r14</td><td class="gpr">r2</td><td class="gpr">r2</td><td class ="gpr">r14</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">19</td><td class="gpr">r15</td><td class="gpr">r3</td><td class="gpr">r3</td><td class ="gpr">r15</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">20</td><td class="gpr">r16</td><td class="gpr">r4</td><td class="gpr">r4</td><td class ="gpr">r16</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">21</td>
<reserved rowspan="10">not available</reserved>
<reserved rowspan="10">not available</reserved><td class="gpr">r5</td>
<reserved rowspan="10">not available</reserved></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">22</td><td class="gpr">r6</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">23</td><td class="gpr">r7</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">24</td><td class="gpr">r8</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">25</td><td class="gpr">r9</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">26</td><reserved rowspan="5">not available</reserved></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">27</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">28</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">29</td></tr>
<tr><td class="gpr">30</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>special register <regname>register stack control</regname> (<reg>rsc</reg>) stores information about the status of the circular register buffer,
and the current active frame of local general purpose registers.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption> Register format <reg>rsc</reg></caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="32">0</reserved>
    <bitfield size="8">ndirty</bitfield>
    <bitfield size="8">soc</bitfield>
    <bitfield size="8">bof</bitfield>
    <bitfield size="8">sof</bitfield>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>Four fields hidden from direct access store the positions and sizes of register portions local to the rotation buffer.
Their sizes depend on the implementation (register ring buffer size), except for <regfield>sof</regfield> whose size is always 7 bits.
So, for example, for a buffer of 128 registers, the number of bits for each position is 7, for 256 is 8.
Field <regfield>sof</regfield> (size of frame) is the size of the last active frame (possibly empty),
Field <regfield>bof</regfield> (bottom of frame) is the position in the buffer of the beginning of the last active frame and border with the <em>dirty</em> section,
Field <regfield>soc</regfield> (size of clean) is the size of the <em>clean</em> section,
The <regfield>ndirty</regfield> field is the number of <em>dirty</em> registries.
</p>

<p>The special <regname>register stack pointer</regname> (<reg>rsp</reg>) contains the memory address,
where the next local register should be saved when the hardware circular register buffer is full.
Since the address must be aligned on an 16-byte register size boundary for register spilling/filling,
then the lower 4 bits of the register <reg>rsp</reg> are always zero, the writing them is ignored.
A specific architecture implementation can spill/fill the registers in aligned groups of 2-16 registers at a time to optimize the work with memory,
so the additional least significant bits of the register may be fixed as zero.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Register format <reg>rsp</reg></caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="58">address</imm>
    <reserved size="2">0</reserved>
    <reserved size="4">0</reserved>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>In the Berkeley RISC research project, where register rotation was first applied (?), only eight of the 64 existing registers were visible to the program.
A full set of 64 registers is called the <em>register file</em>, and a portion of eight <ndash/> <em>register window</em>.
The file allows up to eight procedure calls with their own sets of registers.
Until the program calls a chain longer than eight calls, the registers never had to be stored in RAM,
which is scary slow compared to register access.
For many programs, a chain of six calls is enough.
</p>

<p>A direct descendant of the RISC Berkeley project is Sun Microsystems' SPARC (UltraSPARC) architecture. Compared to the prototype,
this processor provides the simultaneous visibility of four sets of eight registers each (has 32 simultaneously visible registers).
Of these, 8 are global and 24 are windowed.
Three sets, eight registers each, are implemented as a <quote>register window</quote>.
The eight registers <reg>i0</reg><hellip/><reg>i7</reg> are input to the current procedure,
eight registers <reg>l0</reg><hellip/><reg>l7</reg> are local to the procedure of the current level,
and eight registers <reg>o0</reg><hellip/><reg>o7</reg> are the output for calling the next level procedure.
When a new procedure is called, the register window shifts to sixteen registers,
hiding old input registers and old local registers,
and making the output registers of the current procedure the input registers of the new procedure.
Additionally, eight registers <reg>g0</reg><hellip/><reg>g7</reg> are globally visible to procedures at all levels.
</p>

<p>The size of the frame and the number of output registers, unfortunately, are fixed in SPARC.
It's also bad that flashing registers pushed from the stack into memory is implemented through interrupts,
and the fact that the dumping place is not separated from the regular stack of automatic objects.
</p>

<p>In the AMD 29000 architecture (64 global and 128 window visible registers), the register rotation design was further refined with variable-sized windows,
which helps resource utilization in the general case, when fewer than eight registers are needed to call the procedure.
A <em>second</em> separate stack for saving registers was also implemented.
</p>

<p>Register rotation was used in the architecture of Intel 80960 (i960) processors for embedded applications
(32 visible registers, of which 16 global and 16 windowed, with a fixed rotation step of 16 registers).
</p>

<p>The last (of implemented) known processor that uses register rotation is <em>Intel Itanium</em> (IA64 architecture).
It has 128 registers, of which 32 are static and 96 are windowed.
It is possible to set a frame of any size from 0 to 96 registers with any number of output registers.
To spill registers into memory without processor interrupting, an asynchronous hardware mechanism is implemented.
The spill occurs on a separate (second) stack, which grows towards the main stack and is not visible to the user program explicitly.
Both stacks share the same memory array.
</p>

<p>The rotation of the registers is also applied in the new architecture of the educational processor MMIX,
which replaced the legacy MIX processor in examples for new editions of Donald Knuth's book <quote>The Art of Programming</quote>.
MMIX architecture has a register file of 256 registers visible to the program, allows using the variable window size of visible registers,
and even allows to change the boundary between the global and rotate registers visible to the program dynamically,
which is usually not used in real architectures.
</p>

</section>

<section id="call_instructions">
<title>Call/return instructions</title>

<p>Because the <archname/> architecture uses hardware register rotation,
then the call/return instructions execution is closely related to the operation of the circular buffer of local registers.
When the procedure is called, the current frame of local registers is partially saved,
when returning from the procedure, the previous frame is restored.
</p>

<p>The <archname/> may be extended in the future by big-SIMD facilities (256 or even 512 bit) using register pairs/groups for SIMD.
Such SIMD register pairs/groups shouldn't cross a register frame boundary.
The register frame base (bottom of frame) and the preserved frame size should be a multiple of register pair/group (2 or 4) to guarantee SIMD register pairs/groups alignment.
The link info may be stored only in the even (or multiple 4) register to guarantee register pairs alignment.
Currently, only 2-register alignment is required for frame size.
</p>

<p>Procedure call instructions <mim>call</mim>, <mim>call_ri</mim>, <mim>call_mi</mim>, <mim>call_rvt</mim>, <mim>call_plt</mim> perform similar actions.
They vary by way of computing the target call address only.
</p>

<p>The first argument for all call instructions is the register in which the return address and other link info will be stored.
All local registers starting from <reg>r0</reg>  with lower numbers up to it exclusively will be hidden after the register window rotation.
All local registers, starting from the register specified in the instructions and with greater numbers,
that are currently allocated will become the initial frame of the new procedure.
</p>

<p>Then, the branch effective address is calculated (differently for different instructions).
The return address along with the current frame info is stored in the return register.
</p>

<p>Then the register window is rotated, the frame of local registers is partially saved, and the branch to the target address is performed.
The new procedure always sees its return address and previous frame info in the first rotated register <reg>r0</reg>,
and the input parameters in the following registers <reg>r1</reg>, <reg>r2</reg> ...
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Link register format <reg>r0</reg></caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="60">return address</imm>
    <reserved size="2">0</reserved>
    <imm size="2">rs</imm>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="32">preserved caller future</imm>
    <imm size="18">eip offset</imm>
    <imm size="7">out-size</imm>
    <imm size="7">framesize</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>If the call instruction is the last in the bundle,
call instruction saves the return address as a pointer to the <strong>next bundle</strong> after the current bundle,
and and the stored slot number <regfield>rs</regfield> is set to zero.
If the call instruction isn't the last in the bundle, then the current bundle address and the next slot number <regfield>rs</regfield> were saved.
</p>

<p>In the general case, return to middle of bundle may be less optimal but saves code size.
The processor anyhow fetch and execute whole bundle, but discards execution of first <regfield>rs</regfield> slots.
If the slot number points in the middle of a double-slot instruction then fault triggers.
For better performance, the bundle before call instruction may be filled with dummy <mim>nop</mim> instructions to shift call instruction to the end of bundle.
There is corresponding compiler option to choose between <quote>dense</quote> and <quote>aligned</quote> calls.
</p>

<p>For example, dense calls:</p>

<code>ld_imm %r33, 1234    ; r33 is future r1 (param for myfunc)
call %r32, myfunc    ; r32 is future r0 (link info)
call %r32, myfunc2
call %r32, myfunc3
</code>

<p>For example, aligned call:</p>

<code>ld_imm %r33, 1234    ; r33 is future r1 (param for myfunc)
nop   0
call %r32, myfunc    ; r32 is future r0 (link info)
; this is next bundle and aligned return address
add_i64 %r34, %r12, %r12    ; next instruction after return from myfunc
sub_i64 %r14, %r22, %r11
</code>

<table>
<caption>Instructions for calling procedures, managing the register frame and the regular stack</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Instruction</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td><pre><mim>call</mim>     dst,label</pre></td><td><reg>ip</reg>-relative call</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>call_ri</mim>  dst,base,index</pre></td><td>call register indirect</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>call_mi</mim>  dst,base,simm14</pre></td><td>memory-indirect call, base addressing</td></tr >
<tr><td><pre><mim>call_rvt</mim> dst,base,simm14</pre></td><td>memory-indirect call, word, base relative addressing</td></tr >
<tr><td><pre><mim>call_plt</mim> dst,uimm28</pre></td><td>call procedure linkage table: indirect, relative addressing</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>alloc</mim>    framesize</pre></td><td>allocate register stack frame</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>alloc_sp</mim> framesize,uimm21</pre></td><td>allocate register stack frame, update SP</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>ret</mim></pre></td><td>return from the subroutine</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>retf</mim>    uimm21</pre></td><td>return from the subroutine, update SP</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>The instruction <mim>call</mim> makes a procedure call using <reg>ip</reg>-relative addressing using 28-bit immediate signed offset.
This gives the maximum distance of the <formula><plusmn/>2</formula> GiB to both sides of the current position for a one-word instruction.
A long form of instruction is also implemented.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>call</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <jump>simm28x16</jump>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<extslotbits/>
<slot>
    <reserved size="10">0</reserved>
    <imm size="32">simm60x16 (28+32)</imm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>EA = <reg>ip</reg> + 16 <times/> simm</p>
<p>call (EA)</p>

<p>Instruction <mim>call_ri</mim> (<miname>call register indirect</miname>) is the address of the procedure call from the register.
The branch address is calculated as <param>base</param> plus <param>index</param>.
The <mim>call_ri</mim> instruction discards the 4 least significant bits of the address, so the call address is always aligned at the beginning of the bundle.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>call_ri</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>index</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>EA = (<param>base</param> + <param>index</param>) &amp; mask {63:4},</p>
<p>call (EA)</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>call_mi</mim> (<miname>call memory indirect</miname>) takes the callee address from memory using base+displacement addressing.
The instruction discards the 4 least significant bits of the loaded value, so that the address always aligned with the beginning of the bundle is always obtained.
The instruction is intended to load from address table with aditional checks for finalized state of virtual page.
The vtables should be relocated by linker and set as finalized to disable future access rights changes (hardware-assisted one way relro).
The 14-bit displacement is enough to support vtables (or other function pointer tables) with up to 1024 64-bit items.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>call_mi</mim>, <mim>call_rvt</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <mid_binimm>simm14(56)</mid_binimm>
    <fused_opx>opx</fused_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>EA = <param>base</param> + sign_extend(simm14)</p>
<p>EA = mem8 (EA)</p>
<p>EA = EA &amp; mask {63:4},</p>
<p>call (EA)</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>call_rvt</mim> (<miname>call relative vtable</miname>) takes the callee relative offset from memory using base+displacement addressing.
This offset is used to compute callee address relative to base address.
The instruction discards the 4 least significant bits of the loaded value, so that the address always aligned with the beginning of the bundle is always obtained.
The instruction is intended to load from address table with aditional checks for finalized state of virtual page.
The vtables should be relocated by linker and set as finalized to disable future access rights changes (hardware-assisted one way relro).
The 14-bit displacement is enough to support vtables (or other function pointer tables) with up to 2048 32-bit items.
</p>

<p>EA = <param>base</param> + sign_extend(<param>simm14</param>)</p>
<p>offset = mem4(EA)</p>
<p>EA = (<param>base</param> + offset) &amp; mask {63:4},</p>
<p>call (EA)</p>

<p>The <mim>call_plt</mim> instruction (<miname>call procedure linkage table</miname>) takes the address of the call from memory using <reg>ip</reg>-relative addressing.
The instruction discards the 4 least significant bits of the loaded value, so that the address always aligned with the beginning of the bundle is always obtained.
The instruction is intended to load from address table with aditional checks for finalized state of virtual page.
The import tables should be relocated by linker and set as finalized to disable future access rights changes (hardware-assisted one way relro).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>call_plt</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <call>uimm28</call>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>EA = ip + zero_extend(uimm28)</p>
<p>EA = mem8 (EA)</p>
<p>EA = EA &amp; mask {63:4},</p>
<p>call (EA)</p>

<p>The <mim>ret</mim> and <mim>retf</mim> instructions (<miname>return from subroutine</miname>) is used to return control from the procedure.
It also restores the caller procedure register window state, and <mim>retf</mim> roll-back fixed-size stack frame.
</p>

<p>Unlike other branch instructions, these instructions may use special hardware structures to predict the destination branch address.
If the prediction array <em>branch target buffer</em> is generally used for branch address prediction,
then for <mim>ret</mim> instructions it can be additionally (for better prediction accuracy) implemented hardware <em>branch target stack</em> as a short stack of saved return addresses.
</p>

<p>While restoring the previous frame state the <mim>ret</mim> instructions may load part or all of the previous frame from memory if necessary
(when the circular hardware register buffer overflows).
Instruction may return control until a complete recovery from memory is completed, but the architecture guarantees
that attempts to use not yet recovered from memory local registers in the subsequent instructions
will be delayed until recovery is performed (via the scoreboard mechanism of the registers).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>ret</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>retf</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <binimm>uimm21 (63)</binimm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The link register is implicit argument for both ret instructions.
It is the first current function local register and provides the return address and the previous frame info.
The argument for <mim>retf</mim> is the displacement which is used for the optional stack rollback (maybe be 0).
The instruction may cause an error if link register contains a broken frame info
and there is no place in the local registers for the outgoing and preserved frame parts of the previous procedure
since the maximum frame size is 120 registers.
</p>

</section>

<section id="frame_allocation">
<title>Register frame allocation</title>

<p>Each callee procedure after call obtains the remaining frame part of the calling procedure starting from the link register(the parameters and maybe slightly more).
If callee wants to increase the size of its register frame it should use the <mim>alloc</mim> (<miname>allocate register stack frame</miname>) instruction.
The first parameter of the instruction is local register, which will be the last in the frame of our procedure (from <reg>r0</reg> to <reg>r119</reg>).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>alloc</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <framesize>framesize</framesize>
    <res21>0</res21>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>If there is not enough free space in the rotate registers hardware buffer to accommodate a new frame,
the <mim>alloc</mim> instruction flushes registers from the previous functions frames onto the register stack in memory.
The instruction can return control before a complete flush is completed, but the architecture guarantees
that attempts by the subsequent instructions to use local registers not yet flushed to the stack
will be delayed until the flush (through the scoreboard mechanism of the registers).
</p>

<p>The new <reg>eip</reg> is set up from <reg>reip</reg>.
The <reg>reip</reg> should point to simple universal function epilog with just ret instruction.
This epilog should live in the highest corresponding usermode/kernel region.
The <reg>reip</reg> should be set up during thread start.
</p>

<p>The next minimum program for a virtual processor
demonstrates the use of the <mim>call</mim>, <mim>alloc</mim> and <mim>ret</mim> instructions.
</p>

<code>.text
; at the beginning of the program, the register stack is empty
<mim>alloc</mim>  54   ; expand frame to 54 registers
<mim>eh_adj</mim>  endfunc
<mim>ld_imm</mim>   %r47, 1  ; will be saved when called
<mim>ld_imm</mim>   %r53, 3  ; first argument
<mim>ld_imm</mim>   %r52, 2  ; second argument
<mim>ld_imm</mim>   %r51, 1  ; third argument
; func procedure call, all registers up to 50 will be saved,
; return address, eip, frame size (50) are saved in r50
<mim>call</mim>  %r50, func
; at this point, after returning, the frame will be again 54
<mim>halt</mim>
func:
; at the starting point, the func procedure has a 4-register frame
; their previous numbers are 50, 51, 52, 53, new - 0, 1, 2, 3
; extend the frame to 10 registers (plus regs 4,5,6,7,8,9)
<mim>alloc</mim>  10
<mim>write</mim>  "r0 = %x128(r0)"    ; print packed return info
<mim>write</mim>  "r1 = %i64(r1)"    ; print 1st argument
<mim>write</mim>  "r2 = %i64(r2)"    ; print 2nd argument
<mim>write</mim>  "r3 = %i64(r3)"    ; print 3rd argument
<mim>ret</mim>
endfunc:
.end</code>

<p>Result of execution:
</p>

<code>r0 = 000000010000c232_fffffffff1230020
r1 = 1
r2 = 2
r3 = 3
</code>

<p>Here:
0xfffffffff1230020 - return bundle address,
0x0000c232 - packed: previous frame size (50 registers), and output frame size (3 parameters and link),
offset between return address and previous eip exception return address (endfunc label).
0x00000001 - previous future mask, nonzero because <mim>call</mim> is a middle from 3 instructions in the bundle, so we return to the bundle middle and skip one instruction.
</p>

<p>The instruction <mim>alloc_sp</mim> is introduced for code compression.
Its function similar to <mim>alloc</mim>, but additionally it push usual stack.
The <mim>alloc_sp</mim> adiust <reg>sp</reg> down by immediate size.
</p>

<code><mim>alloc</mim>    framesize
<mim>alloc_sp</mim> framesize, uimm21</code>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>alloc_sp</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <raopx>opx</raopx>
    <framesize>framesize</framesize>
    <binimm>uimm21 (63)</binimm>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id="function_plolog_epilog">
<title>The function prolog/epilog</title>

<p>The type of prolog/epilog depend on:</p>

<ul>
<li>if instructions inside function may generate software/hardware exceptions</li>
<li>if function need to allocate local registers</li>
<li>if function need to allocate fixed-size stack frame</li>
<li>if function need to allocate fixed-size stack frame more than pagesize</li>
<li>if function need to extend stack frame with variable size (using variable length arrays or alloca function)</li>
</ul>

<p>In the examples below r1<hellip/>r5 are arguments, and r6<hellip/>r10 are optional local registers.
The frame stack grows from up to down addresses.
</p>

<p>The simplest function which doesn't allocate local registers (uses arguments only) and doesn't allocate stack frame.
All instructions inside function don't generate software/hardware exceptions (never touch memory, divide, etc).
Then it's enough just:
</p>

<code><mim>insn</mim>    # can't fail, can use only args r1..r5
...
<mim>insn</mim>    # can't fail, can use only args r1..r5
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>The next function can generate software/hardware exceptions but doesn't allocate local registers (uses arguments only) and doesn't allocate stack frame.
Here in case of exception control can be transferred to <reg>eip</reg>, so we need proper <reg>eip</reg> before execution.
</p>

<p>The special register <reg>reip</reg> is introduced to not blow code with multiple copies of standard universal epilog which consists from only ret instruction.
It stores the address of such epilog.
The proper initialization of <reg>reip</reg> to avalable standard universal epilog is at runtime at thread start.
</p>

<p>Each call instruction setup <reg>eip</reg> by <reg>reip</reg> copy, so we won't worry about proper <reg>eip</reg> just after call.
So even if instructions may fail, we don't need additional setup at function start.
</p>

<code><mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use only args r1..r5
...
<mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use only args r1..r5
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>The next function doesn't allocate stack frame but allocate local registers.
The alloc instruction here does the local registers allocation.
The register allocation may trigger register spilling to memory so may fail and trigger hardware exception.
But again, because <reg>eip</reg> stores the copy of <reg>reip</reg>, we won't worry about <reg>eip</reg>.
</p>

<code><mim>alloc</mim>   11
<mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use r1..r5 and r6..r10
...
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>The next function allocates local registers and allocates the fixed-size stack frame.
In this case we need to set new eip before execution to the label before return for proper traditional stack unwinding.
The stack frame should be no bigger than pagesize, so we don't touch next page after the stack guard page.
</p>

<code><mim>st_i64</mim>     %gz, %sp, -frame_size_immediate # touch new stack frame
<mim>alloc_sp</mim> 11, frame_size_immediate
<mim>eh_adj</mim>   before_return   # immediately after alloc_sp
...
<mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use r1..r10
<mim>ld_u32</mim>    %r7, %sp, +offset # using sp for local frame addressing
...
before_return:
<mim>add_imm_i64</mim>    %sp, %sp, frame_size_immediate
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>The next function allocates local registers and allocates the fixed-size stack frame.
The stack frame is bigger than pagesize so proper guard-page extension via store probing is required.
</p>

<code># guard page probing for frame size bigger than pagesize
<mim>st_i64</mim>     %gz, %sp, -page_size * 1
<mim>st_i64</mim>     %gz, %sp, -page_size * 2
...
<mim>st_i64</mim>     %gz, %sp, -page_size * n
# allocation only after probing
<mim>alloc_sp</mim> 11, frame_size_immediate
<mim>eh_adj</mim>   before_return   # immediately after alloc_sp
...
<mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use r1..r10
<mim>ld_u32</mim>    %r7, %sp, +offset # using sp for local frame addressing
...
before_return:
<mim>add_imm_i64</mim>    %sp, %sp, frame_size_immediate
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>The before_return block:</p>

<code>...
before_return:
<mim>add_imm_i64</mim>    %sp, %sp, frame_size_immediate
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

<p>may be changed to one <mim>retf</mim> instruction:</p>

<code>...
before_return:
<mim>retf</mim>    frame_size_immediate
</code>

<p>and, if there is a space in previous bundle, then <mim>retf</mim> may be copied into it,
and before_return block may be potentially amortized once for several functions with same frame size:
</p>

<code>...
<mim>retf</mim>    frame_size_immediate
before_return:
<mim>retf</mim>    frame_size_immediate
</code>

<p>The next function allocates local registers and allocates stack frame with variable size
(uses variable length arrays or alloca function) possibly with initial size more than pagesize.
In this case we have 2 rollback points:
for the case of failure in local register alocation, and for the case of failure in initial stack alocation.
The <reg>sp</reg> can't be used for access local stack frame (because of variable frame size),
so some local temp register is used to save/restore old sp value (<reg>r6</reg> in example) with negative offsets.
</p>

<code># optional guard page probing for frame size bigger than pagesize
<mim>st_i64</mim>    %gz, %sp, -page_size * 1
<mim>st_i64</mim>    %gz, %sp, -page_size * 2
...
<mim>st_i64</mim>     %gz, %sp, -page_size * n
# allocation only after probing, r6 is allocated on the fly
<mim>alloc_sp</mim> 11, initial_frame_size_immediate
<mim>add_imm_i64</mim>    %r6, %sp, initial_frame_size_immediate
<mim>eh_adj</mim>   before_return   # immediately after saving fp in r6
...
<mim>insn</mim>    # can fail, can use r1..r10
<mim>ld_u32</mim>    %r7, %r6, -offset # using r6 for local frame addressing

# alloca or VLA
# optional guard page probing for big frame size
<mim>st_i64</mim>    %gz, %sp, -page_size * 1    
<mim>st_i64</mim>    %gz, %sp, -page_size * 2
...
<mim>st_i64</mim>    %gz, %sp, -page_size * m
# allocation only after probing
<mim>sub_i64</mim>    %sp, %sp, additional_frame_size
# end of alloca or VLA

<mim>st_i32</mim>    %r7, %r6, -offset # using r6 for local frame addressing
...
before_return:
<mim>mov</mim>    %sp, %r6
<mim>ret</mim>
</code>

</section>

<section id="register_stack_system_management">
<title>The register stack system management</title>

<p>One <mim>alloc</mim> instruction, along with instructions for calling procedures and returning control,
in principle, it is enough for user programs to handle the register stack.
But for system programs that handle interrupt processing, returning from an interrupt,
context switching, initialization of the register stack, some more instructions are needed.
</p>

<p>Instruction without parameters <mim>rscover</mim> (<miname>register stack cover frame</miname>) is used,
to put the last (active) frame of the register stack into the <em>dirty</em> state
(registers belonging to inactive procedure frames).
After executing this instruction, the size of the active frame of the local registers is zero.
This instruction prepares the register stack for subsequent disconnection or switching.
</p>

<p>Instruction without parameters <mim>rsflush</mim> (<miname>register stack flush</miname>)
used to flush all inactive frames of the register stack into memory
(transfer from the <em>dirty</em> state to the <em>clean</em> state).
After executing this instruction, the register stack can be disabled without fear of data loss.
</p>

<p>Instruction without parameters <mim>rsload</mim> (<miname>register stack load</miname>)
used to load from memory the last inactive frame of the register stack and be ready to activate it.
After executing this instruction, the register stack is ready to work (a group of <em>clean</em> registers appears in it).
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>rscover</mim>, <mim>rsflush</mim>, <mim>rsload</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <noargs>opx</noargs>
</slot>
</slot_table>

</section>

<section id="calling_convention">
<title>Calling convention</title>

<p>ABI defines a standard relationship function relationship, namely
stack frame location, using registers, passing parameters.
</p>

<p>The standard function call convention applies only to global functions.
Local functions (not available from other object files) may be used by other
agreement unless it prevents the correct recovery after an exception.
</p>

<p>Convention about the use of registers in standard function calls
divides all the global registers available to the program into two categories:
<em>saved</em> (preserved) and <em>non-saved</em> (scratch) registers.
</p>

<p>preserved registers are guaranteed to be saved when the procedure is called.
The called procedure (callee) guarantees the safety of the contents of such a register
with a normal return from it. She either doesn't touch this register, or saves it
contents somewhere and restores before returning.
</p>

<p>Unsaved (scratch) registers may not be saved when a procedure is called.
The calling procedure (caller) must store the contents of such a register in memory (on the stack)
or in another, but persistent register, if it doesn't want to lose its contents when calling callee.
The callee function called uses this register for its needs without restriction.
</p>

<p>The architecture provides 128 general purpose registers of 128 bits,
and several 64/128 bit special purpose registers.
General purpose registers are divided into global (static) and rotatable.
The following table shows how registers are used.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Saving registers when calling procedures</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>registers</th>
<th>volatility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>sp</td><td><regname>stack pointer</regname> is saved.
The address of the top of the stack must be aligned on a 16-byte boundary.
It should always point to the last placed stack frame, growing down in the direction of lower addresses.
The contents of the word at this address always points to a previously placed stack frame.
If required, may be reduced by the called function.
The stack top pointer must be updated atomically with a single instruction to avoid any period of time in which the interrupt can
happen with a partially updated stack.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>tp</td><td><regname>thread pointer</regname> is saved.
This register stores the base address of the TDATA segment of the main program module.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>r0</td><td>communication register, saved automatically by the rotation mechanism of the registers.</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>r1-r32</td>
<td>Used to pass parameters to the called function (not saved).
Registers r1 and r2 store the return value.
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Static registers g0-g7 must retain their values in the process of accessing the function.
Functions that use these registers must save their values before changing, and restore them before returning from the function.
</p>

<p>External signals can interrupt the flow of instructions at any time.
Functions called during signal processing do not have any special restrictions on their use of registers.
In addition, when the signal processing function returns control, the process resumes its work with correctly restored registers.
Therefore, programs and compilers are free to use all registers above except
reserved for use by the system without fear of signal processing programs that inadvertently change their values.
</p>

<p>The operating system provides each thread with its own stack, in which data is placed on both sides.
The stack of rotated registers grows from the bottom towards the higher addresses, work with it under the control of the equipment and is not visible to ABI.
The usual stack of software local objects grows from top to bottom towards lower addresses.
Each frame (frame) corresponds to an activation record of a procedure in a call chain.
The stack pointer <reg>sp</reg> (stack pointer) always points to the first byte after the top of the stack.
The stack frame should be aligned at the 16-byte boundary, and should be a multiple of 16 bytes in size.
</p>

<p>The last function in the call chain, which itself doesn't call anyone, may not have its own frame.
Such functions are called leaf or terminal (in the graph of dependencies between functions).
All other functions must have their own stack frame in the dynamic stack.
The following figure shows the organization of the stack frame.
<reg>sp</reg> in the figure means the pointer (register r1) of the top of the stack
the called function after it has executed the code setting the stack frame.
</p>

<p>Stack frame organization</p>

<pre>highest address

        + -> Frame header (return address, gp, rsc)
        | Register storage area (aligned on the boundary of 16 bytes)
        | Local variable space (aligned on the boundary of 16 bytes)
sp ---> + - The title of the next frame (sp + 0)

lowest address
</pre>

<p>The following requirements apply to the stack frame:</p>
<ul>
<li>The pointer to the top of the stack should always be aligned on a 16-byte boundary.</li>
<li>The pointer to the top of the stack should point to the beginning of the most recently placed stack frame <ndash/>
8-byte number of <quote>return address</quote>. The stack should grow down towards lower addresses.</li>
<li>The first 8-byte number of the stack frame should always point to the previously allocated frame (in the direction of the older addresses) of the stack,
except for the first frame of the stack, which must have a null pointer.</li>

<li>Pointer to the top of the stack, if required,
should be reduced by the called function in its prolog and restored before returning.</li>

<li> Before a function calls another function,
it must save the value of the register <reg>lp</reg> in the storage area for the return address.</li>

<li> Some space below the stack top may be available as volatile storage (<def>red zone</def>), which is not saved when the function is called.
Interrupt routines and any other functions that can be performed without an explicit call should take care to guard this region.
If the function doesn't need more stack space than is available in this area, then it doesn't need to have its own stack frame.</li>
</ul>

<p>The header of the stack frame consists of a pointer to the previous frame (link info),
storage areas <reg>rsc</reg>, <reg>lp</reg> and <reg>gp</reg>, resulting in 32 bytes.
Link info always contains a pointer to the previous frame in the stack.
Before function B refers to another function C, it must save the contents of the communication register received from function A in the storage area <reg>lp</reg>
for the stack frame of function A, and must set its own stack frame.
</p>

<p>Except for the header of the stack frame and inserts for alignment at the 16-byte boundary,
the function should not allocate space for areas that it doesn't use.
If the function doesn't call other functions and doesn't require anything from the rest of the stack frame, then it should not set the stack frame.
The parameter saving area follows the stack frame, the register saving area should not contain any inserts.
</p>

<p>For machines of the RISC type (where there are many registers) it is generally more efficient to pass arguments to the called functions in the registers (real and general purpose),
rather than constructing a list of arguments in memory or pushing them onto the stack.
Since all calculations must somehow be performed in registers,
then extra memory traffic can be eliminated if the caller can calculate the arguments in the registers and pass them in the same registers of the called function (callee),
and she can immediately use them for its calculations.
The number of arguments that can be passed in this form is limited by the number of available registers in the processor architecture.
</p>

<p>For <archname/>, up to 16 parameters are passed in general registers and are visible in the callee new frame in registers r1<hellip/>r16.
The caller passes parameters starting from any register.
Exact register number on the caller side depend on caller local frame size.
</p>

<p>Parameter storage area, which is located at a fixed distance of 32 bytes from the pointer to the top of the stack,
reserved in each frame of the stack for use under the argument list.
A minimum of 8 double words is always reserved.
The size of this area should be sufficient to preserve the longest list of arguments passed to the function if it owns a stack frame.
Although not all arguments for a particular call are in storage,
consider their list formation in this area, with each argument occupying one or more double words.
</p>

<p>If more arguments are passed than are allowed to be stored in registers, the remaining arguments are stored in the parameter storage area.
Values passed through the stack are bitwise identical to those that would be placed in registers.
</p>

<p>For variable argument lists, the ABI uses the type <var>va_list</var>,
which is a pointer to the location in memory of the next parameter.
Using the simple va_list type means that variable arguments should always
stay in the same location despite the type, so that they can be found at runtime.
This ABI defines the location, which is the common registers r8-r18
for the first eight double words and the parameter storage area on the stack for the rest.
Alignment requirements, such as for real types, may require
so that the va_list pointer is pre-aligned before accessing the value.
</p>

<!--
<p>Rules for passing parameters:</p>

<li> Each argument is projected onto how many double words the parameter save area,
because you want to keep its value.

<li> Single values an exact floating-point are projected onto the first word in a single double word.

<li> Double precision floating-point values are projected onto a single double word.

<li> The extended exact float values are projected onto two consecutive double words.

<li> Simple integer types (char, short, int, long, enum) are projected onto a single double word.
Values that are shorter than a double word expand signally or unsignedly if necessary.

<li> Complex floating-point and compound integer types are drawn map as if
the argument was specified as separate real and imaginary parts. 

<li> Pointers are projected onto a single double word.

<li> Vectors are projected onto a single quadword, quadword aligned.
This can lead to missing double words in the parameter save area.

<li> Corrected aggregates of size and union passed by value,
are projected onto how many double words of the parameter storage area,
since the value is used in memory.
Aggregrates and pools will align according to their alignment requirements.
This can lead to double words being skipped for alignment. 

<li> An aggregate or a smaller union than a double word in size padded in this way
that it appears in the lower digits of the double word.
All others padded, if necessary, in their tail.
Volatile aggregates of size or pool pass by help. 

<li> Other scalar values are projected onto the number of double words required by their size. 

<li> If callee has a known prototype, the arguments are turned into a kind of corresponding
parameter in front of the drawn map in the parameter save area.
For example, if longer is used as an argument to the double parameter of the float,
the value is converted to double precision and projected onto a double word in the parameter storage area.

<li> floating-point registers f1 through f16 are used sequentially,
to pass up to 16 floating-point values.
Complex values occupy two registers. 
The first 16 of all double words in the parameter storage area,
that the arguments to the floating-point of the map, except for the arguments,
corresponding to the variable part of the callee argument with a prototype containing an ellipsis,
transmitted in floating-point registers.

<li> If there is no known description of an external function for callee,
or if the description of the external function for callee contains an ellipsis (ellipsis <hellip/>) and the value of the argument
not part of the corrected arguments described by the prototype,
then the floating-point and vector values are traversed according to the following rules for non-floating,
non-vector types.
In the case of no known prototype, this could lead to two copies of the floating
and the passing values of the argument vector. 

<li> General registers are used to pass some values.
The first eight double words projected onto the parameter storage area,
correspond to registers from r3 to r10. The argument, except for floating-point and vector values,
fully described by the prototype that maps to this area either in whole or in part,
transmitted in the respective general registers.

<li> All other arguments not already covered (or parts of it) should be remembered
in the parameter storage area following the first eight double words.
The first eight double words projected onto the parameter storage area,
never remembered in the parameter storage area by the call function. 

<li> If callee takes the address of any of its parameters, then the values passed in registers,
stored in the callee parameter storage area.
If the translation unit for the visitor contains a description of the external function, but callee
has a mismatch definition, this can lead to incorrect values being remembered.</p>
-->

<p>The return value of the function. Functions must return type values
<type>int</type>, <type>long</type>, <type>long long</type>, <type>enum</type>, <type>short</type>, <type>char</type>, or pointers to any type,
in register r1, extended to 64 bits (zeros or sign).
</p>

<p>Arrays of characters up to 8 bytes long, or bit strings up to 64 bits long, will be returned in the g8 register, right justified.
Structures or joins of any length, and character strings longer than 8 bytes, will be returned in the storage buffer allocated by the caller.
The caller passes the address of this buffer as a hidden optional argument.
</p>

<p>Functions must return a single real result of type
<type>float</type>, <type>double</type>, <type>long double</type> (quadruple) in the r1 register, rounded to the desired precision.
Functions must return complex numbers in the registers r1 (real part) and r2 (imaginary part), rounded to the desired accuracy.
</p>

</section>

</chapter>

