<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xhtml.xsl"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.example.com/postrisc" id="virtual_memory">
<title>Virtual memory</title>

<preface>

<p>This chapter additionally defines operating system resources to translate 64-bit virtual addresses to physical addresses.
The virtual memory model introduces the following key features that distinguish it from the simplified presentation of application programs:
</p>

<p><strong>Translation lookaside buffer</strong> (TLB) support high-performance paged virtual memory systems.
Software handlers for populating and protecting TLBs allow the operating system to control translation policies and protection algorithms.
</p>

<p><strong>Page table</strong> (PT) with hardware browsing capabilities has been added to increase TLB performance.
PT is a continuation of the processor TLB, which is located in RAM and can be automatically viewed by the processor.
The use of PT, its size, is entirely under software control.
</p>

<p><strong>Sparse 64-bit virtual addressing</strong> is supported by provisioning
large translation structures (including multi-level hierarchies, like a cache hierarchy),
effective support for processing translation misses, pages of different sizes, fixed (non-replaceable out) translations,
mechanisms for sharing TLBs and page table resources.
</p>

<p>The main addressable object in the architecture is an 8-bit byte.
Virtual addresses are 64 bits long.
An implementation may support less virtual address space.
Virtual addresses visible by the program are translated into physical memory addresses by the memory management mechanism.
</p>

</preface>

<section id="mem_virtual_addressing">
<title>Virtual addressing</title>

<p>From an application point of view, the virtual addressing model represents a 64-bit single flat linear virtual address space.
General purpose registers are used as 64-bit pointers in this address space.
</p>

<p>Less than 64 bits of a virtual address may be implemented in hardware.
Unimplemented address bits must be filled with copies of the last implemented bit (be a sign extension of the implemented part of the address).
Addresses in which all unimplemented bits match the last implemented bit are called <def>canonical</def>.
Implemented virtual address space in this case consists of two parts: user and kernel.
For N implemented virtual address bits, the user addresses ranges from 0 to 2<sup>N-1</sup>-1,
and the kernel addresses ranges from 2<sup>64</sup>-2<sup>N-1</sup> to 2<sup>64</sup>-1.
</p>

<p>So, for example, for 48 bits:
</p>

<code>0x0000000000000000 - start of user range
0x00007FFFFFFFFFFF - end of user range
0xFFFF800000000000 - beginning of the kernel range
0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF - end of kernel range</code>

<p>Each virtual address consists of a page table index (1 bit), virtual page number (VPN) and page offset.
The least significant bits form the page offset.
The virtual page number consists of the remaining bits.
Page offset bits don't change during translation.
The border between page offset and VPN in the virtual address changes depending on the page size, used in virtual display.
In the current implementation, 16 Kib page sizes are available, and super pages are multiples of 16 Kib (32 MiB and 64 GiB).
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Virtual address, unimplemented bits, 16 KiB pages</caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="17">sign extension</reserved>
    <imm size="33">virtual page number</imm>
    <imm size="14">16 KiB page offset</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>Switching between physical and virtual addressing modes is controlled by the privileged special register <reg>pta</reg>.
The <regfield>mode</regfield> field sets the page translation mode.
After restarting the processor, this flag is zero.
Virtual addressing is allowed via <regfield>pta.mode</regfield>!=0.
</p>

<table>
<caption>PTA modes</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>pta.mode</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0</td><td>without translation (physical addressing)</td></tr>
<tr><td>1</td><td>reserved</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>2 translation levels</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>3 translation levels</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>4 translation levels</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>A variable page size is needed to help the software display system resources, to improve TLB utilization.
Typically, operating systems choose a small range of page sizes to implement their virtual memory algorithms.
Large pages can be statically distributed.
For example, large areas of virtual addressing space can be allocated to the kernel of the operating system, frame buffers, or mapped IO regions.
The software can also selectively pin these translations by placing them in translation registers.
</p>

<p>Page size can be specified in: translation cache, translation registers, and PT.
Page size can also be used as a parameter for TLB cleanup instructions.
</p>

<p>The page sizes are encoded as a 4-bit field <regfield>ps</regfield> (pagesize).
Each field defines the display size of <formula>2<sup>ps+12</sup></formula> bytes.
</p>

<p>Virtual and physical pages should be aligned on their natural border.
For example, 64 kilobyte pages are aligned at the 64KiB border, and 4 megabyte along the border of 4 megabytes.
</p>

<p>Processors using variable virtual page sizes,
are characterized by the need for hardware implementation of the <strong>fully associative</strong> TLB buffer.
Processors that use only one page size can be bypassed in part by an associative buffer,
although usually fully associative.
</p>

<table>
<caption>Page permissions</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>abbreviation</th>
<th>designation</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>r</td>
<td>read</td>
<td>read access with the usual load/store instructions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>w</td>
<td>write</td>
<td>write access with normal load/store instructions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>x</td>
<td>execute</td>
<td>code execution access</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>b</td>
<td>backstore</td>
<td>saving/restoring registers from the hardware register stack</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>f</td>
<td>finalized</td>
<td>final state, page rights cannot be changed,
gives the right to read addresses for indirect call instructions through trusted import tables and virtual function tables</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>p</td>
<td>promote</td>
<td>the right to elevate privileges of the current thread to the kernel level</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The software can check page level permissions with the instructions <mim>mprobe</mim>, <mim>mprobef</mim>,
which check the availability of this virtual page, privilege level,
read/write permissions at the page level, and read/write permissions with a security key.
</p>

<p>Executable-only pages may be used, to increase privileges on entering operating system code.
User level code should usually go to such a page (managed by the operating system)
and execute the instruction <mim>epc</mim> (<miname>Enter Privileged Code</miname>).
When <mim>epc</mim> has successfully elevated privileges, the subsequent instructions are executed at the target privilege level indicated by the page.
A branch can (optionally) lower the current privilege level if the page where the branch is made has a lower privilege level.
</p>

</section>

<section id="mem_tlb">
<title>Translation lookaside buffers</title>

<p>Virtual addresses are translated to physical addresses using
a hardware structure called Translate Lookaside Buffer (TLB) or translation cache.
Using the virtual page number (VPN), the TLB finds and returns the physical page number (PPN).
A processor usually have two TLB architectural buffers: instruction TLB (ITLB) and data TLB (DTLB).
Each TLB buffer translates, respectively, references to instructions and data.
In a simplified implementation, a single (combined) buffer used for both types of translation can be implemented.
The term TLB itself refers to the union of instructions, data, and translation cache structures.
</p>

<p>When the processor accesses the memory in the TLB, a translation record is searched with the corresponding VPN value.
If the corresponding translation record is found, the physical page number PPN (physical page number) is combined with the page offset bits,
to form a physical address.
In parallel with the translation, page permissions are checked by privilege level and the permissions granted for reading, writing, and executing are checked.
</p>

<p>If the required translation is not found in the TLB, the processor itself can search the page table in memory and install it in the TLB.
If the required input cannot be found in the TLB and/or page table, the processor generates a miss error in the TLB so that the operating system establishes the translation.
In a simplified implementation, the processor may generate an error immediately after a miss in the TLB.
After the operating system installs the translation in the TLB and/or page table, the erroneous instruction may be restarted and execution continues.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Translation format in TLB</caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="50">ppn</imm>
    <bitfield size="2">pl</bitfield>
    <bitfield size="4">ma</bitfield>
    <bitfield>a</bitfield>
    <bitfield>d</bitfield>
    <reserved>0</reserved>
    <bitfield>p</bitfield>
    <bitfield size="3">ar</bitfield>
    <bitfield>v</bitfield>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <imm size="50">vpn</imm>
    <reserved size="8">rv</reserved>
    <bitfield size="6">ps</bitfield>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="40">rv</reserved>
    <imm size="24">asid</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<table>
<caption>TLB translation record fields</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Translation field</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td>v</td><td>Valid bit. If this bit is 1, then translation can be used in the search.</td></tr>
<tr><td>ar</td><td>Global permissions for the virtual page.</td></tr>
<tr><td>p</td><td>Present bit. This bit indicates that the mapped physical page is present in the physical memory and not ejected to disk.</td></tr>
<tr><td>ma</td><td>memory attributes. Describes caching, coherence, writing method, and other attributes of the displayed physical page.</td></tr>
<tr><td>a</td><td>Access bit. This bit may cause an error on access for tracing or debugging purposes. The processor doesn't modify Access bit when referenced.</td></tr>
<tr><td>d</td><td>Dirty bit. There was a write or semaphore instruction on this page.</td></tr>
<tr><td>pl</td><td>Privilege Level or Page Level.</td></tr>
<tr><td>ppn</td><td>Physical page number.</td></tr>
<tr><td>ps</td><td>Page size 2<sup>ps</sup> bytes.</td></tr>
<tr><td>vpn</td><td>Virtual Page Number.</td></tr>
<tr><td>asid</td><td>Address Space identifer.</td></tr>
<tr><td>rv</td><td>Reserved (doesn't exist)</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>TLB is local processor resource (local insertion or clearing of translation entries on one processor doesn't affect the TLB of another processor).
Global TLB cleanup is provided to clean translations in all processors within a coherent TLB region in a multiprocessor system.
</p>

<p><def>Translation Cache</def> (TC) is an implementation-defined structure,
designed to store a small working set of dynamic translations for links to memory.
The processor directly controls the record replacement policy in the TC.
</p>

<p>Purge translation cache <mim>ptc</mim> (<miname>purge translation cache</miname>) produces
cleaning ITC/DTC local processor entries that match the specified range of virtual addresses.
The software should handle the case where cleaning should be extended to all processors in a multiprocessor system.
Flushing the translation cache doesn't affect fixed TC inputs.
</p>

<p>The translation cache has at least 16 inputs for itc and 16 inputs for DTC.
An implementation may have additional levels of a TLB hierarchy to increase efficiency.
</p>

<p>The translation cache is controlled by both software and hardware.
Generally speaking, the software cannot assume how long any installed translation will remain in the cache.
This term, as well as the replacement (extrusion) algorithm, depends on the implementation.
A processor can push translations out of the cache at any given time for various reasons.
TC cleanups can remove more inputs than is explicitly required.</p>

<p>Records in the translation cache must be maintained in a <em>consistent</em> state.
When you insert or clean a TLB, all existing entries must be deleted.
which partially or completely overlap with the given translations.
In this context, <em>overlap</em> refers to two translations with partially or completely overlapping ranges of virtual addressing.
For example: two 64K pages with the same virtual addressing,
or a 128K page with the virtual address <hex>0x20000</hex> and a 64K page with the address <hex>0x30000</hex>.
</p>

<p><def>Translation registers</def> (TR) is part of the TLB, which contain translations whose replacement policies are controlled directly by the software.
Each translation cache entry can be <em>fixed</em> and turned to a software-controlled translation register or unlocked and sent to a common pool.
Fixed translations are not replaced when the TC overflows (but are flushed when overlapping with new translations).
Fixed insert into the previously unfixed TC entry removes the cached translation in this entry.
The software can explicitly embed translations in TR by determining the entry number in the cache.
Translations are deleted from TR when the translation register is cleared, but not when the translation cache is cleared.
</p>

<p>Translation registers allow the operating system to <em>pin</em> critical virtual memory translations into TLB,
for example, IO spaces, kernel memory areas, frame buffers, page tables, sensitive interrupt code, etc.
The interrupt handler instruction fetching is performed using virtual addressing, and therefore,
virtual address ranges containing software translation miss handlers and other critical interrupt handlers should be fixed,
otherwise, additional recursive misses in the TLB may occur.
Other virtual mappings may be pinned for performance reasons.
</p>

<p>Insertion record will be fixed if it is done with the fix bit turned on.
Once such a translation falls into the TLB, the processor will not replace this translation in order to make room for other translations.
Fixed translations can only be deleted by the TLB software cleanup.
Insertions and cleanups of translation registers can selectively delete other translations (from the translation cache).
</p>

<p>A processor must have at least 8 fixed translation registers for itc and 8 for dtc.
An implementation may have additional translation registers to increase efficiency.
</p>

</section>

<section id="mem_page_table_walker">
<title>Search for translations in memory</title>

<p>In case of a miss to the TLB translation hardware cache (lack of the necessary record), an interrupt occurs
and the software miss handler comes into play.
He should find the necessary translation in the page table in memory and place it in TLB,
after which the instruction that caused the interrupt is restarted.
However, many systems contain a hardware (or half-hardware) implemented unit
translations
Then, in case of a miss in TLB, the hardware block for searching for translation in memory comes into play,
and only if this block doesn't detect the desired translation,
an interrupt occurs and a system (software) miss handler is called.
</p>

<p>If the processor implements an automatic search block for translations in memory,
then the format of individual translation records, the format of the translation table as a whole,
and the search algorithm in the translation table ceases to be the free choice of the operating system.
At the same time, the system (owned by the OS) translation structures should work in close cooperation with the hardware translation search unit.
</p>

<p><def>Page Table Walker</def> (PTW) is a hardware unit for
independent search for translations in RAM in case of their absence in the TLB.
PTW is designed to increase the performance of a virtual address translation system.
</p>

<p><def>Page Table</def> (PT) is a translation table in memory,
viewable by the PTW hardware unit (must be configured according to the requirements of the PTW equipment).
</p>

<p>The processor PTW block can be (optionally) configured to search for translation in PT after a failed search in the TLB for instructions or data.
PTW unit provides a significant increase in productivity by reducing
the number of interrupts (and therefore delays and cleanup of the processor pipeline),
caused by misses in the TLB, and by ensuring the parallel operation of the PTW block
to populate the TLB translation cache at the same time as other processor actions.</p>

<p>To organize a page table in memory, traditionally in different architectures, the following schemes are used with varying success:
</p>

<p><strong>top-down</strong> is a traditional multi-level translation search scheme based on direct downward parsing of a virtual address,
when each level of the table tree is directly indexed by the next portion of the virtual address.
The easiest way for a hardware implementation. All tree tables are placed in physical memory.
The number of memory accesses for searching for translation is equal to the number of levels (depth of the tree) - 2 for X86, 3 for DEC Alpha, 4 for X64, 5-6 for IBM zSeries.
It has problems with sparseness and fragmentation, limited support for variable page sizes.
It takes up too much space for translation tables (proportional to the size of virtual memory)
and inefficiently uses table space with large fragmentation.
</p>

<p><strong>guarded top-down</strong> is an improved multi-level translation search scheme based on direct downward parsing of a virtual address,
when each level of the table tree is directly indexed by the next portion of the virtual address, and omissions of some levels are possible.
Harder for hardware implementation. All tree tables are placed in physical memory.
The number of memory accesses for translation search may be less than the maximum number of levels.
Reduces problems with sparseness and fragmentation, limited support for variable page sizes.
</p>

<p><strong>bottom-up</strong> is a scheme of the reverse recursive ascending order of viewing translation tables,
when recursive misses are used in one large linear table located in virtual memory.
Requires hardware implementation of nested interrupts.
The number of memory accesses for searching for a translation depends on the number of recursive misses in the TLB and, at best, is 1,
but in the worst case, it is proportional to the top-down method.
Has problems with sparseness and fragmentation, limited support for variable page sizes.
It takes up too much space for translation tables (in the worst case, it is proportional to the size of virtual memory)
and inefficiently uses table space with large fragmentation.
</p>

<p><strong>inverted hash page table</strong> of pages.
Its size is proportional to the size of physical (rather than virtual) memory and doesn't depend on the degree of fragmentation of virtual space.
The number of memory accesses for translation search doesn't depend on the size of the page table and,
if the hash function is correctly selected and the hash table size is usually 1.
It copes well with sparseness and fragmentation, limited support for variable page sizes.
It caches poorly when looking for translations for neighboring pages.
</p>

<p>In the architecture <archname/>, a multi-level translation search scheme was chosen to implement the page table
based on the direct top-down order of viewing the translation tables,
when each next level is directly indexed by a new portion of the virtual address.
The number of memory accesses for translation search is equal to the number of levels (variable, currently 3 levels).
The page table is located in the physical memory space as a multi-level structure of service tables.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Virtual address: 16KiB pages and possible translation levels</caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="17">sign extension</reserved>
    <imm size="11">11 bits</imm>
    <imm size="11">11 bits</imm>
    <imm size="11">11 bits</imm>
    <imm size="14">16 KiB page offset</imm>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<p>In the event of a miss in the TLB translation hardware cache (lack of the necessary record), the hardware translation search block in memory comes into play,
and if this block doesn't find the required translation, an interrupt occurs and the program miss handler is called.
</p>

<p>Special register <regname>page table address</regname> (<reg>pta</reg>)
defines the search parameters for translation in memory for the virtual space,
describes the location and size of the PT root page in the address space.
The operating system must ensure that page tables are aligned naturally.
</p>

<reg_table>
<caption>Special register <reg>pta</reg> (root level) and translation records for the next levels</caption>
<bits64/>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="16">reserved</reserved>
    <imm size="36">ppn</imm>
    <reserved size="9">0</reserved>
    <bitfield size="3">mod</bitfield>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="16">reserved</reserved>
    <imm size="36">ppn</imm>
    <bitfield size="4">ma</bitfield>
    <reserved size="6">0</reserved>
    <bitfield>s</bitfield>
    <bitfield>v</bitfield>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="16">reserved</reserved>
    <imm size="36">ppn</imm>
    <bitfield size="4">ma</bitfield>
    <reserved size="6">0</reserved>
    <bitfield>s</bitfield>
    <bitfield>v</bitfield>
</reg_row>
<reg_row>
    <reserved size="16">reserved</reserved>
    <imm size="36">ppn</imm>
    <bitfield size="6">ar</bitfield>
    <bitfield>g</bitfield>
    <bitfield>d</bitfield>
    <bitfield>a</bitfield>
    <bitfield>p</bitfield>
    <bitfield>0</bitfield>
    <bitfield>v</bitfield>
</reg_row>
</reg_table>

<table>
<caption>Translation record fields</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Field</th>
<th>Bit</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>mod</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Translation mode: 0 - no translation, 1,2,3 and so on - the number of indexing levels when searching.
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>v</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Bit of validity.
For intermediate and final formats, if 1 - the page entry is valid, otherwise a search error occurs.
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ppn</td>
<td>varied, 30-50</td>
<td>Physical page number if <regfield>p</regfield>=1, or other system data if <regfield>p</regfield>=0.
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>s</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Superpage bit, stop the search (final format instead of intermediate).
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>p</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>The page is in memory
</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>ma</td><td>4</td><td>Page Physical Attributes. Should be defined per superpage.</td></tr>
<tr><td>a</td><td>1</td><td>Access Bit</td></tr>
<tr><td>d</td><td>1</td><td>Dirty bit - indicates whether there were any changes in the page.
When a page is pushed into a swap, it may not be saved if the page is already in the swap and has not changed.
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ar</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>Permissions
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>rv</td>
<td></td>
<td>Reserved (must be zeros)
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The format of the page tables should take into account the mapping of virtual addresses to a physical address space of a total depth of 64 bits.
</p>

</section>

<section id="mem_tlb_instructions">
<title>Translation instructions</title>

<p>List of translation instructions.
The processor doesn't guarantee that the modification of translation resources is observed by subsequent samples of instructions or by accessing data in memory.
The software should provide serialization
(serialization by issuing a synchronizing barrier instruction)
according to instructions before any dependent selection of instructions and serialization according to data before any dependent reference to data.</p>

<table>
<caption>Instructions that modifies TLB</caption>
<thead><tr>
<th>Syntax</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr></thead><tbody>
<tr><td><pre><mim>ptc</mim>     ra,rb,rc</pre></td><td>Purge translations cache</td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>ptri</mim>    rb,rc</pre></td><td>Clear the instruction translation register. ITR <larr/> <param>rc</param>, <reg>ifa</reg></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>ptrd</mim>    rb,rc</pre></td><td>Cleans the data translation register. DTR <larr/> <param>rc</param>, <reg>ifa</reg></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>mprobe</mim>  ra,rb,rc</pre></td><td>Returns page permissions for the privilege level <param>rc</param></td></tr>
<tr><td><pre><mim>tpa</mim>     ra,rb,rc</pre></td><td>Translates the virtual address to the physical address</td></tr>
</tbody></table>

<p>The <mim>ptc</mim> instruction invalidates all translations from the local processor cache specified with the address and ASID.
The processor determines the ASID-specifiec page that contains that address and invalidates all TLB entries for that page.
The instruction deletes all translations from both translation caches that intersect with the specified address range.
If the paging structures map the linear address using a large pages and/or there are multiple TLB entries for that page, the instruction invalidates all of them.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Format of instructions <mim>ptc</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>address</gpr>
    <gpr>asid</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Translation records can be inserted into fixed translation registers by instructions
<mim>set_itr</mim> (<miname>set instruction translation register</miname>) and
<mim>set_dtr</mim> (<miname>set data translation register</miname>).
The data for the inserted translation is taken from the first register argument of the instruction and special registers <reg>ifa</reg>.
The translation register number is taken from the second argument register.
</p>

<p>Translation records can be deleted from translation registers by instructions
<mim>ptri</mim> (<miname>Purge Translation register for Instruction</miname>) and
<mim>ptrd</mim> (<miname>Purge Translation register for Data</miname>).
The first argument is the base address register number, the second argument is the register number that stores the translation register number.
The instructions also delete all translations from both translation caches that intersect with the specified address range.
The instructions only remove translations from the local processor registers.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>set_itr</mim>, <mim>set_dtr</mim>, <mim>ptri</mim>, <mim>ptrd</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>target</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>asid</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Permissions for a virtual page can be specified by instructions
<mim>mprobe</mim> (<miname>memory probe</miname>),
<mim>mprobef</mim> (<miname>memory probe faulting</miname>).
The <mim>mprobe</mim> instruction for a given base address and privilege level returns the available rights mask.
The privilege level is set as a value in the register.
The <mim>mprobef</mim> instruction doesn't return rights, but tests for the necessary access rights for a given base address and privilege level.
If there are no rights, the <mim>mprobef</mim> instruction raises a <error>Data Access rights fault</error> error, otherwise the instruction doesn'thing.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>mprobe</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>pl</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>mprobef</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <regzero>0</regzero>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>pl</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>Privileged instruction <mim>tpa</mim> (<miname>translate to physical address</miname>)
returns the physical address corresponding to the given virtual address.
</p>

<slot_table>
<caption>Instruction format <mim>tpa</mim></caption>
<slotbits/>
<slot>
    <opc>opcode</opc>
    <gpr>dst</gpr>
    <gpr>base</gpr>
    <gpr>asid</gpr>
    <misc_opx_res>0</misc_opx_res>
    <misc_opx>opx</misc_opx>
</slot>
</slot_table>

<p>The common sequence of TLB/PT search looks like this.
If the TLB search fails, if the PTW is blocked (<regfield>pta.v</regfield>=0), a miss error in ITLB/DTLB occurs.
If PTW is enabled (<regfield>pta.v</regfield>=1), then PTW calculates the index for access to the root page table, and tries to find the missing translation in the PT memory,
looking through the table tree.
If additional misses in the TLB occur during PTW operation, PT generates an error.
If the PTW doesn't find the required translation in the memory (that is, the PT doesn't contain it), or the search is interrupted, an instruction/data miss TLB error occurs.
Otherwise, the record is loaded into ITC or DTC.
The processor can upload records to ITC or DTC, even if the program did not require translation.
</p>

<p>Insertions from PT to TC follow the same <quote><em>cleanup rules before inserting</em></quote> as program inserts.
PT insertion of entries that exist in TR registers is not allowed.
Specifically, PT can search for any virtual addressing, but if the address is mapped to TR, such a translation should not be inserted into the TC.
The software should not be placed in PT translations that intersect with current TR translations.
An insert from PT may result in a machine abnormal termination if there is overlap between the TR and the inserted PT record.
</p>

<p>After the translation record is loaded into the TLB, additional translation errors are checked (in order of priority):
lack of rights to the page, enabled access bit, enabled dirty bit, lack of a page in memory.
</p>

</section>

</chapter>
